You're going to think about the design and
implementation of a class for
generating random stories.
This problem is a bit larger than
the ones you have solved so far, so
you will need to think about the methods
that you need and how they work together.
The same ideas that you are used to
from the seven step process will still
guide you through this.
You will not only need to think about the
algorithm, but also the data involved and
how to represent it.
In Java, thinking about the data and
methods guides you through
designing a class.
As always, you want to work the problem
by hand before you do anything else.
You could use a story template like this,
with pencil and paper, by yourself or
with friends.
This template is similar
to one you've seen before.
It uses words and
labels to create an interesting story.
Let's look at how you might create
a story from this template.
This story template starts out my name is,
then the template requires a name.
Remember that a label in angle
brackets requires replacement.
Here we want a name, so
I'll pick my own, Drew.
After that it goes my job is to,
and then we need a verb.
I'll let my friend pick a verb.
>> Ride.
>> And a noun.
>> Dinosaurs.
>> If you have ever seen one of these, you
know that this job is really adjective.
>> Entertaining.
>> Because they are so adjective.
>> Fluffy.
>> Yep, that sounds like a great job to
do when I retire, ride fluffy dinosaurs.
Now, if you started
developing the algorithm for
this random story program, you might end
up with something along these lines.
We read each word, saw if it had
angle brackets around it, and
then if it did,
picked a random word from that category.
If there are no angle brackets,
we just kept the word.
But as always you need to
be careful as it is easily,
easy to mentally gloss over things
that happen naturally for you.
In particular, we picked random words for
each category.
But how did we do that?
More importantly for this problem, how
would you make a computer program do that?
If I ask you to think of an animal,
you can just do it, and
it may seem hard to explain
an algorithm to think of an animal.
As a human,
you just know what animals are.
You implicitly have a mental
list of animals in your head and
can just name one of them.
It may not be truly random, but
maybe you just saw a cat recently or
were thinking about your pet dog.
But picking some animal is easy.
For a computer, however,
you need an algorithm and
it needs to have data to operate on.
The program will need an explicit list of
animals to choose from, which could be
written into the program source code, or
read from a file, or from the internet.
So if you think about these steps, there
was a step that was implicit for you, but
needs to be explicit for the computer.
Making a list of animals.
More generally, making a list for
each template label, not just for animals.
You should also think about this step,
reading each word in a story template.
Where did these words come from?
This should be some sort of input,
like a file or a website.
Your program will need to
read that file or website,
which makes use of familiar classes
like file resource, and URL resource.
You might also notice that some of
these steps are a bit complicated.
Making a list of words in each category
might require more than a few lines of
code, though using a file resource or
URL resource will help.
Picking a random word might also
require some planning and programming.
It is perfectly fine for
your algorithm, and thus your program,
to end up with complicated steps.
These steps may be names of other
methods you will need to write.
For example, you might write a method
to pick a random word from a category.
Suppose the method were
named pickRandomWord.
If you have this method,
the corresponding step in the algorithm
is now just one line of code.
You just call the method pickRandomWord
and it does the work for you.
Working through the algorithm
development helps you figure out what
methods to write.
As you write each of these methods,
you may in turn find you need yet
more methods.
Don't let this worry you,
as you break the large program down into
many smaller problems, the methods you
find you need to write will often be
simpler than the ones you started with.
To make the list of words, you will
need some variable to hold the data.
But how should you store this data?
What type are each of these lists
of words for template labels?
You have seen two types that would work,
an array of strings and
a storage resource.
But neither one is ideal for this problem.
Each of these structures has benefits and
drawbacks.
The StorageResource class is
relatively simple to use.
Your code can add elements
to a StorageResource
without knowing how many
elements are going to be added.
That is, without knowing
the number of colors, or nouns, or
names that will be added.
Accessing StorageResource
elements requires using a for
loop to iterate over all of them.
This will make using an element at
random a little tricky to code.
On the other hand, string arrays have
almost the opposite benefits and drawback.
It's simple to choose
an element at random,
pick a random index less than
the size of the array, and
return that element,
like the element at index two or seven.
However, declaring an array variable
requires knowing how many elements would
be stored.
That makes arrays not
always the right choice.
We could use either a StorageResource or
a string array to implement this program,
but we'll see that a new concept,
the ArrayList, combines the best aspects
of both arrays and StorageResources.
Happy coding!