Hi, we're gonna show an example of
how the array list structure works.
We'll show code that keeps track of how
many times each word in a file occurs.
The file or it could be a URL,
could be a large file,
like text from Shakespeare's Romeo and
Juliet, or like the sayings of Confucius.
We don't know how many different
words there are before we start
reading the file.
So we can't easily use an array.
Instead we'll use two
ArrayList structures.
One that holds strings and
one that holds integer values.
We'll need integer instead of int.
We'll explain why.
The kth value of the array list, whose
name is myFreqs, will store an integer.
The number of occurrences of the kth value
in the instance variable array list,
myWords.
The names are names of instance
variables that we'll see in the code.
As shown here we see two occurrences
of the with a string and an integer
stored in the location with index zero
in the two different array lists.
Similarly there were three
occurrences of the word dog, and
one occurrence of the word green.
Let's write code.
We've got a class, WordFrequencies.
I'm gonna open it up, and
take a look to see how it works.
And one way we can
easily see how it works,
before we look at the code,
is simply to run it.
I've created an instance of
it on my object work bench.
I'm going to right click and
run the tester method.
I'm gonna open the file romeo.txt,
the entire text of Shakespeare's Romeo and
Juliet.
And I can see that there
were 5,895 unique words.
What I like to do with ArrayList is
count how many times each word occurs.
So I'll find out how many
times the occurs Montague,
Capulet, all the words from Romeo and
Juliet.
Just going through this code very quickly
to highlight the key features before I
add the counting.
I have an instance variable, myWords,
which is initialized to be able to
hold strings in the constructor.
In tester, I call the function findUnique.
Which creates a file resource and
because it had no parameters that
allowed me to open up any file I wanted.
It looks over every word,
converts each word to lowercase.
If the word has never been seen before,
which I find out by using the array list
method .indexOf which is a method whose
same name we've seen in the string class.
If it has never been seen,
I add it to my words.
Now what I want to do is
have a parallel array.
I will call it myFreqs,
for my frequencies.
So I need another instance variable.
This has to store integer values,
and unfortunately with array lists
in Java, I must use integer.
You've seen this before
with integer.parseint.
Similar to the class Double.parseDouble,
I'll explain this as I go,
I need to store integers.
I'm going to create a place for it.
I'm going to initialize that
in the constructor to a new
ArrayList of Integer values.
And then If I've never
seen the word before,
that means this is the first occurrence.
So, I'm gonna add to the end
of the array list the value 1.
This is just like the idea of, the first
time you see a word, it's occurred once.
But, if I've seen it before,
this is in my else statement.
If I’ve seen it before I know where
it is because index tells me.
So what I’m going to do is find
the value that’s in myFreqs,
this is the number of times
it’s already occurred.
I can get this value using the get
method and then I can set the value.
In myFreqs, to value +1.
So, let me make clear what
I've just done there.
I've accessed the value at
the location specified by index,
which was returned to me
by the dot index of method.
And the idea here is that if the word the,
occurs in location 500 of my words,
the frequency, or number of times that
occurs is in location 500 of myFreqs.
They match up exactly.
This will, I hope, compile.
Cannot find myFreqs.
So, I've looked up here and
I can see myFreqs, myFreqs myFreqs, that's
because I forgot to say set, the name
of the method to set the value is set.
Now I'm ready to run it.
But I haven't printed any values.
After I've printed them, so
after I've tested them all and
found them I will literally print every
single word and how many times it occurs.
So I'm gonna use the standard four
loop that loops over array values or
array list values.
Size is the method that
tells me how many there are.
And I'm going to print The number
of occurrences which is in myFreqs,
a tap character and then the word itself.
That compiled I'll create a new one by
right clicking and creating a new object.
And then I'm going to run the tester
method on this object by right clicking.
There's the right click, run tester.
Let's count romeo.
And you can see how many times
different words have occurred in Romeo.
For example, the has occurred 677 times,
Romeo 48 and Juliet 23.
Another word that occurs often
is Juliet with a period.
I haven't taken into
account punctuation at all.
And from occurs 86 times.
Let's make sure that part
of the code is clear.
I've accessed the value in myFreqs and
stored it in the Int value.
And then I've set
the value at index to value
+1 because array lists use integer rather
than int, this is a two step process.
Find the value and then store the value.
That's what we need to do with integer
which would be a little bit
different than we had with int.
We'll see that in a later video.
Let's look down here.
MyFreqs .get(k) returns the kth
value of the frequency array list.
And myWords.get(k) returns
the corresponding word.
The 23rd frequency is the number of
times the 23rd word has occurred.
Now that you know a little more about
array lists, let's write some code.