[MUSIC]
All right, here's your overview
of the last part of the project.
I'm actually only gonna demo part
of the last part of the project,
because the very last part of the project
is an open-ended extension of your choice.
So, you'll get to have some freedom and
some creativity with that.
Really, anything goes.
It's up to you.
But for the first part of
the project that everybody will do,
what we are asking you to do is actually
make no changes to the map at all.
So your map is going to behave
basically just like it did
in the last part of
the programming assignment.
But what you are going to add is,
you are going to add code
that will sort the earthquakes in
descending order of magnitude.
So when you run the program now,
in addition to printing out the number of
earthquakes per country,
they will also print out a list
of the earthquakes in the RSP that
you read sorted in reverse order.
So, strongest magnitude first,
and then a descending order.
And you'll write a function
that allows you to
control the number of earthquakes
that get printed out here.
So that's really it, and then you'll get
to work on that open ended extension, so
have fun with it.
You're gonna get to learn about some
searching and sorting algorithms to write
this part of the project and
then dive into that open ended extension.