[MUSIC]
Hi, my name is Nina Ye.
I'm on the Google Fiber
software engineering team.
Search and sort are both used very
commonly in the work I do at Google Fiber.
Actually, don't some people use the word
Google and search interchangeably?
Let me Google this movie.
Can you Google that recipe?
On fiber.google.com,
which my team works on,
one of the most used features by our
users is the check address button.
It lets our users enter an address and
check whether Google Fiber is coming to or
if it's already available
in that location.
Once user enters an address,
the system searches through
an address database of millions and
millions of records to find a Google Fiber
readiness status for that entered address.
And the result is expected to come back
almost instantaneously to the user.
For that, we need a variable bust and
high performing searching algorithm.
Sorting is used in day
to day programming too.
For instance, to show investors choices
of something in an organized format,
we sort the list before
displaying them to the user.
In Google Fiber's sign up web pages,
the sports TV packages, available for
customers to chose from,
are displayed in alphabetical order.