Now it's time for you to solve
a new problem with web server logs.
For this problem you'll be writing
a program to determine how many times each
user visited the website.
This information can be quite useful for
understanding how people use your website.
Do the same people visit
your site repeatedly?
For example this person keeps coming
back to the site again and again.
Her IP appears many times in the log file.
Seeing the same visitor
repeatedly coming to your site
might indicate that they find the website
useful because they keep coming back.
By contrast, this person visited
the site once, but never came back.
Maybe it wasn't what he was looking for,
or maybe he found the site hard to use.
If most users only visit your site once,
it might suggest that there are some
issues you would want to look into.
Of course, as with all problems,
the techniques you are going to learn
are useful in a wide variety of
other problems, not just those
dealing with web server log analysis.
So, let's dive right in.