As always, you are going to apply
the seven steps to solve this problem.
As with the previous problem,
we'll observe
that the problem is fundamentally
the same no matter what Strings you use.
And use Strings that are easier
to talk about than IP addresses.
We'll work through this
using some animals.
We want to count how many times each
animal name appears in this list, cat,
snake, T-Rex, snake, cat.
Now, you start by working through this
example in a step by step fashion,
examining each animal and keeping count
of how many times you have seen its name.
When you have finished looking at each
animal in the list, you have your answer.
Cat and snake both appear twice,
and T-Rex appears once.
Now that you've worked an example,
it is time to think about and
write down exactly what you just did.
The first thing was to
make an empty table, or
you can keep track of each name and
how many times you had seen it.
Saying you made a table is fine, but it is
also good to think about what this means
in terms of actual data types
you can use in your program.
What type have you seen that is useful for
representing this kind of information?
Yes, a HashMap that maps Strings
names to Integers counts.
Once you realized that this is a HashMap,
you may as well call the columns by
their technical names, Key and Value.
Finally, you'd want to give this HashMap
a name so that you can refer to it easily.
We'll call it Counts.
Next, you looked at the first
string in the list, Cat.
Then you looked for Cat in counts and
saw it wasn't there,
so you put it in with a value of one.
You did a similar step for
the second String Snake,
which was also not in counts,
and for the third String, T-Rex.
For the fourth string, Snake,
things were a little different.
When you look in count, you see Snake is
already there with a count of one, so
you update the count to be two.
And similarly,
for the last string, Cat, you find
that it already has a count of one.
So, you update it to have a count of two.
After all of that,
the entire HashMap count is your answer.
That leads to these steps for
this particular instance of the problem.
So now, it is time to find patterns and
generalize to any instance of the problem.
Notice there are several steps where
you did not find the current String in
the HashMap.
In each of these cases, you put it
into the HashMap with a value of one.
Why one?
Do you always want one, or
should you look for some other pattern?
If you think about it for a moment,
you will realize that here,
you always want one.
It is the first occurrence of that name,
so you've seen it once.
There are also some cases where
you already had that particular
name in a HashMap.
In these cases,
you updated the value to be 2.
Again, you should should ask yourself,
why did I use 2?
Do I always want 2, or
is there some other pattern?
In this case, you do not always want 2.
Instead, you want the old value plus 1.
That just happens to always be 2 here,
because of the specific
example you worked.
With all of that in mind, you should
be able to generalize these steps and
come up with an algorithm
that looks like this.
This algorithm makes an empty HashMap,
then iterates over
each String in the input, and checks if
that String is already in the HashMap.
If not, the algorithm puts that String
in to the HashMap with a value of 1, and
if it's already there, it updates
the value to be 1 more than the old value.
After processing all the Strings,
the answer is the HashMap counts.
Now, you want to test this algorithm out.
Test it on the input fish,
dog, fish, fish.
This algorithm got you the right answer so
you can be more confident
that it's correct.
Before you turn this into code,
we're going to remember that our input
is not actually a list of Strings but
a list of login entries whose IP
addresses you want to process.
This slightly adjusted algorithm
is basically the same.
But we have changed this variable
name to le, to stand for log entry,
and are iterating over the contents
of the array list records,
which is an instance variable
in the LogAnalyzer class.
Then, you want to get the IP
address out of that log entry, and
use that as the string that
you use to update the HashMap.
Now, it is time to turn this into code.