We'd like to find out how many
times somebody visits a web site.
So we're gonna look at a log file that
has IP addresses and see, for example,
for one IP address, how many times did
that IP address appear in the file?
That's how many times that
person visited the web site.
So we have a program here,
a class called LogAnalyzer.
And we are going to write
the method count visits per IP.
So how many times does each
IP address visit a page?
And what we have in here is we're going
to put log entries in an ArrayList.
It's called records.
So we have a constructor that
initializes that ArrayList.
We then have readFile, which is gonna
have the file name of the log entries.
And that is going to allow you
to select a log entry file.
And then it just goes through and
reads through all the lines and
puts them into records.
So we are gonna focus on
writing countVisitsPerIP and
we are gonna use a HashMap to do that.
So the first thing we are gonna do
is we need to make an empty HashMap.
And we're going to be mapping
a string to an integer.
So for each IP address, which is a string,
we're gonna map that to the account,
which is the number of times that
IP address appears in the file.
So first let's make, let's see.
A HashMap of type String,
which is the type of the key,
and of type Integer, which is the type
of the value for the HashMap.
We need to give it a name, so
we're gonna call it counts and
then we have to create a new one.
So a new HashMap of type
String for the key and
Integer for the value.
There we go.
Now that we have it,
we want to iterate over all
the records that we have,
so we're gonna use a for
loop for Each log entry.
And we need a variable name so
I'm just gonna call that le.
We're going to iterate over the records
where we've put all the records from
the file.
Okay.
All right, there's our for loop.
And now we're going to look at
each LogEntry, one at a time.
So, first what we'll do from the LogEntry
is we'll get the IP address.
Okay, so we need a variable for that,
and that is gonna be of type String.
So we'll call that variable, say,
IP, which is of type String.
And we will use the log
entry to get the IP address.
So if you remember we have getIpAddress.
And that should get us the IP address.
Now that we have the IP address, we have
to see if it's already in our HashMap or
not, so
we'll have to ask a question about that.
So, we're going to ask if.
Counts.containsKey, okay.
So again, counts is our HashMap and
we're using the containsKey function,
and we will ask if that IP
address is in there or not.
And I am actually going to ask
first if it's not in there.
So we'll put the not there.
And if it's not in there, then that
means we want to put it in there for
the first time.
When we put it in there for
the first time, its count is gonna be 1.
So we'll add code for that.
So we get the name of
the HashMap which is counts.
And we'll use the put.
And we need to put in the IP address,
which is the variable IP.
And we put in 1 for the count 1.
Now if it's not in there.
Then we'll want to.
Sorry, if it is in there,
then we'll know it's already in there.
We need to get the value out.
We need to add 1 to it and
we need to put it back in.
So we'll do that now.
So essentially we're
gonna use counts.put but
what we're gonna put in there is we're
gonna put the IP address in there again,
or basically replace it with, we have to
get the old value out and add 1 to it.
So we'll have to use counts.get
to get the old value of it.
And then we'll have to add 1 to that.
And then what else do we have to do?
We come down here.
So if we get to the end of that and
we've put all of our log entries into our
HashMap and essentially they're each in
there once, with the count of how many
times they appear in the file, then we can
return the answer, which is just counts.
So we'll compile this and, let's see,
we gotta spell getIpAddress correctly,
so we'll fix that.
And we've compiled it with
no syntax errors now.
All right, so now we wanna test this out.
Again, let's just see, countVisitsPerIP
is gonna return the HashMap that is all
the mappings of the IP addresses to their
counts, so you get the whole thing.
We need to test it out now.
So in order to test it out,
we're going to create another class here,
which I've started, called CountTester.
And what we'll do in here is
we'll first create a LogAnalyzer,
the class that we just had, so,
we'll create a LogAnalyzer object.
We'll just call it la.
And we have to create a new one.
Okay.
So, now we have a LogAnalyzer object.
We'll need to pick a file to read from.
So I'm going to use the readFile and
we'll put in.
I happen to have a very small
test file to make sure and
convince myself that this actually works.
So it is called short-test_log.
And I'll show you that in a minute, and
then I want to now call
count visits per IP.
And remember that's gonna
return a HashMap, so
I need to have a HashMap
variable to put it in.
So I'll do that.
HashMap of type String Integer.
I'm gonna call it counts and
now that is gonna be assigned
the value returned by our
LogAnalyzer which is called la and
that's gonna call the method we just
wrote which is countVisitsPerIP.
And then once we have that, we can just
print out the HashMap that we created.
So I'll just have
system.out.println on counts.
Now, let's see if this compiles.
And we're missing something.
Let's see.
We need to use.
We used the wrong kind of quotes.
So, we'll put double quotes here.
And we'll try compiling it again.
And we forgot the semicolon at the end.
All right good, we're good.
So that works, and I want to show you over
here my simple file and then we'll run it.
So I have this very short test file, and
you can see it's got one, two, three,
four, seven log entries in there.
You can see the second entry which is
152.3.135.44 is in there three times.
Now we're gonna run it.
So we'll come over to BlueJ.
Everything's compiled.
We'll run count tester.
We gotta create the new object first.
And we'll run, and there we go.
And you can see, if I can put both
of these up here at the same time.
There we go with one.
So we created a HashMap,
and you can see that
the one that starts with 152.3 is
listed as being there three times.
That is, we print out the HashMap and
it prints out each IP address equals
its count that we came up with.
And so the second entry here
is 152.3.135.44 with a 3 and
you can see the 157.55 one is
only in there one time and
we got 1 and you can see
the 152.3.135 is in there twice.
And you can see, we counted it twice.
So now I'm more convinced that
what we wrote is correct.
All right, happy coding.