Think back to the problem where you found
how many unique IP addresses there were in
a web server log.
That problem was essentially finding out
how many different strings there were.
If you look at what you just did, finding
how many times each string occurred,
you may realize that you have
solved a larger problem.
The solution to the problem of counting
unique Strings is already here.
You have each unique String
in this HashMap as a key, and
would just need a way to turn
it into the answer you want.
Your counting out rhythm has
already done the hard work.
You would just need to be able to
extract the answer from the HashMap.
This situation is common in programming.
You may write code to solve a more
complex problem and then be able to solve
a simpler problem easily by using the more
complex algorithm to do the hard work.
Recognizing such situations
can be quite helpful
to becoming a highly
productive programmer.
In this case, using the HashMap from the
second problem to solve the first problem,
is easy.
HashMaps have a .size() method,
which tells how many key
value pairs the HashMap has.
As each key appears once in the HashMap,
the result from .size() tells you
exactly how many unique keys
there were in the input.
If you had written
countVisitsPerIP() first,
you could have written countUniqueIPs()
with just these two lines of code.
The first line uses countVisitsPerIP()
to solve a larger problem.
And the second line uses the .size()
method in HashMap to turn the answer from
that problem in to
the answer to this problem.
The size of the HashMap is exactly
the number of unique keys,
which is the answer to this problem.
Whenever you are programming,
try to think of way to use code that
you have already written and tested.
Thank You.