Congratulations you have solved the
problem of counting how many times each
user has visited a site.
You solved this problem using Hashmaps,
which you learned about previously and
should be becoming quite
proficient with by now.
That proficiency is great, as HashMaps
are really useful data structure
to solve a lot of different problems.
You also saw how you could use
the solution to this problem
to solve a different problem easily.
You could just take the size of
the resulting HashMap to figure out
how many unique IP addresses
there are in the log file.
Being able to realize when the solution to
one problem can be used to solve another,
is a very useful skill to work on
as you develop as a programmer.