[MUSIC]
Everyone wants to write efficient code, or
putting it another way,
no one wants to write inefficient code.
If your program takes ten
minutes to display the welcome
to my program screen, everybody knows this
is bad, okay fine we wanna avoid that.
But making an active decision to write
efficient code is a little different and
it's important because it
influences how you design it.
You make different decisions for the
underpinnings of the logic for your code,
the way you're going to approach it.
Writing efficient code is really important
for us at Google because of how it
plays out for millions of users
making billions of requests everyday.
When in the group that I work in,
when we submit changes to the code
one of the things that it gets evaluated
on before it can actually go live
is its impact on the latency
that's seen by end users.
There are certain pieces of our system and
as you might imagine, Google's
system is a stack of different components,
each communicating with each other.
But in our system there is a few places
in particular that we look at where
taken as a whole,
if the user's request takes so
many milliseconds to be
processed that's okay.
But in the specific pieces of that system,
even though they may run separately and
in parallel with the rest of the software,
we have much tighter constraints.
For the areas that I work in,
if I submit a change and
it increases the amount of
time that it takes to run
that part of the request by more
than one tenth of one millisecond.
I have to justify it.
We keep that tight of constraint on it.
If I blow that constraint,
I have to go back and
fix my code, or I have to prove
why it's okay for me to do that.
In our case,
it's because we look at it and, well,
a tenth of a millisecond here,
not a big deal, maybe.
A tenth of a millisecond there,
But when you get as many programmers
writing code as we do at Google,
suddenly those tenths of milliseconds
really start adding up, and
now we're at the point where
submitting your search request
takes three hours to satisfy which
obviously isn't gonna work for you.
You're gonna go off and
look for somebody else.
So, efficiency is hard and
it's important and
you have to design for it.
You have to plan for it.
And you have to watch it all the time.
Because those inefficiencies sneak in and
mount up.
And this little change today
may not seem like a big deal.
But when all those little changes get
tacked together, suddenly it's forever.
So, be careful.
Yay, efficiency.