Now that you've learned about ArrayLists,
it is time to work with
the Gladlib.java program.
You will learn how it works and
how to modify it to create stories and
new kinds of data.
You'll need to understand the programs so
that you can modify it.
As a programmer or software engineer,
sometimes you'll be creating programs from
scratch and
sometimes you'll be modifying programs.
Enhancing them,
making them more robust, and more.
In this program there are many pieces,
many methods each of which
you can write yourself.
This means you'll be able to
understand each method and
be able to modify the program
in different ways.
Since you'll start with a working program,
you'll be able to make improvements and
additions while testing your program to
see that it continues to work correctly.
You'll be able to understand class design,
method design and the limitations of
the GladLib.Java program you start with
as you make improvements to the code.
As you work to understand these
aspects of software design and
engineering, you can
tell stories about it.
As you modify the program you'll be
creating reusable program components and
reusable ideas that you'll be able to use
as you develop software experience and
expertise.
We'll take a tour of the program before
you begin to make enhancements and
improvements.
As with all Java classes, a constructor
will initialize a GladLib object.
The constructor will create
the ArrayList instance variables
that hold replacements for
nouns, colors, and more.
It will also create
the Java.util.random object used for
choosing a replacement at random.
The general control flow of
the program after initialization
will be to read a story template and
process each word.
If the word is a label, like country or
timeframe, indicated by angle brackets,
the code will find
a replacement at random.
After the story is created,
the program will print it.
Let's look at these pieces in more detail.
First, let's take a quick look at creating
stories from the template you just saw.
There is one public method in the class,
makeStory.
Calling this method will use
a template to generate a story
as we'll see when we look
more closely at the code.
In Kenya, a long time ago,
nearly 245 decades ago,
there live a pink, funny tiger.
It so loved to sing and dance,
but there was an angry,
gigantic lion named Lance
that scared it so much.
In Ecuador, a long time ago,
nearly 105 months ago,
there lived a jovial, yellow polar bear.
It so loved to sing and dance, but
there was a furious, angry rabbit
named Albert that scared it so much.
Reading words from the template and
printing the story will be code
you likely won't need to modify.
Calling makeStory will read
a template from a file or URL and
loop over each word in the template.
If the word is a label with angle
brackets, it will be replaced.
Finding labels is a straight
use of .indexOf and
.substring in the private
method processWord.
We use these methods to ensure that
punctuation or letters before and
after the angle brackets are preserved.
Printing the story will display the final
result in the console window of Blue Jay.
Or a different programming environment.
The private method printOut has
a parameter to specify the line width, so
you can create a story and use 80 or
40 characters, or any other number.
You could modify the printOut method
to write this story to a file,
too, using
the edu.duke.fileresource class.
Changing the GladLib.java program requires
understanding how the ArrayList
variables are used.
There is one ArrayList for
each possible label in a story
template like noun or color.
These instance variables should be named
appropriately so that programmers will be
able to easily understand their
use in reading and modifying code.
As with all instance variables or
fields, they'll be created and
initialized when the GladLib constructor
is called either using new or
from within BlueJay when
you create an object.
The program can use all of
the fields when replacing words
as part of telling a story.
The field adjective list will hold
replacements for the label adjective.
The field nounList will be for nouns and
the instance variable colorList will
hold colors to be chosen at random.
Each field holds replacements for
the label that's part of its name.
This is a convention in the program
not required by Java, but
following the convention will make it
simpler to create a new instance variable,
like verbList, for a new label.
We'll look at each use of these fields.
One is finding a substitute for
a label like color.
Based on the word that's part
of a label like color or
noun, the private method
getSubstitute will
access the appropriate instance variable
to find our random replacement.
For example if the label is color,
then a replacement will be chosen
from the field color list.
If the label is noun
then noun list is used.
You can see in the method
getSubstitute that adding a new label
will require adding a new if statement
to access the appropriate ArrayList.
A value is chosen at random using
a private method, randomFrom.
Both randomFrom and
getSubstitute are private.
They're called as a result of
calling the public makeStory method.
When getSubstitute calls randomFrom,
getSubstitute will always pass one of
the instance variables you made such as
adjective list etc., as the value for
the parameter source.
Initializing the ArrayList
is straightforward, but
you'll need to understand it to
create a new field for a new label.
All the ArrayLists must be created and
initialized when
the constructor is called.
The constructor will call a private
helper method, initializeFrom.
The source for the data for colors, nouns,
and so on, could be a URL or a file.
Calling initializeFrom will
result in reading files or
URLs to store strings in each ArrayList.
If the parameter to initializeFrom
begins with HTTP then
eventually a URL resource object
will be used to read data.
Otherwise, a file resource
object will be used.
You can't see that in the code here
because the parameter source is simply
passed to the helper method, read it,
where the reading code is located.
Let's summarize how the instance
variable for replacing labels are used.
You'll need to understand this to enhance
the program by adding a new label.
For example, to create a label like verb,
you'll need a new instance variable.
You'll name it appropriately
like verbList.
You'll need to modify code in two
methods with the addition of verbList.
You'll modify the method initiazeFrom,
a private method called
from the constructor.
You'll modify the code in
the method getSubstitute,
also a private method,
called by the public,
makeStory via the private methods
fromTemplate and processWord.
The program documentation should include
information like this to help you,
the software engineer,
make modifications and enhancements.
Have fun telling stories and writing code.