We'll outline some of the design
features of the GladLib class and
talk about software design in general.
Adding a new label, like verb,
means modifying the GladLib.java
implementation in several
different places and
requires following a naming
convention used in the class.
You'll need to create a new
instance variable for
the array list that stores examples
of verbs, like run, think, or swim.
You'll need to initialize the array
list using the method initialize from
called from the constructor.
You'll need to get a random verb,
when needed,
by modifying the code in
the method get substitute.
You should follow the naming conventions
used in the class where the label
noun is associated with
the instance variable nounList,
just as the label country is
associated with countryList.
This means you should use
the name verbList for
a field that's the array list that
stores strings that are verbs.
As you modify and
extend programs and classes,
you'll gain experience with many
kinds of programming and design.
You'll gain experience that will help you
make good decisions when programming and
create good designs.
But you'll see that sometimes
experience comes from bad judgment or
bad designs that, nevertheless,
allow you to reason about the trade-offs
in doing things in more than one way.
So you might realize
that a choice that works
can lead to code that's
not easy to maintain.
Some software designs are called brittle,
meaning that the software or
design breaks when you try to extend it or
use it in ways that is a little bit
different than what's initially intended.
Flexible designs,
on the other hand, are better able to
cope with changes in the software.
When you learn about
object oriented design,
you may come across a principle that says,
code should be open for
extension but closed for modification,
the open/closed principle.
The idea is that you should
be able to extend software
without extensive modifications
to the existing code.
That's more possible with
object oriented design ideas
that we won't be able to
cover in this course, but
you can still create designs
that are more open than others.
You'll be able to understand a better
design after working with this design and
implementation.
The GladLib class does
have some good features.
It's relatively easy to understand
each method, and the code works.
It is possible to extend the code,
as you'll see,
even if the extension requires
changing the code in several places.
You'll be able to create a better design
after learning some new Java concepts
we'll introduce soon, but
those concepts will be more clear
because you'll have this experience
with this code and class,
and you'll understand why the new Java
features can make the code simpler.
The new Java features will let
you keep changes in one place,
rather than being sprinkled
across three parts of the class.
The new features will also
minimize the duplicated code
that's in the current implementation.
Have fun making new stories!