Hi, we're gonna walk through
the process of adding a new label to
the GladLib.java program and
the GladLib class.
A new label might be something like
verb which would go along with noun,
color and the other labels we have.
To do that,
you've seen part of that process
outlined in one of the previous lessons.
What I'm going to do here is show
you that to add a new label we need
a new template file, so I've taken the
standard template file that we had before,
which was called madtemplate.txt and
I've replaced sing and dance, the two
things that a creature would do in the
stories we generated, with verb and verb.
So I'm adding the label verb to replace
sing and dance in the original story.
I still call this madtemplate.txt.
You will use whatever text editing
software you have which is
usually something like
TextEdit on a Mac or
Notepad++ on a Windows machine,
but you can use any text editor.
Now I'm going to take the GladLib
program that we've used before, and
I'm going to walk through the locations
where we need to make changes.
I need to create a new array
list to store my verbs.
I'm going to go along with the same
conventions that have been used before and
make sure that I use verbList to go
along with adjectiveList, nounList, etc.
As I scroll through my source code,
I see that these
ArrayLists are initialized in
the initializeFromSource method.
It's called from our class's constructor.
I need to initialize verbList.
And its going to be
initialize by calling readIt.
Passing the source.
Which is either a place on my computer
where it can access files, or a url.
This is verb.txt.
I'm going to also have to
make one other addition.
Because now my label might be
an adjective or an animal or a name.
But I'm going to need to copy and
paste these so
that in addition to using timeframe,
I'm going to use verb.
So I'll replace that,
make sure I get the syntax right.
If the label is verb, I'm going to
replace the label from verblist.
I'm going to compile my program.
I know that in this program it's reading
the template form madtemplate.txt
which I've modified to include the angle
bracket verb angle bracket label.
I'm going to create a new
GladLib on my object work bench.
And then I'm going to run
the Make Story method.
It so loved to unknown and unknown.
There was a funny, slippery lion
named Vivian that scared it so much.
So if we go back and look at our source
code we'll see that it must have found
verb but failed to replace the verb with
the objects that it was replaced with.
In this case, I've got verb list here,
my instance variable.
I've initialized it from verb
here I've made sure that if,
oh look, if label.equals verb t,
I had a misprint when I spelled it.
Now it's got verb.
So I'm going to go back and recreate that.
Create my gladLib object,
open it up and make a story.
Hey, it's so loved to think and
contemplate, but there was a gigantic,
gigantic tiger.
Let me run that one more time and
see if I get something besides think and
contemplate.
It's so loved to ride and surrender.
One more time, and I'll be convinced
that it's actually reading verbs.
It so loved to surrender and
surrender, we've done nothing to make
sure that it can use the same word or
verb more than once, so
just to remind you what we've done.
I've used this location to
change when the label was found.
I've made sure that the label
was read from the source.
And I used verbList here, which is
the name of my instance variable here,
verbList.
Using the same naming conventions
we've used in all the other programs.
I compiled my program, I tested it,
I created a new text file to hold verbs,
and a new text file for the template.
Happy verbing.