Hi, today we're gonna write some code to
find out how many times every word in
a file occurs.
So we'll find out how many times the word
the occurs, how many times the word
wonderful occurs, and we're going
to start with a working program.
Let me show you very quickly
what that looks like.
This countWords function that we
have here, this method countWords,
simply creates a file resource,
loops over all the words in it, and
counts how many total words there are.
If I take this program, make an object
on my workbench, right click and
call countWords, it will ask me for
to enter the name of a file.
I will use Confucius, and
it will tell me that there are 34,582
words in the works of Confucius.
Rather than knowing
the total number of words,
I'd like to find out how many
times each individual word occurs.
To do that, I'm going to use a map.
So I'm going to need to add another
local variable here, a HashMap.
I'm going to map strings to integers.
Each string will be a word that occurs
in my file, that's the key in this map.
And the value in the map is how
many times that word occurs.
So I need to create a new one.
I'm allowed to make a HashMap
because I've imported java.util.
That's the package in
which we find HashMap.
Now, as I read the words,
rather than incrementing the total,
I'm going to ask,
have we seen w in the map before?
So I'm going to ask whether the key set
associated with the map contains w,
the word I'm looking for.
And if it does, I've seen the word before,
I'm going to put the value
w back in the map.
It's already there.
I'm going to get the number of times
that word occurs and add once.
I'll go over again what
I'm doing in a minute.
If I've never seen the word before, then
what I'm going to do is put it in my map
with the number one, because the word
will have occurred one time.
Let me compile and
make sure I've got that right.
So let me go over very
quickly what I've just done.
I've looked to see, does this word,
w, that I just read and converted
to lowercase, is it in my keyset?
Have I ever seen it before?
If I have seen it before, let me get
the integer value associated with it.
That's the number of times
it's already occurred.
Add 1 to that, and put that in the map
as a key value pair, with the word and
an incremented count.
If I've never seen it before,
this is the first time.
I've now added all the values to the map
and now I'd like to print them out.
The way I'm going to print them
out is to loop over the key set.
That's all the words
that are keys in my map.
And I'm going to get the value associated
with it, that's the number of occurences.
That's the value associated with my word,
and if that value is big, and here I'm
gonna say if it's bigger than 500, I'm
going to print the words that occur a lot.
Which is, so I'm going to print the number
of occurrences, a tab character,
and the word itself.
So I'm looping over the keyset
that allows me to find every key.
I'm getting the value associated
with that key in the map, and
if that's big, I'm going to print it.
Big in this case is bigger than 500.
So I'm going to right click and
create a new object.
And I am going invoke the method
countWords which before,
used to count the total number of words,
and
now it's gonna count all
the individual words in Confucius.
And here we can see that
in the file Confucius
there are not that many words
that occur more than 500 times.
The occurs more that 2,000 times.
And occurs 762.
If I wanna see a little more in
the way of words, I'll say 200,
just to make sure that I'm
getting something more.
And I'll make a new version of this
that sits on the object workbench.
I'll right click and call countWords.
I'll once again count Confucius, and
you can see there are more words.
Master occurs 484 times.
Confucius was the master of many things.
You are now going to be the master
of programming as you use maps
to map keys to values
to solve many problems.
Have fun coding.