In this lesson, we'll look at how we can
use the HashMap class to make our GladLib
class easier to extend,
have fewer lines of code, and
be a good example of how to become a more
skilled and experienced software designer.
As a reminder, extending
the class to use a new label like
angle bracket verb angle bracket, requires
modifying the code in three places.
You'll need to create an array
list instance variable,
initialize it properly, and use it as
the source for your random replacements.
You should also follow a convention of
using field names, like verbList, for
the label verb.
This makes it difficult to
use text files or URLs for
the source of word replacements unless all
such sources follow the same conventions,
such as using a file name noun.txt for
the label noun, or the field,
nounList, or color.txt for
colorlist in the field color.
Let's take a look at the concepts
behind these requirements for
extending the GladLib class, to look at
a new way of structuring data in classes.
Each label is associated with
an ArrayList instance variable.
You see the label
associated with nounList,
the label  with colorList,
and so on.
These named instance variables make for
a poor design.
Adding a new label, like verb, requires
defining an instance variable by name,
initializing it by name,
and using it by name.
That's three places in which
the program must be modified.
Instead, we'll use a HashMap to help
create a better and more flexible design.
The HashMap will allow us to label or
align the label to an ArrayList without
ever having to name the ArrayList, itself.
Given a label, the code will look up or
find the associated ArrayList
in the HashMap structure.
As you've seen,
this is similar to how indexOf works for
finding a value in an ArrayList or
a character in a string.
Getting the value associated with
a label will return an ArrayList.
Let's take a closer look at how using
a HashMap creates a more flexible design.
One HashMap will replace seven or
more instance variables.
The HashMap will reference as
many Arraylists as needed,
rather than us having to define
separate instance variables, and
following a naming convention,
as you see here.
The code will use a single instance
variable, a HashMap named myMap.
This will associate
an ArrayList with each label.
So the keys in the map are strings,
the label in the GladLib program.
The value associated with each key is
the ArrayList of replacement words for
that label.
This means that to add a new label and
a new ArrayList, we don't have
to add a new instance variable.
We simply need to store new values in
the single HashMap instance named, myMap.
Let's look at how the method,
getSubstitute, works with a HashMap.
In the original program, a sequence
of if statements was used to identify
the instance variable associated
with the particular label.
The naming convention of
using countryList for
country allows a programmer
to extend the code.
But there will always be as many if
statements in the getSubstitute method
as there are labels and
instance variables.
The last if statement is different.
You can see that the label,
angle bracket, number, angle bracket,
generates a random number instead of
finding one in a list of numbers.
When using a Hashmap, the getSubstitute
method is much more simple.
The Hashmap associates a label with
the ArrayList of replacements.
The ArrayList for a label is accessed
using the HashMap.get method to
get the ArrayList associated with a string
label like country or noun or color.
Adding a new label doesn't require
modifying this method at all.
And that's an example of
the open/closed principle
we talked about in a previous video.
Using a HasMap makes for a more flexible
class that's easier to extend, but
there's room for even more
improvement using HashMaps again.
The original program reads a file or
URL to store information in each
named instance variable, the ArrayList
of replacement values for that label.
That was done in a sequence of statements
that called the helper method, readIt.
The HashMap version still associates
a label with a file name, and
that file name must be
specified in the program.
But the code is different because we
use a loop to associate each label with
a file name.
This wasn't possible in
the original program.
Note the private helper method,
readIt, is still called.
What changes if we want to
add a new label like verb?
The program will still
associate the name of
the file of replacement values
in verb.txt with the new label.
We could store a new string,
like quote verb quote, in the local
string array of variable labels.
We could add that just after the string,
timeframe, for example.
Unfortunately, we still have
the limitation in that the code
uses a naming convention for
files like verb.text for the label verb.
We could use a HashMap in a different
way to associate file names with labels,
without modifying the program.
The program could be designed to read
a file of information that specifies where
to find the words to replace the labels.
Rather than requiring the code to
modified, compiled, tested, and
run to simply find nouns in
a different file or website.
This kind of file is often called
a .properties or property file.
As shown here,
it simply associates a label with
a source of replacements for that label.
The convention of using a colon to
separate values in a .properties
file is common, but
equals could also separate the values.
The ,properties file can be read using
a file resource object, for example, and
the information in the properties
file stored in a HashMap.
Suppose a HashMap instance variable named
myLabelSouce is used to associate labels
like noun with the source of
words that are now replacements,
like GladLibs.com/nounsfunny.txt.
The method initialized from source
would simply loop over the values
stored as keys in the HashMap.
Recall that keys are accessed
via the method, keySet.
The string that specifies the source for
each label is retrieved from
the map using the .get method.
The source is used to read values
into the ArrayList for the label.
You could add such a feature to
the GladLib program to make it
even more extensible.