Computers are very good at modeling and
simulation, in part because
computers can perform billions of
mathematical operations every second.
Often simulation and modeling relies
on generating random numbers.
In this coding example we'll see a simple
use of arrays to help determine how
really random
the java.util.Random class is.
Computers don't use
natural random phenomena,
but model randomness of what's
called pseudo-randomness.
Using mathematics to model what
might be random events in nature.
In this example,
we will simulate rolling a pair of dice.
Many times.
By generating random numbers.
We would like to know how
many twos do we roll,
how many sevens do we roll, we will count
how many times each type of roll occurs.
So I've got this code right here
called Simple Stimulate and
I can run it and say how many
rolls I want to do, and right now,
it counts how many times I get two,
and how many times I get 12.
So let's run it and see what it does.
So we'll come over here.
It's already compiled.
I'll create the object.
And we'll run simple simulate.
And here we actually get to choose how
many times, so I'll say 10,000 times.
And we'll just run it.
And you can see I got two 298 times,
and I got 12 271 times.
It'd be nice to run it and
count all the possible rolls you could
get from two to 12, so
let's look at doing that.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna cut and
paste this and
we'll write a different method.
So we'll just copy this whole thing.
And then we'll put it up here.
And we'll just call this one Simulate.
There we go and so
now we're gonna have to modify it so
the first thing is we have generate
a rand and then we need counters for
two, three, four, five, six,
seven, eight, nine, 10, 11, 12.
That's a lot of counters.
So what I would like to do instead
is to use an array of counters,
so that's what we'll do.
So we'll replace this here with an array.
So we want an array of counters so
it'll be int array instead.
We'll have to give it a name.
We'll call it counts.
And then we'll have to create the array.
It's an integer array and
then what size is it gonna be?
So, two through 12,
we need at least 11 counters but
it would be kind of nice if we set
it up so that when we threw a four,
we would count four in
the fourth slot of the array.
So what we'll do is we'll create
the array with size 13 which
will allow us to use from zero to 12 and
really we'll just use two through 12 and
we'll ignore the zero and one counters.
So I'll make my array of size 13 I
don't need this 12 counter anymore.
So we'll get rid of that.
Okay.
So
now we're gonna have to adjust the code
to handle using this array of counters.
Okay.
So we're still rolling
whatever number of times we typed in for
rolls.
So that's the same.
We're still throwing two dice, d1 and d2,
and we are gonna to add them together.
But, as you can see here, we have this if
statement, where we have to check and see,
was it two?
Was it 12?
And
we could add all these
other if statements.
Was it three, four, five and so on?
But instead, we can just notice,
we just add the two together.
That's also the index position of
the counter and that's all we have to do.
So we can get rid of this if statement.
And instead we're just gonna add code, so
we're gonna update or
counter that position by one.
So our array is called counts,
we're gonna add in the d1 + d2 slot,
we're just gonna add 1, + = 1.
That's it,
that replaced a huge if statement.
Let's see, so now we're gonna output.
So you can see we have two lines
of output for twos and 12s.
What we're gonna do instead is it would be
nice if we just had one print statement
and we used it over and over again for
each position in our counter array.
So we're gonna add a four loop here.
And remember, our counter started at two.
So we'll have our k start at two.
Cuz the first, lowest thing you can
get is two ones, from each dice.
And that's two.
So that'll be the lowest, and
then it'll be k less than or equal to 12.
Because we're gonna go from two to 12.
And then we'll update it the same way,
k++.
Okay and then we just need one of
these output statements to modify.
Or I'll just, I'll just type a new one,
will just say here so
System.out.println, and
what we wanna do is we wanna print
k cuz that'll be the counter,
so k for two through 12, right.
So we will print k and then we'll print,
we can still do the quotes.
Equals and a tab.
\t is the tab.
Plus, and then we wanna know,
how many twos were there,
or how many tens were there, etc.
And that's just counts k.
That's how many of type k
there were that we counted.
Plus, we can add another tab.
And then we can add the rest of this,
100 times counts of k divided by rolls and
I'll just put that in parenthesis.
I guess it doesn't matter.
We do need to add a semicolon at the end.
And then I can get rid of these
two print statements here.
Oops, there we
go.
Okay so I think we have everything now,
so we've got,
we now have our loop that prints for
each one, two through 12 what it does.
Let's see if we have it compiling.
Oh, we're missing one right paren,
right here.
So we can add that.
Oops, we'll add it and
then put our semicolon.
There we go.
Let's try compiling it again.
And it says it compiles.
There's our code.
So now let's run it and see what happens.
It's already compiled.
We can create our object.
And then we can run it, simple simulate,
this is called simulate.
And then we'll run it again,
let's run it 100,000 times.
There it goes, okay, so now you can
see we're getting lots of numbers.
Lots of counts for twos,
threes, fours, and so on.
How do you know it actually works?
We just got lots of numbers.
It looks pretty good in the sense
that if you wrote seven you're
going to get that more likely than any
other thing because seven is two and five,
one and six, three and four and it does
have the highest number but to really be
sure what we'll do is we'll run a simple
example and we'll add print statement.
Like, let's run it ten times and
let's see what the actual roles are and
we can see if our counters
are really working correctly.
So, let's do that real quick.
We'll go back to the code here.
So, this is really adding just for
testing it to make sure that the counters
are really the counters we think they are.
So whenever we roll a dice,
which is right here,
I'm just gonna add a print statement here.
So what I'll do is I'll
print out roll is d1.
Plus.
D2 which equals.
D1 + d2.
So, that's all we're doing,
we're just printing out the roll.
Then we're just gonna run it
a very small number of times, so
that we can see our counters
are actually working correctly.
So, we'll compile that and that worked.
So, let's run it now.
Okay, so I'm just gonna run it ten times.
Throw the dice ten times.
And let's see what we get.
So, we got it looks like one,
two, three sevens and
if you look, it counted seven three times.
We got one, two, three tens and
it counted ten three times.
We got a four once, we got a four.
So it looks like it is
counting them correctly.
So this is way you can kind of test
it on a small amount of data and
that seems to work.
All right so anyway,
I hope you enjoyed dice rolling.
Thank you.