We'd like to automate the cracking,
or breaking, of the Caesar Cipher.
To do this, we'll rely on frequencies
of letters in English text.
If you're encrypting a message in
another language, you'll need to use
the frequencies from that language,
but the approach will be the same.
We'll write code to find the character
that occurs most frequently in the message
being decrypted.
We'll assume this is the letter
e since e occurs more frequently
than any other letter in English text.
In Russian, for example, the letter
o occurs more frequently than e.
If our assumption about e is wrong,
we won't decrypt the original message.
It's possible to use more than just e,
but to rely on the frequencies of
all the letters and use statistical
approaches to break the CaesarCipher.
In some cases, these approaches will break
other encryption methods, though not
the methods used to encrypt data for
online shopping and secure transactions.
Let's look at the code for
decryption in two steps.
We need to count the occurrences
of each letter, a through z,
in the message we're encrypting.
We'll have code to scan each letter
of the text, an increment counter for
each of the 26 different letters.
Initially all the counters are zero
since we haven't started scanning
the text letter by letter.
Each counter is numbered from 0 to 25
because the counters are array elements.
The index from a string of 26 letters
will help us find the right index for
the counter we'll increment
as we scan the text.
As we scan the message,
looking at each character, we'll
increment the counter at index 7 for H.
Then as we scan,
I will increment the counter index 8,
which is the index of I
in our alphabet string.
We won't increment for
the comma, or for the space.
Then we'll increment the calendar
at index 3 for the D.
The counter at index 14 for the O,
we won't increment for the space because
space doesn't occur in the alphabet.
Then, we'll increment
the counter at index 24 for Y.
And we'll set the counter at index 14 to 2
when we scan the second O in the message.
When we're done scanning every character,
we'll have these values for each counter.
If you look carefully at these values,
you see that our decryption
method is likely to fail.
The value of the counter
with index 4 is 0,
there are no Es in this message,
but this is a very unusual message.
Now we'll look at the code for this idea.
We scan the message character by
character using a standard for loop.
We find where the character occurs in a
string of each letter in the alphabet, so
that E will be found at index 4.
Notice that we converted the characters in
the message being decrypted to lower case.
We use the index in the alphabet to
increment the corresponding counter
as part of decrypting the message.
If the character wasn't in
the letters of the alphabet,
the .indexOf method returned -1,
and we don't increment any counter.
The code that uses the idea of e occurring
most frequently, is straightforward
developed from the ideas, algorithm,
and code you've just seen.
As you can see, the code isn't very long
but we've created two helpful methods and
relied on the CeasarCipher class to help.
We've called the method countLetters,
which we just discussed.
This method will count the occurrences of
every character in the string encrypted,
with a being stored in the first,
or index 0, location of the array
returned by the function, and
referenced here by the variable freqs.
Then we call a method maxIndex,
which will return the index of their
entry in freqs that is the largest.
The location we will assume
is where the e was shifted.
We'll find the distance from this
location to E, E has index 4,
since we start with 0 for A, and then get
B, C, D, E, for 1, 2, 3, 4, respectively.
If the maximal index is less than 4,
we'll need to wrap around from
26 to find the shift use for E.
If the value dkey was used to encrypt,
then 26- dkey
is used to decrypt, and
we return the decrypted string.
You'll be ready to use your programming
knowledge to finish the task of
decrypting, and
then apply this knowledge in the mini
project with a different cypher.
But there's some details
we want to highlight.
The array freqs in the code we've just saw
has a relationship between the index and
the value in the array.
For example, freqs of 8 is how often
I occurs since I is the ninth letter and
has index 8.
Remember, we start with index 0.
When looking for a maximal value, as with
the method maxIndex that we called, and
whose implementation you see here, we
returned the index of the largest value,
not the largest value itself.
We use the index to find
the distance from e.
Using the existing CaesarCipher class made
decryption much more straightforward.
In general it is a good idea to use
code that has already been developed and
tested, rather than reinventing it.
Have fun coding.