[MUSIC]
Hi again.
I’m Christine Alvarado.
And in this video, I’m going to give you
some information that will help you choose
your own path through this course.
So when I’m not teaching, what I like
to do is I like to build programs and
curriculum that help bring in
a diverse set of learners to study and
work in the field of computer science.
And one thing I've learned about
reaching a diverse audience
is that you need diverse courses
with diverse support structures.
So we've engineered this
diversity into our course and
into the whole specialization.
We know that you're coming to us with lots
of different motivations, backgrounds,
experience levels.
So one size fits all is not
going to work for this course.
And that's okay, that's actually great.
We love that you're coming from
all these different backgrounds.
And what we want is for
each of you to feel challenged,
because otherwise what's the point.
But, also never to feel overwhelmed.
We wanted it to be the case that when
you feel like your starting to get
overwhelmed, you can always have some more
support to help you with your learning.
What we've designed is a course where
we have different video styles,
different video series,
to help meet that goal.
So you're not going to want to take
this course by just sitting down and
watching the videos one after another.
What you're going to do is pick and
choose a path through the videos
that's right for you.
And to help you do that, I'm gonna tell
you about our different video series.
But first I wanna say that at the end of
the day, it's all about what you can do.
Mia described this really cool project
that you're going to be doing throughout
this course, and that's really
what we want you to be able to do.
So, what we care most about are these
end of module assessments, which are,
a lot of the time, going to have you
building a piece of that project.
So, if you're feeling really advanced, and
really good about the material,
always feel free to race ahead and
just start working on that project or
do the end of module assessment.
But if you want a little instruction,
which most of you will,
you'll wanna watch some of the videos.
So the first video series that I'm gonna
tell you about is our Core Content series.
So these are the videos that
we expect everybody to watch.
They’re mostly lecture style and
they're going to introduce you to the core
concepts and skills that you will need
to do the end of module assessments.
Once you've watched those videos, we're
going to probe your knowledge a little
bit more with our
Concept Challenge series.
Again we encourage most learners
to watch these videos, and
what they're going to do is they're
gonna ask you to think about
the material you just
learned in a new way.
And Leo's gonna tell you more about these
concept challenges in just a minute.
The next series that we have for
you are Additional Support videos.
Now we don't expect everybody
to watch these videos.
These videos are designed for,
if after watching the core content and
doing those concept challenges,
you don't quite feel ready to tackle
the end of module assessments.
You might want to watch these
additional support videos.
The last two video series that we have,
we're really excited about.
These are series that aren't
designed to deliver content so
much as to put the content that
you're learning in context.
So the first of these series
is called In the real world.
And we've got a team of real-life
Google engineers talking about why
what you're learning is important
in their work at Google and
in general in the software industry.
So that'll be a really good opportunity
for you to learn not only why what you're
learning is important but how it's
important to these individual engineers.
And then the last series that we have for
you is called When I struggled.
And what you're gonna see in this
series is a number of UC San Diego
learners as well as us talking
about our own experience
learning the material that you're
going to be learning in this course.
We'll talk about a time when we struggled
with the material that we're presenting.
And then we'll talk about how
we overcame these struggles.
So we hope you'll watch
both of those series and
that it will enrich
experience in this course.
So again, to summarize, the standard
path we imagined learner taking through
this course is that you would watch
this introduction with the Google
engineers talking about why these
concepts are important in the real world.
You would go through and
watch the core concept videos and
perform these concept challenges.
Maybe watching some videos about when some
learners struggled with these concepts
along the way.
And then perform the module level
assessment and you would repeat that for
each module.
But if you're feeling more advanced,
you might just want to race right through
those core concept videos and get to
that end of module assessment faster and
get developing on those projects.
And we encourage you to do that
if you're feeling comfortable.
And again, if you feel like you
need a little more support,
you've got those support
videos available to you.
So any time you feel like you don't
quite understand what's going on,
you need a little more help, go ahead and
pull out those support videos, and
we hope that you'll find
the support that you'll need.
So choose the path that's right for
you, challenge yourself and have fun.