[MUSIC]
Hi again, I'm Leo Porter, I'm a Computer
Science professor here at UC San Diego.
One of my areas of research is
Computer Science Education.
What we like to do in that area of
research is look at the best practices for
student learning in the classroom.
One of the best practices we know about
in computer science is Peer Instruction.
With peer instruction,
students get to tackle hard problems,
discuss it with their peers, and
then participate in a large class
wide discussion with the professor.
We do this in a number of
the courses here at UC San Diego,
and we like to bring this to you.
And we're gonna do this through a series
of videos known as the Concept Challenges.
So, let me walk through an example here.
So, here we have you watching a video.
Now, let's assume this is from a previous
class in Java that you've taken before,
where you learned first about for loops.
So, you watch the video on for loops and
then you get done with the video and
the question becomes,
well, did you learn it?
I mean there's certainly areas of the
video that you probably understood well,
but there may be some areas that
you didn't understand as well.
So the best way to find out whether or
not you really understood the material,
is to solve problems.
So we're gonna ask you questions to help
illustrate what areas you're strongest in,
and which areas you're not.
So, a question may look
something like this.
So here you've just watched
the video again on for loops.
And here is an example of for loop.
And the question here is asking, how many
times does i less than 10 execute?
Now, the reason we ask a question
like this is because we expect
a number of folks will get this wrong.
In fact, we want you to get
a number of these questions wrong,
because that means it's an opportunity for
learning.
What we expected is a lot of novice
learners would answer B here.
They would say that the loop executes ten times,
so i is less than 10 will execute ten times.
But the condition i less than 10
actually executes 11 times.
And we'll talk more about
that as we go forward.
So after you solve the problem on your
own, after you tackle the problem yourself
which we will then see, or we hope you can
do is work with other learners around you.
So if you have anyone else in your
neighborhood or friends who are taking
the same course this is a great time to
get together and discuss the question.
And by discussing with your friends your
gonna find out one of you might say wait
a second, does it execute that last
time and then you realize oh shoot yeah,
it does actually execute 11 times.
But if you don't have
some friends around you,
what we're gonna give you also
a series of videos where you're seeing
UC San Diego learners
discussing the question.
And there you'll hear them say things
like, wait a second it's really easy to
forget that last check, oh yeah,
so the answer must have been 11.
And then after you hear
the UC San Diego learner discussing it,
you're gonna hear one of our explanations.
So the full course of one of
these questions is gonna look
something like this.
You're gonna pause,
try solving the problem yourself.
You're gonna discuss the question with
other learners around you if you can.
You're then gonna watch a video of
the UC San Diego learners discussing it.
And then you're gonna
confirm your understanding by
listening to our explanation.
By solving these kind of hard problems,
you're gonna understand
your material much better.
You're also gonna identify areas
that you might need improvement.
And that's where more support videos and
the forums come in.