[MUSIC]
Hi, my name is Jesse Chuy Chavez and I and
a software engineer on the Google privacy
team in the Google office in Chicago.
I world on products that help keep
our users' data safe and secure.
I'm Aaron Sure, and
I'm a software engineer working on
shopping at Google's Pittsburgh office.
>> Hi, I'm Kelly.
>> Hi, I'm Quti.
>> And we're software engineers at
Google on the Google Docs team.
>> Hi
>> I'm Matt Healey.
I'm a Google engineer working on
conversational shopping in our
Pittsburgh office.
>> Hi there.
My name is John Taylor, and
I'm an engineer in
Google's Pittsburgh office.
I'd like to welcome you to
Intermediate Programming.
Now, I find programming a lot of fun.
Not only can you do some
extremely useful things with it,
the act of programming itself can
be very satisfying and creative.
For any particular problem there
are lots of different ways you
could write a program to solve it.
But a good program has
a certain beauty and
elegance about it and an elegant program
is easy for other people to understand and
it's also easy for you to extend and
adapt later as requirements change.
And this course will help you write
beautiful and elegant programs.