[MUSIC]
In the programming assignment for
Module 3,
we'll be overlaying information
about events onto a world map.
For our assignment we've
chosen earthquake data.
But you could use the same principles
to map out rates of disease,
social network activity, Internet
connectivity, and really much more.
There are three major
components to this assignment.
The first is creating marks in
the world for recent earthquakes.
The second is to customize
those marks on the map,
based on the magnitude of the earthquake.
And the last step is to create the legend,
over here on the left,
to help someone understand
the markers on the map.
Some of these steps may
seem daunting right now but
we'll provide you code and
support to help you succeed.
Along these lines the next videos will
teach you how to create graphical user
interfaces or
sometimes called GUIs in Java.
We'll work through some examples with
unfolding maps in the processing
libraries as well.
Now if you're already familiar
with designing GUIs and
these libraries, feel free to skip ahead
to the project walk-through video so
you can get up and
running with the project.
We hope you have fun.