[MUSIC]
Welcome back.
In this video, we're gonna do a walk
through of the program assignment for
module 5 focused on spelling suggestions.
Now, this project consists
fo two major parts.
The first part is creating a class that
allows us to do single operation mutations
on words.
So for example it'll let us
do the changing of the word
his to the word this by adding
the letter T at the start of the word.
We're gonna use that in the second
part where we're gonna now look
at these quote nearby words to
provide spelling suggestions.
So you happened to mistype and
you write swone,
it will suggest to you words like stone.
So those are the two main
parts of this project.
And like all the other projects the first
thing to do is to make sure you have
the starter code.
So the two main classes that we're
going to be focused on in this project
are spellingsuggest.java and
nearbywords.java.
Let's focus on nearbywords first.
So NearbyWords is gonna take in
a dictionary that you're gonna need to use
for a number of features of the project.
Essentially, just determine whether or
not a string is, in fact,
a word in our dictionary.
The main method that you're gonna
worry about here is DistanceOne.
And the purpose of this method is to
return all words that are essentially one
letter mutation away from the original
string that's provided to you.
And you can use this boolean ords
only to essentially select I
only want the strings that are actually
words to be returned back to me.
If you have this as false it will give
you back all possible mutations based on
insertions, substitutions, or deletions.
So the thing I'll need to do then is write
insertions, substitutions and deletions.
Now doing these kinds of manipulations
of strings can be a little bit tricky.
So we've done,
is we've given you substitution for you.
So you can take in the string s.
That's the original string.
You’re gonna pass it into the current list
that you're gonna be adding words to.
And then you also take this
flag again which is words only.
Which allows you to essentially select
only those strings which are in fact words
in the dictionary.
I would recommend that you walk through
this code carefully to see what
it's doing.
You'll then need to write the insertions
method and the deletions method which
are going to be very similar to that
initial substitutions method that we
gave to you.
And that's essentially the whole
first part of this project.
So if you scroll through this you'll see
that I've given you more details on what
these methods do and
how they should function.
Both the ones I've given to you as well as
the ones you're going to write yourself.
And again, focusing on the fact that you’ll
only need to write insertions and deletions.
And as you write them, as with everything
else we've ever done, I encourage you,
test your methods.
So it's a great point for you to print
out all the different mutations that
are suggesting to make sure it's in fact
doing all the mutations that it should.
This leads you then to part two,
which is to complete the method
suggestion in NearbyWords.
And if you go back to the source code,
what you'll see is spelling suggest
is an interface and it requires just
one method, and that's suggestions.
So the idea here is if I feed in
a string which is a misspelled word,
I should be able to ask for some number
of suggestions as the maximum number of
suggestions to be given back to me.
And it'll return back a list of words up
to the length of the number of suggestions
of real words in the dictionary.
That's essentially how spelling
suggest would work and
we are all familiar with spelling suggest
because we've used text editors before.
So then you'd write words, that actual
method s going to exist right here.
I've done some setup for
you, and I'll show you why I've done
some setup with this initial algorithm.
So if you look back at suggestions
in the project writeup,
what you'll see is I've actually
done a fair amount for you.
And if you want to take
on an extra challenge for
this project, don't read
the algorithm that I'm giving you.
Because essentially the algorithm that
you're gonna be doing here is very similar
to the Breadth First Search that
you did in the last week's project.
So you did a Breadth First Search
of the tree to simply find words
that you should suggest for
auto completions.
This is the same idea except now what
we're doing is we're gonna be looking
a Breadth First Search out based on words
that are mutations of my initial word.
Now, if you do want to look at it,
continue on.
And you can see that I've actually
given you the algorithm for
essentially breadth first
search in this space.
Again, I encourage you to
look carefully at this and
understand it before you
attempt to write the code.
There are some hints that
I like to provide as well.
And first you almost certainly want
feedback from your code as you're
writing this method.
So to do this, what you'll wanna do
is print the contents of the queue,
essentially per while loop iteration.
That's a great first step
to essentially just see,
is my queue growing the way
I would expect it to.
Notice that we've also
added a few suggestions
to our NearbyWords class itself.
So if you scroll to the very bottom of
NearbyWords, what you'll find is a main
method that has essentially some
test cases already built in here.
And this is a great place to
essentially run some tests.
There is an optimization that
is worth considering for this.
And given the algorithm that we have
above, if you attempt to run your spelling
suggests on a misspelled word like
kangaroo, it's gonna cause some problems.
And it's worthwhile thinking about
why it's gonna cause these problems
on your own.
But what you're gonna attempt to do to
solve this is you're gonna make it so
that you've searched for a while and you
still haven't found any correctly spelled
words, you may be off on a tangent.
You may be off looking at space
that's never gonna arrive at
a correctly spelled word.
Moreover, by the time you actually
do arrive on a spelling suggestion,
it's gonna not resemble the initial
word at all because there have been so
many mutations done to the letters.
So the optimization here is to use
the threshold variable that we gave you in
the source code to essentially
stop looking at a certain point.
So you've explored for
some amount of time, and you stop looking.
This is an optional optimization,
but I encourage you to do it.
Especially if you want to
use your text editor, or
show off your text editor to your friends.
All right, last piece,
how are you gonna cement this code?
Just like the previous ones,
you're gonna go up to my submission.
You're gonna create a new submission.
And you'll recognise that we ask for
nearby words, such java twice.
And the reason we did this,
is that you can actually submit just for
the mutations and
get those tested and get feedback on that
before you go on to spelling suggestions.
If there are errors in your insertions or
deletions method that's gonna cause
compounding errors when
we get to suggestions.
So I actually encourage you to submit
the NearbyWords.java first to test your
mutations, get full feedback, see if you
need a full score, and then after that,
submit again for suggestions.
Like with all our previous assignments,
you can always click on Show Greater
Output to find out what you got right or
what you may have gotten wrong.
And then we've also given you
The text cases in the source code.
Nearby words greater one, nearby words
greater two, to essentially look at,
to help me figure out what
essentially went wrong.
If you need help, check the lesson videos,
as well as look in the learner forums.
Good luck on the assignment!