[MUSIC]
In this video we're gonna do a walkthrough
of the programming assignment for
module 5 that's focused on word paths.
And this assignment is a lot of fun.
I had a lot of fun doing it myself but
it can also be a bit challenging.
Here's what we're gonna do,
we're gonna bring together
the content of a number of the components
of this class into one assignment.
And what I mean by that is you're gonna
be doing a Breadth First search, very
similarly to what you did for spelling
suggestions, while you're also dynamically
building a tree, which is somewhat similar
to the work that you did in week four.
With the try.
So we're combining both Breadth First
search as well as dynamic tree generation
to essentially solve this puzzle.
Now again the puzzle, the game that we're
playing here, is trying to find a path
from one word to another with
the restriction that you can only make
one change at a time and whatever change
you make has to result in a real word.
In the previous videos,
we've already done a few examples, but
here's another example to help you
understand exactly how this process works.
I actually encourage you to try
this on your own in your head, or
on a piece of paper,
before you ever try to code this, so
you essentially see how is this gonna
work and how should you play the game.
As with all the previous assignments,
make sure you grab the starter code.
The starter code that we're gonna be
focusing on for this are WordPath and
WPTree.
So, first off, with WordPath,
WordPath is just an interface, and
all it has in it is a find path.
And this will just return that list of
words that go from word 1 to word 2.
Or it'll return null if
no such path exists.
Your class, WPTree is gonna
essentially implement this.
First off what I wanna focus on here is
that we have our WPTree that implements
WordPath and it has a tree that you're
gonna be building dynamically and
it also has, essentially, new brighter
words object that it's gonna be able to
reference essentially to perform
these single character mutations.
But before we dive into
the details of WPTree,
let's focus on WPTree node [SOUND].
So, we've actually given you entire
class WPTree node with [SOUND] all
the methods that I think you're
gonna need for this project.
So it has a word.
Each node is going to have the word.
It's gonna have a list of children
that are essentially words
which are one mutation away from,
this word.
And then they all have a parent.
The root node is gonna have this be null,
but then each of the children will have
their parents be again this
one character mutation away.
And each noted self is gonna have,
the constructor takes in both
the string and the parent's node.
Again, you would call this WPTree node as
null if you're creating the root node.
You're able to add children
to this tree node,
and you're able to return
the list of children [SOUND].
Most importantly we have this
build path to root method,
which I'll mention in just a second, but we also
have methods like get word and two string,
which will help you with debugging.
So what is this build path to root piece,
and
why are we having to
create this dynamic tree?
The difference between this, let me go
back to our write up real quickly [SOUND],
the difference, and this is all the code
that we were just walking through.
But the fundamental
difference between this and
the spelling suggestions is that once
you find the word you're looking for,
you have to be able to
reconstruct how you got here.
With spelling suggestions all we
wanted to do is determine the list of
potential suggestions.
But you didn't need to know how
you got to a specific suggestion.
In word path you have to
know how you got there.
And to know the path that you got
there requires essentially having
building this tree on the fly.
And what we've given which
is potentially useful here
is this method which will return back
to you the path back to your route.
If you're at a leaf node and
you wanna know how did you get here,
you can just call this
method to find that out.
Now you might be thinking well this is
a lot of code that you're gonna be using.
What are we required to do?
Well, you're required to do
the heart of the logic here.
Which is doing find path.
What we've done is given you just
like in the previous example [SOUND],
we've given you the algorithm.
Now, again, if you want a larger
challenge, feel free to just stop reading
this, don't look at the algorithm and try
to come up with the algorithm on your own.
But feel free to look at the algorithm.
This is a little bit
tricky to piece together.
What you'll find is a lot commonality
between this algorithm and
the spelling suggest algorithm.
With the key feature or
the the key difference
is that you're constantly building
this tree as you're working along.
Some hints as you're working
through this assignment.
First off, we create that nearby distance
one methods to allow us to restrict
to just real words.
The big advantage to doing so
back with the nearby words assignment
was that you could use this here.
So now you don't have to.
When you call the distance one,
you get back a list of words.
And if you use that boolean flag of true,
the one that restricts to just real words.
You don't need to prune
out non dictionary words.
You're only gonna get back real words.
And that's really useful.
We've also give you a method add child in
the WPTree node which will return back to
the node that it creates.
This is gonna be really helpful when
you're trying to construct your tree.
Methods print queue, and print queue is in
WPTree, and the method to string in WPTree
node, will be essential when you're
trying to debug and test your code.
I encourage you to do some
really small examples.
And then see what's being produced in
terms of the queue, as it's running,
to see whether or not it's doing
what you would expect it to do.
And lastly, think about corner cases.
And we have a couple corner cases here.
But you should be thinking about
other corner cases as well.
All right.
The last step is to upload and
submit your code to our graders.
So you'll submit WPTree.java.
You'll do so the same way we've
done with the previous assignments.
You'll go to My Submission.
You'll create your submission and
you'll submit WPTree.java and
you'll get greater output.
As the previous ones, I encourage you to
look at the greater output to see what
test cases you may have missed.
We also have within the source code
that we've provided WPTree greater,
which will show you essentially the cases
that we're testing for [SOUND].
If you run into any problems,
feel free to review the previous videos.
Also, feel free to post in learner forums,
and good luck on your project.