Welcome back.
Now that you're becoming proficient
at solving problems in Java it is
time to talk about some aspects of Java
that will help you solve larger problems.
You've probably heard that Java is
an object oriented language but
what exactly does that mean?
As the name suggests, your code works with
objects which you've already been doing
with objects from a wide variety of types,
strings, image resources,
and CSV records, just to name a few.
One of the important characteristics of
objects is that they encapsulate code and
data, putting them together
into one logical unit.
You have already written methods,
which are the code in an object.
However, you've not yet
made your own fields which describe
the data within an object.
As a familiar example, think about
strings which you have worked with a lot.
A string is an object and
it encapsulates code and data together.
For a string, the data is the sequence
of characters which it represents.
These characters are logically
inside of the string object.
You can also call a lot of different
methods on a string to operate on it and
not on the data inside of it.
You are familiar with many methods in
string such as indexOf and substring.
As you learn a bit more about
object oriented programming,
it is useful to be
precise with terminology.
A class defines a type,
specifically what fields and
methods are inside of
objects of that type.
Objects are instances of a class.
You can make many different objects from
the same class, which you do with new.
You have seen new before and
learned that you use it to make things,
but now you can be a bit more precise.
New creates a new instance of an object.
So why use an object oriented language?
What is the point of classes and objects?
A long time ago programming language
designers realized that it was helpful for
programmers to be able to
think in terms of objects
as they correspond more naturally
to how you think about the world.
They designed object oriented languages
around this idea along with a variety of
features which help programmers design and
write large programs.
You're going to learn some basic features
of object oriented programming here so
that you can create your own
classes with both code and data.
If you continue onwards to take our Java
Programming: Principles of Software Design
course after this,
you will learn some more principles and
techniques of object oriented programming.
So let's dive right in.