Welcome back.
To start learning concepts of
object oriented programming,
it is useful to take
an existing piece of code and
see how you could write it differently
in a more object oriented way.
Here is the code you wrote in a previous
lesson to perform encryption with
a CaesarCipher.
As you may recall one of
the parameters to this method
is the encryption key that you wanna use.
And the first thing you did with this code
was to compute the shifted alphabet based
on this key.
Here's a different way to write
the CaesarCipher class, which does exactly
the same thing but makes better use of
the object oriented nature of Java.
This class has two fields.
A field is a special kind of variable
which lives inside of an object
instead of inside of a method.
Here, the two fields are the strings for
the alphabet and
the shifted alphabet and they have been
moved outside of the encrypt method.
Notice that they are now declared inside
of the class, but outside of any method.
These are now data that
are encapsulated in your object.
When you make a CaesarCipher object,
it will have these two fields,
which any code inside that
class can refer to by name.
Next, notice that there is some code
here which looks like a method,
where we forgot to write the return type,
and named it the same as the class.
This code is actually a constructor, which
means code that gets run to initialize
an object when it is created using new.
This constructor takes in the key as a
parameter and initializes the alphabet and
shifted alphabet fields using
the same approach you used before.
If you look further down in this
implementation of the CaesarCipher,
the encrypt method looks
mostly the same as before but
it no longer takes the key as a parameter,
nor does it compute the shifted alphabet.
But the rest of the code is the same.
In fact, the code uses the alphabet and
shifted alphabet fields in the object,
even though these are not
declared inside the method.
This code is allowed to use them
because it is inside the object.
So it can use any fields
within the object.
An illustration helps understand the
differences between these two approaches.
In the old code,
a CaesarCipher object held no data.
When you do new CaesarCipher,
you pass in no arguments and
create an object with nothing in it.
When you call encrypt,
you pass the message and
the key and
the method returns the encrypted message.
In the new way,
each CaesarCipher object contains a key.
Now when you do new CaesarCipher,
you pass in the key and
the object you have created
stores that key inside of itself.
When you call encrypt on such an object
you pass in only the message.
The key is already in the object and
it still returns the same
encrypted message as before.
So if these two implementations
produce the same result
what are the benefits of
an object oriented approach?
When you encapsulate the key
inside of the cipher object,
you have one thing that is capable of
taking a message and encrypting it.
That makes a nice logical unit to
think about, a thing that does a task.
You do not need to separately
track the key and pass it in.
For small programs,
such as the ones you have written so
far, that may not seem like a big deal.
However, as you solve larger
programs with more complex code,
this design idea will help you immensely.
Now that you have seen an example of these
ideas in action, the rest of the lesson
will teach you about the details
of the technique you just saw.