Hi.
Now that you know a bit about
object oriented concepts.
It's time to go a bit deeper
into the idea of fields,
which are also called instance variables.
Remember that when we redesigned our
CaesarCipher to be more object oriented,
we created two fields.
One for the alphabet, and
one for the shiftedAlphabet.
These fields are declared inside of
the class, but outside of any method.
They belong to the object and are created
when new is called to create an object.
Either in code you write, or
when you create an object in BlueJ
that's shown on the object workbench.
These fields are part of the object and
exist as long as the object exists.
What does all this mean?
Every CaesarCipher object you
create has its own alphabet and
its own shifted alphabet.
This is why fields are also
called instance variables.
They act like variables,
where there's one variable per
instance of the object you create.
What does this really mean?
Let's look more deeply at fields and
instance variables.
Every CaesarCipher object has its own copy
of the alphabet and the shifted alphabet.
You can make different
CaesarCipher objects and
each will have its own
inference variables.
These variables are specific
to the instance.
If you create three CaesarCiphers,
with three different keys.
Each has its own copy of these fields
with potentially different values.
One cipher might have a shifted
alphabet of QRS for example.
Based on the integer shift value
passed to the constructor.
While another object might have MNO as
the shift value and the third object
could have HIJ as it's instance variable
set again when the object is constructed.
To call a method like
encrypt on an object,
you'll typically use a variable
name like cc and you'll cc.encrypt.
You can also call a method from
an object on the BlueJ object workbench.
These objects have names too.
And when you call .encrypt for example,
the method will use the values of
the fields in the object you
used to call the method.
Like CC, if you wrote CC.encrypt.
Calling encrypt on this CaesarCipher
will use it's QRS shifted alphabet.
So when we call .encrypt and
provide the message,
first legion attack east flank,
as the parameter.
The QRS alphabet is used to create
the encrypted version that you see here.
In the same way,
calling encrypt on this CaesarCipher
object will use its MNO shifted alphabet.
This is the principal of encapsulation.
The method and the data
are logically inside of the object.
And the method acts on the data
inside the object that it lives in.
As you can see here, calling encrypt
uses this shifted alphabet and
we see a different encrypted
version of the same message.
Because the field shifted off of
it's starch, with MNO, is used here.
Finally, using this object
with HIJ as the field,
will result in a different
encrypted message.
When encrypt is called, the encrypt
code uses this shifted alphabet,
of this instance.
And the encrypt code creates
the encrypted message you see here.
Fields, or instance variables, are very
important concepts in designing and
using classes.
Since they can be accessed by
every method in the class.
Like encrypt, that you see here,
and the constructor as well.
As you begin to design our own classes,
and think about the fields and
methods to put in these classes.
Here are a few design principles
you should keep in mind.
The first is that a class name
should correspond to a noun.
Classes describe things.
Each object you make for
a particular class is one of that thing.
Let's think about the classes
you've seen so far for this course.
Strings, pixels, CSV records.
Each of these is a noun.
It describes a thing.
A class could be a car for example.
That's a noun.
And then the methods and
fields would correspond to
things that a car can do.
Methods, on the other hand, are verbs.
They're what you do to or with an object.
Things like get pixel,
set care at, or encrypt.
Sometimes method names don't sound like
verbs, such as substring or index of.
But these describe actions,
get a subscreen, or find the index of.
The program has just shortened the name.
For the car,
a method might be accelerate or brake.
These are things a car can do.
For example, invoking a method would
make the car go faster or stop suddenly.
Fields, or instance variables,
are important class concepts.
Fields are also nouns.
And should describe things the class has.
The string class might have a field for
a sequence of characters.
A sequence of characters is a thing and
a string has one of these things.
Similarly an image might have many pixels.
Fields can also be adjectives as they
describe the properties of an object.
For example, a pixel might have a field,
or fields describing its color.
That could be an adjective giving more
information about the properties of
the pixel.
For cars, fields could include
things a car has, nouns.
Like an engine with a certain number of
cylinders, or wheels of a certain size,
for cars adjectives might
describe the color of the car.
Or the kind of engine the car has or
the type of wheel.
As you get started making
more complex classes,
we will provide guidance on fields and
methods you should make.
But think about these designs
principles as you write your code.
As you gain more experience,
you'll want to start designing classes
on your own, based on these ideas.
Happy coding acceleration.