>> Welcome back.
In this lesson, you are going to learn
about the two visibility modifiers that
you saw in the object-oriented
version of the CaesarCipher.
Public, which was used here, and
private, which was used here.
There are two other visibility modifiers,
however.
Explaining them requires some
more advanced concepts, so
you will only learn about these now.
When you declare something, whether it is
a class, field, method, or constructor as
public it means that any code, anywhere
in your program can access that thing.
Code from any class can call a public
method, read or update a public field,
use a public constructor when making
an object, and make use of a public class.
By contrast, when you declare
something private, it tells Java that
only code inside of this particular class
can see the thing you declare private.
These two fields are declared private so
all of the code inside of the CaesarCipher
class can read and update them but
code outside of the CaesarCipher class
is not allowed to access them at all.
So what happens if you write code that
tries to access private fields or
methods from outside the class?
The Java compiler will give
you an error like this,
which says that you are not
allowed to do that.
In general,
when you get this sort of error,
it either means that you
are improperly using a class.
Especially if it's a class that
is part of an existing library.
Or that you have designed a class and
made something private that should not be.
So why do you want to
declare things as private?
After all, it seems like it would just
be easier to make everything public.
So you can just access whatever you want,
wherever you want.
Remember the idea of distraction?
The principle that you want to separate
the interface from the implementation.
Restricting the visibility of
the implementation details
helps you enforce abstractions you design.
You can make the interface of a class,
all the methods that other classes
are supposed to call public, and
then you can make
the implementation details private.
No other class should know about
the implementation details directly.
And declaring them private lets you
enforce that rule in your code.
In our CaesarCypher example, you want
other classes to be able to call encrypt.
But they should not know about
the implementation details,
such as the fact that you made
a variable called shifted alphabet.
Keeping these details private
means that you can change them and
be sure that no other code relies on
the private implementation details.
As you start to think about designing
your own classes, there are a few general
pieces of guidance to get you started
on how to choose public or private.
First, fields are generally part of
the implementation of an object.
So they typically should be private.
For methods it depends on what
the purpose of the method is.
If the method is part of the interface
you want your class to have,
that is part of the behaviors you want
it to provide to other pieces of code,
you should declare that method public.
On the other hand,
some methods are helpers.
You array them to abstract out specific
complex tasks which are not meant for
other classes to call.
They just help accomplish
the public interface.
These methods should be private so that
only the code in your class can call them.
For classes,
you should always declare them public.
As you become more skilled in Java, you
will learn some more advanced topics that
lead to situations where you
might want non-public classes.
But for now, always use public.
Likewise, for constructors, you should
always make these public for now.
Typically, constructors are part of
the public interface of a class.
They specify how to make an instance.
There are situations where non-public
constructors are appropriate.
But as with non-public classes,
these only come up when you have
learned some more advanced topics.
So for now,
you should just make constructors public.
Great.
So now you know what public and
private mean.
Why they are useful and
some general guidelines for
how to use them in your own classes.
Thank you.