Welcome.
The last object oriented concept
you're going to learn in this lesson
is constructors.
Recall that the object oriented
CaesarCipher we wrote had a constructor,
which took the key as a parameter and
initialized the fields on the object.
When you want to write a constructor,
there are certain rules for declaring it.
The first is that its name has to be
exactly the name of the class it is in.
Here, the constructor's name
must be CaesarCipher because
it's in a class called CaesarCipher.
The second rule is that the constructor
has no return type, not even void.
Normally you would write a method's return
type here between public and the name
of the method, but for constructor you do
not need to write anything between them.
Like a normal method, a constructor
has its parameter list in parentheses.
You can make constructors with any
number and types of parameters you want.
You can have no parameters
to a constructor or several.
Here we have one parameter of type int,
the key.
Finally, a constructor has a body,
like a normal method.
You can write whatever code you want in
the constructor's body to specify how
to initialize the object.
Constructors are not quite
like normal methods, however.
You do not call them directly.
Instead, they are automatically
as part of newing an object.
When you create a new object, the
constructor is invoked to initialize that
object immediately after
the new object is made.
This is one of the great
benefits of constructors.
They allow you to specify how an object
should be initialized, and you can be sure
that code will always be run for
every object, as soon as it is made.
You do not have to worry about
bugs in your code from forgetting
to call some initialization code.
What happens if you do not write
a constructor for your class?
Whenever you write no constructors as
you've been doing up to this point,
the Java compiler will provide
a default constructor for you.
The constructor that the compiler
provides looks like this.
It is public, which you should recall,
means any piece of code may use
it to initialize an object.
It takes no arguments, so you would pass
no arguments when you create new objects.
And it does not do anything, there is no
special initialization of the object.
Now that you know the rules
about constructors,
let's see how a constructor works.
Let's suppose you had a line of code
somewhere else in your program like this,
CaesarCipher cc = new CaesarCipher(22).
This line of code asks Java to make a new
instance of the CaesarCipher class and
initialize it by passing
22 to your constructor.
Let us see what this does by starting when
Java is just about to execute this line.
The first thing it does is
create a new variable, cc.
Then it creates a new instance
of the CaesarCipher class.
That means you have a new object with its
own copy of the fields of that class,
alphabet and shiftedAlphabet.
Then it calls the constructor,
passing 22 for the key.
Once inside the constructor,
Java begins executing the code you
wrote to initialize the object.
This code initializes alphabet,
then initializes shiftedAlphabet.
Having finished the constructor,
Java returns back to where
you are creating the object.
The key was just a parameter
to the constructor so
it only exists during that call.
However, the fields are part of the object
so they continue to exist in it.
And then finishes the assignment
statement by initializing the cc variable
to the newly created object.
Great, now you know the basic rules of
how to write constructors, what they do,
and how they are used
to initialize objects.
Thank you.