In this lesson,
you'll learn some of the basic concepts
of object oriented programming.
You'll learn about encapsulation,
the idea of putting code and
data together in an object,
such as the methods of the object act on
the data that's inside the same object.
You learned about fields,
which are also called instance variables.
They let you declare data that
should be inside of objects.
And you learned about visibility
modifiers, private and
public, which let you expose or
restrict access to fields and
methods, so you can enforce abstractions
and provide the interface you want.
Finally, you learned about constructors,
which let you write code specifying how
to initialize the objects you create.
When you do object oriented programming,
it's called OO programming,
giving you OO7, license to code.