[MUSIC]
In this video, we're gonna talk about
a new data structure called a trie.
So by the end of this video,
you'll be able to explain what a trie is
as well as describe the algorithms for
inserting data into the trie and
finding whether data exists in the trie.
So to start off, let's go back to the test
that you're going to have in your
programming assignment, which is you wanna
figure out whether the words the user
is typing into the screen, into
the text box are actually legal words.
In other words,
do they appear in a dictionary?
So we can think about representing this
dictionary in a number of ways and
one reasonable way to
represent this dictionary
is using the data structure that Mia just
taught you about, the binary search tree.
And if we assume the binary
search tree is balanced,
then the tree might look
something like this.
So this is a very simple dictionary.
It only has six words in it, but you can
see that they're arranged in a binary
search tree according to
their alphabetical ordering.
So the words that are closer
to a are over on the left and
the words that are closer to the end
of the alphabet are over on the right.
Now this is a perfectly fine way to
organize words into a dictionary, but
we can see that in a binary search tree,
the binary search tree doesn't
take advantage of some of
the structure of the words themselves.
It just does these pairwise
words comparisons to figure out,
which word comes first in the alphabet in
order to arrange the words in the tree.
But even with these six words,
we can see that there's some
shared structure to them.
For example, ear, east and eat,
all contain ea right at the start and
the binary search tree representation
is not using that information at all.
So now we're gonna look at
a data structure called a trie,
which takes advantage of the structure
of the keys that it stores.
So the idea behind a trie is,
it's gonna use the key itself to navigate
the search through the structure.
Now the word trie,
actually comes from the word retrieval.
So it's the middle part
of the word retrieval,
because these keys help you
retrieve the keys themselves.
The structure of the key helps you
retrieve the key in this structure.
However, trie, T-R-I-E in retrieval is
pronounced the same way as T-R-E-E.
And it would be very confusing
if we were talking about a tree,
because we're already talking about trees,
T-R-E-E.
So they decided to call T-R-I-E, trie
to disambiguate it from the word tree.
Because in fact, tries are trees.
Hopefully, you're not thoroughly confused.
Let's go talk about tries.
So here is at the representation
of a trie for
that small dictionary of words that I
just looked at in the binary search tree.
So we have the same six
words represented here.
A, at, ate, ear, east and eat and
I'm going to talk to you
about how this try works.
Now right after the bat, you will notice
some differences between the binary search
tree and this trie representation,
which as I imagine is also a tree.
One thing that you'll notice is that not
every node in this tree represents a word.
So you'll see some of the nodes, those
blue shaded nodes do represent words.
But some of the nodes, the white
nodes are just internal nodes and
they don't actually represent
any word in this dictionary.
The other difference you're going to note
is that these tries can have more than
two children at each node.
So a binary search tree
always has two children,
these tries can have
more than two children.
In this case, we'll use a restricted set
of the alphabet, only five characters.
And so each trie node can have up to
five children or it may have less,
all of the nodes here have
fewer than five children.
But in this way,
they're going to be kind of bushier and
wider than our binary search trees, which
always have two, one or zero children.
So with an understanding
of those two differences,
let's talk about how this trie works and
how it's put togethe and
we'll do this in the context
of finding a word in the trie.
So let's have looking for the word eat.
The way I'm going to find
the word eat in the trie
is I'm going to start up here at the root.
And then as I mentioned before,
the structure of the word,
the structure of the key, eat is the key
that I'm looking for is actually going to
provide me with information about
how to find that key in the trie and
the information it provides is
the characters in the word itself.
So I'll start by looking at the first
character in the word, which is e and then
you can see that array has one entry for
each potential character in my alphabet.
So what I'll do is I'll find the entry for
e, the first character in my word,
it's there.
And then if there's a link there,
which there is,
I'll follow that link to
the next node down the trie.
So that's the link to that node, given
that I've seen an e as my first character.
Then I'll look ahead at my next character,
which is a.
I'll find the location that links to
the next node, given the character a,
I'll follow that link and
get to the next node in the trie.
I repeat the process, I find the next
character in the word, which is t.
I find the link that I have to follow,
given that I've now seen a t
from this position and
I'll follow that link to the next node.
Now at this point, I look at my word and I
find that I have no more characters left.
So now I'm stuck and I go back and look
at the node where I ended up stuck and
I ask, does this node say
that it represents a word?
And in this case, we see that it's shaded.
So yes, this node does in fact,
say that it represents a word.
And in fact, I'm storing the word it
represents right there in that node,
which is eat.
It's not strictly necessary to store
the word that's represented by
a node in the trie node itself,
because you can always recover it by
tracing down the trie as
you follow the links, but
it does make things slightly easier at
the expense of using a bit more space.
So in your primary assignment,
we will have you store the words in
those trie nodes that end words.
So that's how you find a word in the trie.
Let's look now at how you
add a word to the trie.
So now let's say we want to
add the word eats to the trie.
So that's not currently in this trie and
you'll see how we're going to take
advantage of a lot of the structure that's
already in the trie when we add this word.
So what we're gonna do is start off
exactly the same way that we did
when we found the word eat, we'll
start by looking at the first letter.
First, we'll start at the root,
then we'll look at the first letter e and
follow the link that we should follow
if we're looking at the letter e.
So we follow that down on the next node,
our next letter is a.
We find the link to the node for
the character a,
we follow that down to the next node,
we find t.
Follow that down to the next node and
now we see that we have an s.
But if we look in the location
where the link for s should be,
we'll see that it's null.
That indicates that this
word is not in the trie.
So if we were looking for the word eats,
we would conclude at this point,
it's not in the trie.
But given that we're trying to add it,
what we need to do is actually create
a new node that will represent that next
character s down further in the trie.
So we create that new node and
you'll notice that when we create it,
it's not shaded,
because we don't quite know yet
that this is the end of the word and
we link it in to the character
array above at position s, because
that's the character that we added.
Now at this point, we see that we're out
of letters in the word we're trying to add
and so
we can take that node we just created and
flag it as an end of word node and
add the word itself, eats to that node.
So that's basically all there is
to adding a node to this trie,
adding a word to the try.
Now eats is in the trie and if we were
to look for it, we would find it.
So coming up of next, we'll talk about
a little bit about some of the advantages
that tries have over binary search
trees in terms of their performance.