[SOUND] Now that we've seen what tris are,
let's compare
them in terms of their performance
to binary search trees.
So by the end of this video,
you'll be able to do just that.
Compare the performance of binary
search trees and tries for
storing dictionaries of words.
So to start off, let's think about storing
our dictionary as a binary search tree.
So what I wanna know is,
if you have n words in your dictionary,
how long in the worst case might it
take to find a word in this dictionary.
In particular to find out that
a word is not in this dictionary.
And you can assume that the binary
search tree will always stay balanced.
Okay.
So it takes order logn
because this balance tree
is guaranteed to have a bound
on it's height of logn.
And in order to conclude that a word is
not in the tree you essentially need to
search it all the way from
the root down to the bottom.
So it's going to be, it's going to
depend on the height of the tree.
So logn is not bad.
As I mentioned,
binary search trees are not a bad way
to store dictionaries of words, but
let's ask the same question now for a tri.
Let's consider the worst case, finding
a word that's not in the dictionary.
How long is that going to take
using a tri representation?
Okay, so again this relates
to the height of the tri.
But this time, what determines
the height is not the number of words
in the dictionary, but
in fact the length of the longest word.
So, in the worst case,
if we're looking for
a really long word that's not in the
dictionary we're going to have to traverse
that many levels down the tri,
one level for each character in the word.
So, now we've got one situation
where it's taking logn steps,
logn comparisons to figure out that
the word is not in the dictionary.
And the other situation, where we've
got on the order of the number of
characters in the word to figure out
whether the word is not in the dictionary.
So which one is better,
how does this compare?
Well we need to sort of thing
about what could n be and
how long are our words in general.
If we take an estimate of a number of
words in a complete English dictionary,
might be around, say 250,000.
If we take logn of 250,000
that's about more or less 18.
So in the worst case, if our words are not
in the dictionary we're going to have
to take 18 comparisons to conclude
that word is not in the dictionary.
And if the word is not in the dictionary,
we'll always need about 18 comparisons,
because the height of that tree is
about 18, because it's balanced.
On the other hand, for our try,
we would only need 18 steps
if we were trying to check a word
that was 18 characters long.
That's a pretty long word.
And yes, in the worst case,
you're going to have to deal with words
that are 18 characters or even longer.
But in general, most of the words
that you're going to be looking for
that are not in your dictionary, most
misspelled words are relatively short.
They're going to be five characters,
six characters, seven characters long.
So this kind of illustrates that
tris are going to be faster.
Right?
I'd rather do seven comparisons
to conclude that my word's
not in my dictionary
than 18 comparisons every time I need to
conclude the word is not in my dictionary.
So these are both good representations but
tris turn out to be slightly better
than binary search trees for
that performance reason alone.
Now in the next video we're gonna talk
about some implementation details,
because you'll be implementing
these tris as part of your project.
As well as talk about one more advantage
that tris have over binary search trees,
which is the ability to implement the
autocomplete functionality that you'll be
building into your project.