[MUSIC]
So finally in this video, we're gonna look
at the implementation details of Tries,
and we'll also look at the algorithm for
doing auto-complete.
So by the end of this video,
you'll be able to implement these Tries.
So you'll be all set to go for
your project, and
you'll also be able to implement
that auto-complete algorithm.
So going back to our Trie,
we'll see that just like
the link structures we looked at before,
just like trees.
The key structural piece of the Trie
implementation is going to be
the node class.
We're gonna implement a class called
TrieNode, and let's focus on that first.
So the TrieNode has a number of
things it needs to represent.
One of the things it needs to keep
track of is, does this node end a word?
Because some of the nodes in the Trie
end words, while others do not.
So we'll keep a boolean flag to indicate
whether this particular node represents
a complete word or not.
Another thing that we wanna
store in these nodes,
is the actual text representing the word
that is represented by this node.
We only really need to represent this
text if it actually does end a word.
So otherwise, it'll just be empty.
And again as I mentioned before,
this is an optional field.
You don't have to maintain this field,
because you can always recover
it by tracing down the Trie.
But it makes things a little bit easier to
implement if you do maintain this field.
So, we'll recommend in your implementation
that you do keep this field.
The last piece of the TrieNode,
the most important piece are the links
to the children of this node.
Now, in a binary search tree,
you could represent these links as just
a left pointer and a right pointer.
But in a Trie we have more than
two children, potentially.
So one way we can
represent this is an array.
So we might have an array of,
in this case, length five, because we
have five characters we're dealing with.
But if we were using the whole
alphabet we might have 26 characters.
Or if we wanted to use both lower case and
upper case letters,
we might have twice that many.
And in every single node,
we would want that big array
to have a potential pointer to
a child coming from that character.
So, we might represent that just
like this using an array list.
But if we go back and look at the tribe,
what we can see is that
most of the time a lot of these
entries are going to be empty.
So even in a complete dictionary
we're gonna have a very sparse usage
of this array of pointers
to the next level down.
So that's a lot of wasted space, because
an arrays have to be declared to be
a certain length in order to
access each element in that array.
And we don't necessarily want
to waste all that space.
So at this point, you may be thinking aha,
I know what we can use.
We can use a linked list,
because linked lists grow dynamically,
to accommodate the number
of elements in them.
Well that's true, but
the problem with using a linked list is
that then we don't have that association.
Between a particular position in the list
and the character that it represents.
Here, we're really relying on that
association in order to do those links.
So for these reasons,
we're not going to use an array
list to represent the children.
And we're not going to
use a linked list either,
what we're going to use is
something called a hash map.
Now, we'll go into much more
detail about hash maps and
hash tables in the next
module in this course.
But if you took our course one then you're
already familiar with the concept of
a hash map.
We used then back in our course
one in this specialization.
The idea behind a hash map
is it's going to associate
a key with a particular value.
And in this case, our keys are gonna to
be the characters that are in our words.
And the values are going to be
the children nodes in our tribe.
So you have here
the documentation page for
the hash map class that's built into java.
And we encourage you to look around and
figure out which methods you want
to use in your implementation.
And pay particular attention to
the methods put, which associates a key
with the value, and get which gets
back a value for a particular key.
They'll be a couple more
methods you want to use.
Those are gonna be the main ones you'll
be using when you implement the find and
insert methods in your Trie.
So that's the gist of a TrieNode.
Now let's bring that back to
the trie data structure itself.
Of course,
a trie consists of a bunch of trie nodes,
which are all linked together
via these children links.
So in order to store the entire trie,
all you really need to do is store
a point or a reference to the root node.
So your overall trie data structure,
your dictionary trie,
is really just gonna have one main
pointer, which is the pointer to the root.
And then it's going to implement all the
functionality that we just talked about,
so finding a word in the trie,
inserting a word into the trie.
And then for the last piece of
functionality you'll need for
your project, it's going to implement
this auto-complete functionality.
So let's take a look at how we can
do auto-complete using the trie
data structure.
So we have our partial word,
our word stem ea, and
we want to auto-complete that word.
So what are all the possible completions
that could result from the stem ea?
Well the first step to
solving this problem is to
first find the stem in the trie.
So to do that you use the same
algorithm that we talked about before.
You start at the root and navigate down by
following the appropriate child pointers,
given the characters in the stem.
And maybe you'll find yourself at that
bottom most highlighted yellow node.
And from there you're out of stem words,
so
now you're ready to generate
the auto complete options.
Now notice that you may end up may
be a word and may not be a word,
depending on whether the stem is a word or
not.
But from there, all you need to do
is explore downward from that node.
Finding all the words that you can
find down from that particular node.
And this is just a tree traversal, which
Leo talked to you about in the first or
second lesson in this module.
You can do any kind of tree traversal, and
that will give you a number
of auto-complete options.
But if you want to generate the auto
completions from shortest to longest,
then what you're going to want to do is
perform a level order tree traversal.
Or as Leo explained,
a breath first search,
starting from the node you found when
you navigated based on your stem.
All the way down either to
the bottom of your trie or
until you've generated enough words for
the auto-complete.
So that's it, that's all you
need to know about Tries and
you're ready to do your project.