[MUSIC]
Welcome to the module four project.
This project is gonna be a lot of fun
because you're going to get to enable
this Spelling Suggestions,
not suggestions yet, but
at least the ability to flag incorrectly
spelled words, and most excitingly,
this AutoComplete functionality.
So, you're gonna be adding some
spelling help into your application.
So, let me just give you a demo
of what this is gonna look like.
So, if I turn on Spelling Suggestions,
what you'll see when you type,
is that as I type, Hello,
as long as the words are typed correctly,
there's no problem.
But if I type something like sentenc,
like that and I forget the e,
you can see that this word is
going to be flagged as misspelled.
Now, in the next week,
next week you'll be able to add the
ability to right-click on this word, and
get some spelling suggestions of
what I might have meant to type.
But that's not going to be
implemented until next week.
So for now, you'll just see that
it's flagged as a misspelled word.
But even more excitingly, what you're
going to get to do is, you're going to get
to turn on this AutoComplete functionality
and have it actually work correctly.
So, now when I start to type,
you can see that I can have all
of the possibilities of what I might
be trying to type displaying for me.
Or at least it just displays
six right now, so I can choose,
like maybe I meant to say sentence,
oh, look I did.
So, I can just choose that and
then go on, sentence this, and
you can see that sometimes it doesn't
come up with what I'm looking for,
cuz it's only showing
me six possibilities.
But it then almost always does,
once I type a little bit more.
So, this is really fun piece of the
project, and I hope you're looking forward
to learning everything you need to know,
in order to add this functionality.