[MUSIC]
In this lesson, we begin to
start working with hash tables.
And hash tables are one of
my favorite data structures.
In fact,
when I'm working on software projects,
I find myself using hash
table more often than not.
So, what we're gonna try
to do in this video.
By the end of this video you should
be able to describe why hash tables
are valuable, you should be able to
understand the role of a hash function.
So let's start this off
with a thought experiment.
Let's say I'm trying to keep
track of integers in a set.
And by in a set I just mean is
95 in the set, or is it not?
Is 100 in the set, or is it not?
And you know the possible integers
that could be in this set
are bounded between 0 and
less than a million.
Now you could store this as
an array of a million booleans.
If I did this, how long would it take for
me to add an integer into my set?
Go ahead and answer this as an NVO quiz,
and I'll see you in a moment.
I hope the NVO quiz made sense.
At this point,
your pretty comfortable with arrays, so
you should be recognizing that if I want
to access an individual element of array
I can do this at essentially
all at one time.
I can do this in constant time.
Arrays are, in fact, incredibly fast and
the reason they're so fast is that if
you know where an array starts in memory
you can determine the address of any
element just by using the index.
So, if I know the address of an element
in an array, I can look this up really
quickly because essentially accessing an
address in memory is all of one operation.
Now, with a hardware background I
have to put a quick caveat on this.
Different addresses may have different
access times as programs run
because of various constraints within the
hardware and within the operating system.
If you're curious about this more
advanced detail please look at
computer architecture courses or operating
system courses for some more answers.
But for right now, let's just assume
that this is a constant time operation.
You always get an answer back quickly.
So the idea behind a hash table is
if I knew an index for an element,
I could look immediately
into that array and find it.
And that's all we're gonna try to do.
Is we're gonna take a key, which is
the value we're trying to put in there.
And just figure out a way to
convert it into an index.
The way that we do this is to take a key
we'd run it through a hash function.
Which we'll be talking
about it momentarily and
this hash function has to be really fast.
It has to be constant time operation.
That's gonna produce for
us an index which we call a hash code.
We're gonna use that hash
code to point into the array.
You might notice that I have both an index
and data in the array, but really,
there's just data in the array.
I have the index there to help
us visualize how this works.
So, the core of this is really figuring
how to make a hash function that
works well.
So, let's start with some ideas here.
So, let's say,
I have an array of just five elements.
And I want to figure out a way of
hashing an element into an index.
So I've got the key three, and
I want to figure out how can
I turn that into an index?
Well if I'm working with an integer
three and I've got five elements,
I really just could use
three as the index, right?
Not really much I have to do there.
But what if I had 11?
Well I can't go to index 11 because
that's out of the bounds of the array.
So what could I do to make sure that
it has a value between zero and four?
Well I can use that
handy function modular.
So if I just do 11 modular five here,
this will give me an index
into that same array.
In fact of you look back at the previous
one, you look at the equality.
I could have just done three module of
five and that would have worked just fine.
In fact K mod N is a very common
hash function where K is the key and
N is the number of elements in the array.
But we won't necessarily
just want to store integers.
We might wanna store
things like characters.
So how would I work with character a?
Well, the nice thing about characters is I
can convert them to integers quite easily.
The ASCII representation for a is 97.
So after I converted to
the ASCII representation 97,
I can just do module 5 and
I get a hash code.
So working with characters isn't
gonna be very hard either.
Well, how might I work with a string?
Something like Hi?
Well, if I wanna work with Hi, again,
I can convert the characters into ASCII,
convert the characters into
their ASCII values of 72 and
105, add them in any module of five.
And again,
now I've got an index into this array.
And this is all we mean by
creating a hash function.
So now we have a basic
idea of a hash function.
I want you to take a moment and
think about this question and
we'll come back in a moment.
Welcome back.
So if you have two elements
that are considered equal,
they have to be able to hash
the same location, right?
If I have seven, it better hash
the same location as seven, right?
If two things are the same,
they better hash the same location.
And set,
that answer A is the correct response.
The problem with B,
is that B is actually false.
So as we saw before you could have
three module of five give you three.
But you could also have eight
module of five give you three.
So you can multiple things point to the
same index and that's called a collision.
Now let me give you
another example of that.
So if I have three, three mod five
gives me the hash code of three.
Again, if I have 13, 13 mod five
This is again a collision.
You can have multiple elements
pointing to the same index.
So, a key part in trying to figure out
a hash function is trying to minimize
these collisions.
We could spend a lot more time
on hash functions, but for
now we can just keep working
with this notion of K mod N.
What we'll do in the next series of videos
is look at how to deal with collisions
in hash tables.