[MUSIC]
In the last video,
we began working with hash tables.
Now one of the hardest parts to hash
tables is dealing with collisions.
So in this video,
we're gonna do two things.
You should be able to describe
alternative methods for
handling collisions in a hash table.
And you should be able to identify
some other challenges associated with
hash tables.
So, first off, let's talk about
where these collisions happen.
So I'm trying to do a hash table insert,
and I've got the value 9.
I'm gonna run it through my hash function.
We'll assume my hash function is K mod 7,
just like we talked
about in the last video.
I'm gonna run that through and, again,
I had 7 because I have 7
elements in the array.
I'm gonna run it through the hash
function, and it produces an index or
a hash code of 2.
That's gonna allow me now to
insert 9 into the hash table.
Next thing I want to insert is 16.
So I run 16 through my hash function.
That also produces a hash code of 2,
and now what do I do?
This is a collision.
I already have 9 in there at
the place I wanna put 16, and
I can't keep both in
one spot in the array.
So what we're gonna do is talk about
really two solutions for this.
And the first of these
solutions is linear probing.
And the idea behind linear probing is
just look for the next open spot and
put the value there.
So what we do here is we have a collision
at location two or index two, and
what I'm gonna do is look at the very
next location and see, is it open?
And because it is open,
I'm just gonna put 16 there.
So that's essentially how we're
gonna work with linear probing.
So let's do a couple more examples.
So now I try to insert 3.
I do K mod 7 again on 3.
That's gonna produce the index 3.
I go to index 3, and
I get another collision, right,
because now 16's in my way.
So, I'm gonna look for
the next open element and place 3 there.
Let's do one more of these.
Now, I'm gonna try to do a search.
I'm gonna check to see whether or
not 2 is in my hash table.
So I'm gonna run 2 through my has
function to give me the hash code 2.
And I'm gonna look at the next two,
and I find nine there.
But I can't stop there,
right, because I may have put 2 in a later
location because of linear probing.
So now I have to look at the next element
to see, is there something there?
So, first I look at 9, then I look at 16.
And 16's not 2, but there's still more
valid data, so I have to keep looking.
So now I'm gonna look at 3.
3 is not 2 either, but
I have to keep looking.
And I finally find an open spot,
and that tells me 2's not in there.
Now you'll notice that I just had to look
at a number of spots just to find out
whether or not 2 was in my hash table.
And this is disconcerting, because again,
we like hash tables because we can look,
the goal was to look at one spot and
immediately get an answer.
So there are some ways.
So this is gonna get particularly
problematic when the hash table gets full.
And we'll talk little bit more
about what we mean by full and
how we're gonna address
that as we go forward.
I do wanna mention there's another
approach you can take other than
linear probing.
And that's called random probing.
And the idea there is just essentially,
instead of going just the next step over
to see for an open spot, you essentially
try to jump a random number of steps,
based on seeding at random with a key.
Now, there's a whole bunch of different
trade-offs associated with that.
But, most importantly, the cost of doing
random operations tends to be expensive.
So, this has problems as well.
The second solution I wanna talk about
after linear probing is separate chaining.
Now, the idea behind separate
chaining is pretty simple actually.
Instead of just keeping a single element
within my array, why don't I keep a list?
So when I insert 9, I'm gonna do
the same hash function as before.
It's gonna give me the index 2.
I'm gonna look at index 2, and
I'm gonna add 9 to my list.
Now when I try to insert 16,
I'm gonna look at my location at index 2,
I'm gonna find the list.
Now the list already has 9 in it,
but it's a list.
So I can just add 16 to it.
So it's actually a really clean solution.
So just keep essentially a linked list
at each location in your hash table.
It's often preferred in terms of
implementations, but it has it's own set
of drawbacks, which are a little bit
too advanced for this topic right now.
All right, I do want to mention two
last challenges with hash tables.
The first is we're talking about
when the hash table gets too full,
you're going to need to do
something to help fix things.
When hash tables get, and
the rule of thumb is about 70%,
about 70% full you're
gonna want to resize it.
Essentially create a larger hash table
in order to avoid these collisions and
all these problems that come up.
The problem with resizing is because
we're working with arrays and
arrays are essentially statically sized,
it requires me to create
an entirely new table.
Create a new hash function and
reinsert everything.
This can be expensive.
And the only time you're going to
be really concerned about expense,
is if you're working
on a real time system.
So if you're landing the space shuttle and
the space shuttle's essentially doing
a hash table operation and it decides to
resize, and all of a sudden you can't use
your controls, that's not gonna work okay.
So that's one of the concerns you might
have with hash tables is just this
resize cost.
The second challenge is that hash tables
don't have an implicit ordering of data
within the structure itself.
So thinking back to our binary
search trees, if I want to know,
if I want to iterate through
all the data in order,
I can pretty easily walk this binary
search tree to say A B C E L M Q.
But there's no such ordering
within a hash table.
So if you actually want an ordered
list of all the elements,
you have to pull them out and
essentially sort them.
So when we're thinking about hash tables,
realize that the big pros to hash
tables is that it has, on average case,
O of 1 lookup, insert, and remove,
and that's pretty fantastic.
But there are a couple of drawbacks.
The first is that those resizing costs can
impact you if you're working say on a real
time system and
that there is no implicit data ordering.
You want to keep that in mind
when you're selecting whether or
not a hash table is gonna work for
your project.
So in summary, we've looked at a couple
of solutions for handling collisions.
The first was linear probing, and
the second was separate chaining.
We've also seen some additional
challenges for hash tables, and
next what we're gonna do is start looking
at how to use hash tables in Java.