[MUSIC]
Hi, my name is Maya.
And I took a class about data structures.
And for
most of the class I was doing well.
I was understanding everything.
But then we got to hash tables,
and for some reason it was just so
confusing, and
I didn't know what I was gonna do.
So, I decided to go to my study group.
And my friends were talking through it.
They were like, okay, I was understanding.
But then, when I went back home
to work on it, I was lost again.
I was like,
is it my algorithm that's not right?
Is it maybe I don't understand
what hash table should do?
I wasn't sure.
So I was like, okay.
I started early so I can just take
a break and I'll come back to it.
So I decided to go to sleep and
it was really funny, because while I was
sleeping, I remember just waking up and
was like wait, I know how to do this.
So I just got down from my bunk bed,
went to my desk, wrote some notes.
Went back to sleep, and
when I woke up I found out that it was,
maybe, taking a break.
Or maybe because I just got to move
away from the material for a little bit,
it kind of got to soak in and
I understood it better.
And that's my story on hash tables.