[MUSIC]
In the last couple of videos, we started
to see how Hash Tables can be useful.
We also looked at how Hash Tables
deal with the problem of collisions.
In this video, I want to focus in
on how to use Hash Tables in Java.
And specifically I'm going to focus on
the difference between Hash Sets and
Hash Maps, cause this is often
a point of confusion for students.
So by the end of this video, you should be
able to explain the differences between
those two data structures.
So a hash set just tells you whether or
not an item is in the set or not.
So in this example, car is in a set.
Boat is in a set.
But train is not.
So you just store the things
that are in the set,
and you don't store
the things that are not.
And this is gonna be incredibly useful for
a dictionary.
So if you wanna just store the words
that are in the English dictionary,
a set is probably
the right way to do that.
And the methods you'll wanna use for
this are, add,
which is essentially just add
an element into the set, and contains,
which just tells you whether or
not the set contains that item or not.
Think about hash maps.
Hash maps actually store two things.
They store a key, which is what
we've been working with all along,
along with with some extra data,
or which we call value.
Now this is nice if you wanna
associate some data with each key.
An example of this might be let's
say you are working on Facebook and
you have a friend.
So I have my friend Ivan up here and
we have had a whole bunch of
text communications on Facebook.
And Facebook decides to
store that communication.
Well what they might want to keep is
essentially Ivan in the hash map because
that's my friend and then we will have
a whole bunch of a linked list there which
is essentially just stores the various
texts that I've had with him in the past.
Another example might be if you just
want to store a movie database.
You might have the name of
the movie in one place, and
then you may have a list
of actors as the value.
So when you're working with a HashMap.
You're gonna have to always
have both a key and a value.
And the methods you're almost
certainly gonna use are get,
which will get you back the value for
a given key, and put,
which allows you to put in both a key and
a value into the HashMap.
So now that we understand
more how to do this in Java,
I just wanna remind us really quickly
about the Hash Table Key Points.
Hash tables are fantastic
in the average case.
They're O one for lookup,
insert, and remove.
They do have some concerns associated
with them, in terms of Resizing Costs.
And the fact that they have no implicit
data ordering as part of the structure.