[NOISE]
>> So
in Leo's videos you heard about
HashMaps and how useful they can be.
And, in particular, we talked
already about mod this and mod that.
And so this support video is
an opportunity to remind ourselves what
modular arithmetic is and
how it can be useful when we're
dealing with hash sets and HashMaps.
So, by the end of this video,
you'll be able to explain how and
why to use modular
arithmetic in this context.
So, let's go back to the example
that Leo worked through.
And if we're thinking about
an array that has five elements and
we want to hash elements into that array,
then a very useful function or
a common function is to say K mod N,
where K is the key or so
it's a code for the element that
we're trying to put into the array.
And N is the size of
the hash table that we have.
And so we might wanna do K mod N,
but then why?
It seems kinda arbitrary,
why do we wanna use this mod function?
And so, it's worthwhile to think back
to what the mod function actually does.
And if you think back about
the definition of a mod function and
what it's possible values are, when we
say K mod N, we're saying I want to give
back the remainder of the long division
that happens when we divide K by N.
Okay and so, if we think about what
the possible remainders might be,
well a remainder when we do
long division is either 0,
if the number divides evenly, or
it's some number no bigger than N- 1.
Because if the remainder was as big as N,
well,
then it wouldn't be a remainder anymore,
we could fit more copies of N into K.
Okay, so the remainder is
an integer between 0 and N-1, but
integers between 0 and N-1 are exactly
the indices of an array of size N and
so, the set of possible values for
the mod function is perfect for
storing values into a table of size N.
All right, so at least we know that
the mod function, or mod N, is going to be
related in some way to indices in
a collection or a table of size N.
And so let's think about how even the
definition of this function that has these
values is already gonna help
us calculate hash codes.
So when we think about remainders,
we think about long division and
long division is this algorithmic
process to compare two numbers.
And so we have an algorithm for
comparing the hash codes.
So going back to the examples that
Leo presented, if we think about for
example the hash code of the key 11.
We wanna compute 11 mod 5 and so
that means that we need to do,
the long division of 11 by 5.
And so a way of thinking about
that is that we want to write
11 as some multiple of 5 plus a remainder.
Okay, what multiple of 5?
I want the biggest possible
multiple of 5 that we can.
And so it's 2 because 10 fits into 11.
And so we got 11 equals 2 times
5 plus our remainder 1 and
that remainder is what we get when we say
mod and so the hash code is just one.
Now with three, it's a little bit tricky.
It seems a little bit tricky.
What happens when we divide three by five?
Well, three is smaller than five,
how do we divide it?
Well, we're still looking for
some multiple of five plus a remainder
should all equal to three.
And so the multiple of 5
that we end up using is 0,
because no positive integer
copies of 5 fit into 3.
So 3 = 0 * 5 + the remainder 3.
And so then MOD function outputs 3.
And that's the hash code for 3.
All right, so we now know why MOD
is useful, because it gives us
this limited range of possible values,
and we know how to compute MOD.
But then there was this comment that Leo
made about collisions that we have to
worry about what happens
when different keys,
different values mapped to the same
position in the hash table.
They collide, we wanna have the same
hash code for two different numbers.
And so you might wonder, well,
do we need to even worry about that?
Will that ever happen?
And so let's think about
an example of the keys 3 and
13 when we try to put them
into a hash table of size 5.
If we do the long division in each of
those cases, the remainder, or the mod,
comes out as 3 for both of them.
And in fact, many, many,
many different integers all will
have the same remainder mod 5.
And, so, we will potentially
deal with collisions and so
we have to worry about how our hash
table's going to accommodate those.
And that's what Leo talks about
in those videos about collisions.