[NOISE] Okay, we're ready for
our final concept challenge
of the course on hash tables.
So, just like you've done before,
you'll solve the problem yourself.
You'll discuss it,
you'll watch the UC San Diego learners.
You'll try the problem again, and
then you can watch our explanation.
So here is the problem.
You've got a hash table that
has seven positions in it, and
it's got some elements
already inserted into it.
So you'll need to know a few
things about this hash table.
First thing you should know is that
the hash function is that same hash
function we've been working with
where you take your key and mod by 7,
to figure out where in the hash
table your key should go.
The next thing you need to know is that
it's going to use linear probing for
collision resolution.
And then the final thing you need to know
about the next key we're going to insert
is that we're going to randomly
choose a key to insert next, and
all the keys we could possibly choose,
they're all equally likely to be chosen.
So our question for you is,
what's the probability that that next key
that we choose will end up in each
of the slots in this hash table?
>> I'm Daniel.
>> I'm Melissa.
>> I'm Sarah.
>> All right, so for this problem,
I was started off thinking that
honestly all the probability will be one
seventh, because in the problem it says
that all the integers
are equally likely to be chosen.
So, my first inclination is that it'll be
one seventh chance for all the open spots.
I thought it would be different for 0, 1,
2, or 6, spots 0, 1, 2, and 6,
in the way that if some
number mod 7 was 3,
then it would go from 3 to 4, 5 to 6.
And if there was already something in 6,
then it would go 0, 1,
2 and then go there.
So, it would come out to one seventh,
three seventh,
one seventh and two seventh I
believe in the end, in order.
>> Yeah.
>> I think it works like
that if it lands on 3,
4, or 5, they'll all go to 6 if
any one of them land on there,
because linear probing means it
goes to the next open space.
>> All right.
So, the learners had
a really good conversation
about how to solve this problem.
So let's take a look at it.
And I wanna start by looking
at a blank hash table.
So let's consider that we
have that same hash table,
only this time there's nothing in it.
So, we know that our hash function is
that we're gonna take our key, and
mod it by 7,
in order to figure out where to put it.
And we also know that all keys
are equally likely to be chosen
as the next thing that we're
going to put in this hash table.
So, basically what that means, because
mod 7 will cover all the slots in this
hash table 0 through 6, is that there's
an equally likely chance that our next
key will end up in any of these spots.
So that's if the hash table is empty.
But what happens now if we say
insert 24 into this hash table?
How does that change the probabilities
of the next key going into each of
these slots?
Well, we can start off by observing that
all the keys are still equally likely
to occur.
So, in theory,
we should have an equal probability of
putting them into each of these slots.
But, now we can see that
this one slot is full so
we can't put another key into that.
What should we do?
Well, now we need to go to our
collision resolution strategy which is
linear probing.
So with linear probing, if we try to
put a key into that slot that's full,
instead we're going to move it over
into the next slot that's empty.
So in this case, we would instead of
putting it into slot 3, where there's
already 24, we'd put it now into slot 4,
which means that that 1/7
probability of ending up in slot three
now actually ends up in slot four.
So we take the 1/7, and we add it to
the 1/7 that's already there for slot 4.
Giving us a final set of
probabilities that look like this.
There's no chance it's going to go into
slot three, because it's already full.
But there's a 2/7 chance that it
will end up in that next slot over.
The 1/7 chance that it hit slot 3 and
it had to go over one, and
the 1/7 chance that it was originally
designed to go into slot 4.
All right, so with this we can
continue our reasoning and
go back to our original problem.
What happens if all three of
these positions are filled in?
What is the probability
that the next key is gonna
end up in any of these
different locations?
Just like before, those three slots
are full, so we can't put a new key there.
So what's gonna happen?
Well, if a key tries to go in any
of these spots via linear probing,
we're gonna move that key over, and
over, and over, into that slot 6.
And by the way, if six had also been full,
we would've wrapped back
around to position 0.
But in this case six is empty, so
we'll take the 1/7 probability
from each of the full slots and
move them over into that slot 6.
We add them all together and we're gonna
end up that the first three slots still
have a 1/7 probability of
getting a key put into them,
those three block slots
are zero probability and
then that last slot has a 4/7
probability of a key ending up there.
All right.