[MUSIC]
In this module we're gonna begin looking
at inheritance and polymorphism in Java.
Inheritance and polymorphism
are incredibly power features to any other
oriented programing language but
unlike lobes and conditionals
you don't usually need to use inheritance
and polymorphism for your code to work.
When you first started programming,
you probably could have put a lot of your
code in main and gotten away with it.
But as your code grew,
you started using methods,
and then later started using classes.
Likewise, as the complexity
of your project grows and
you start working on large software
design projects, you start having to use
inheritance and polymorphism to be able
to handle the complexity of the project.
You've already worked with inheritance and
polymorphism to some extent
by having used the keyword
extends in your previous modules.
What we're going to do here is
start working in more detail
with inheritance and polymorphism.
The goal here for this single video is to
look at the value of inheritance and self.
We're gonna do this by
posing a potential problem.
Imagine you're a software
engineer at a university, and
you've been working for
some time on a Person class.
You've actually tested the code, it's much
longer than the code that you see here,
and you're very happy with it.
But your software design
team comes back to you and
says, we really can't just
have one class anymore.
This needs to start behaving
differently for students or faculty.
So you think about how
are you gonna solve this, and
there's a couple potential solutions.
Neither of these are gonna be good
solutions, so I'm not gonna dive into too
much detail with them, but let's talk
through what you might try to do.
The first option is really to say, well,
I'm gonna keep all this
in the Person class.
And I'm just gonna have it behave
differently if you're a student or
faculty member.
And I'm gonna do this by having
a boolean which just says whether or
not you're a student.
True if you're a student,
false if you're faculty.
I'm gonna add a constructor that
handles it this way as well.
And then in each of my methods,
I can just do if student,
do the code for the student,
else do the code for the faculty.
And at this point this doesn't
seem like that bad of an idea.
What's going to happen is your software
design team is going to come back
to you later and say, you know we can't
have all students behave the same,
undergrads and graduate students
are going to behave differently.
They have different needs,
graduate students have thesis advisors,
things like that.
Then they come back to you and
say well we need you to behave differently
if you're a full time student or
you're a part time student.
So what you'll do is you'll add now
boolean flags to say whether or
not this is a graduate student or not and
a boolean flag to keep track of
whether you're full time or not.
And now your methods gonna start looking
something like if you're a student and
you're a grad student and you're full time
and if this sounds really ugly, it is.
In fact, this kind of ugly code
has a specific name for it.
You may have heard of it before.
It's called spaghetti code.
Now I like spaghetti, but
I don't like spaghetti code.
Spaghetti code is code that you're gonna
write, you're gonna realize how bad it is,
you're gonna throw it away,
and you're gonna start over.
So this solution we're not happy with.
Let me propose another potential solution.
Let's just take my Person class and
copy paste it into two files and
we name one to be Student and
the other to be Faculty.
And then within the Student class
I'm gonna change all the code
to match the behavior of a student, and
within the Faculty I'm gonna change all
the code to match the behavior
of a faculty member.
At this point this seems like
a pretty reasonable solution.
This will actually work for
a little while.
But it's not going to work indefinitely.
Take a few seconds to think
where it might go wrong.
All right.
If your answer had anything to do with
either consistency or the ability to store
all the objects in one data structure,
you're on the right track.
So let's talk through it in both of those.
What's gonna happen is your design team's
gonna come back to you and they're gonna
say at some point, you know having
a single string name isn't sufficient.
We really need you to break this
out as first name and last name.
And this isn't a major change,
so you go into your code,
you start changing all the instances
of name to now work with first name and
last name and
you fix all of the Student class.
And then you're gonna realize, wait,
I had name in the Faculty class, too.
And you can't just copy-paste the code
that you just changed in Student into
Faculty.
You're gonna have to
rewrite all the Faculty,
do all the changes you just made
in Student to the Faculty code.
It's gonna be tedious and
it's unnecessary.
But more important,
what if you make a mistake?
What if you miss a change in
Faculty that you made in Student?
This is gonna be really
hard to keep consistent.
The other problem with this
is that there is probably some code
that has an array of persons right now.
What's gonna happen if I now break this
into two classes, only students and
only faculty.
Well I can't keep that single
array of persons anymore.
I'm gonna have to keep two arrays,
one for students and one for faculty.
I know there's no clean way to keep
a single data structure for all persons.
And you may say,
well why is that important?
Well, what if I just wanted to sort by
the time that the person came on campus?
That would be really hard to do.
I could sort the students potentially,
I could sort the faculty, but
how do I merge those?
It's gonna get ugly pretty quick.
So, neither of these answers
are things that we're happy with.
What do we want then?
Essentially, we figured out the goals
by looking at these two examples.
The goals here are 1, to keep all
of our common code in one class.
It'd be great if we could do that.
We also would like it, so
if we have different behaviors,
I split that different behavior
into different classes.
And lastly,
I wanna be able to keep all these objects
in one single data structure.
Now these are somewhat lofty goals, but
the good news is,
they all come to us with inheritance.
We're gonna dive into the details about
how to do this in the next video.