[MUSIC]
In the last video we began to
see the power of inheritance and
polymorphism in Java.
In this video,
we're gonna start diving into the details.
How do we make this work?
The goal here is to use the keyword
extends, and recognize what that does.
We're gonna talk about the relationship
between superclass and subclasses and
what those terms mean.
And we're gonna use UML Diagrams to
design our first class hierarchy.
We left off at the last video
saying we want three key features.
We wanna be able to keep
common code in one class,
we wanna be able to split out different
code between different classes,
and we want to be able to keep all
the objects in one single data structure.
In this video, we're gonna show how we can
do one and two by designing our hierarchy.
Item three will be in the next video.
Where we left off was talking about
three different classes Person class,
a Student class and a Faculty class.
And in a sense we want to have all
the common code in the person class and
we want to have our diverging code in
the student and the faculty classes.
To do this it would be great if we
could have all the power of person and
all the features of person get
inherited into the student class.
So let's focus on that one first.
Now it might seem really powerful to
inherit all the features of another class,
and it is, but you can do it
with just one keyword, extends.
So if you say extends person,
that means inherits from.
It means the student class is
gonna inherit from person,
many of the features of the person class.
So when you've used this
before in previous modules,
this was a really powerful thing to do,
to say, extends.
So what you get when you, before I say
that, let's talk about some terminology.
The Person class here is a base class,
sometimes called a super class and
sometimes called a Parent class.
The Student class here is a derived
class or a sub class or a child class.
Now what features do you actually inherit?
You inherit public instance variables,
and that makes sense.
You inherit the public methods.
So the student's gonna get all
the public methods of person.
You're also gonna inherit the private
instance variables, in a sense.
So we'll talk about that
in a little more detail.
So since you're inheriting the private
instance variables do you really still
need to have that instance
variable with student called name?
No, in fact it's a really
bad idea to do that.
That would be called a hidden variable or
shadow variable and
it's hard to discern which variable,
which name variable you're talking about.
The one in student or the one in person.
So you actually wouldn't have that,
cuz you inherited it
automatically from person.
But there is one catch, because it's
a private instance variable you can only
access it through public methods so
you'll have to use the getters and
setters to access name.
Now that we have an idea of
how we can use inheritance,
let's start talking about how we can
design an inheritance hierarchy.
Now if you're working on
a whiteboard with a design team,
you're not gonna wanna
write out the whole class.
You're gonna wanna have a very
small representation of a class.
The way to do this is
known as a UML Diagram.
I have an example of this on the right.
Now there's a number of different
variants of how you can display this.
This is just one example.
I have the person class name at the top.
I have the instance variable string name,
and then I have the method below that.
So you have again, class name,
instance variables and
methods, all within this
concise representation.
Let's add in the student class
which is a extending person.
May add that in,
you're gonna realize that's blank,
and that's because there are no incidence
variables and no methods within student.
Now that keyword extends along
with person is gonna say,
student inherits from person.
And to do that,
all you have to do is draw that line.
So, that line just says,
student is inheriting from person.
Let's start talking about
our full hierarchy.
Let's bring back in Faculty into to this.
So, we have our Person class and
I two derived classes,
my Student class and my Faculty class.
This alone is already an inheritance
hierarchy, or a class hierarchy.
What I want you to do is pause.
Take a few seconds to think about
what would belong in a Student class
that wouldn't belong in
a Faculty class and vice versa.
Again take a few seconds,
pause the video and we'll come back.
All right,
there are a number of good answers here.
Let's just talk through
a couple that I thought of.
So students get grades in their classes.
In the American education system,
we use this thing called a GPA,
which is essentially just an average
of all the grades that you've gotten.
Students would have these,
Faculty would not.
So in the Student class,
I'd have an instance variable named GPA,
and then I'd have an access or
method called getGPA.
What belongs in a Faculty class that
wouldn't belong in a Student class?
Well, maybe an office number or
office phone, but also a salary.
So, Faculty get paid,
students generally do not.
So I might have an instance
variable called double salary, and
I'm gonna have a method called
getSalary to get access to this.
We've already started designing
our inheritance hierarchy.
We have the code that's common
up in the person class.
We have the code that's divergent
in the Student class and
Faculty class is separately.
This answers items 1 and
2 from our desire list.
But we haven't answered three yet and
that's coming up in the next video.