[MUSIC]
In the last video we began using
the keyword extends to unlock the power of
Inheritance in JAVA.
We also designed our
first class hierarchy and
we're gonna continue
with that in this video.
The goal here is to understand
what the term is a means.
And how it defines a relationship
necessarily between classes.
In the last video, we saw how
designing our class hierarchy and
using the keyboard extends gives us
the first two features on this list.
It allows us to keep all the common code
in one class, allows us to split out
the different behavior between separate
classes, but what we didn't answer was how
can we keep all the objects
in one single data structure.
And to figure this out,
let's play an old fashioned matching game.
What I have here on
the left is a Reference and
on the right I have an Object.
What we're gonna do is
essentially play a matching game.
We're gonna try and figure out, can you
have this Reference point to this Object.
Let's start off with
Person p = new Person ();.
You've done this a whole bunch,
is this legal, absolutely.
The reason this is legal is
because A Person is-a Person.
Somewhat reflective we
kind of recognize that.
We'll use this term though,
again as we go forward.
Likewise, is a Student a Student,
absolutely.
A Student is-a Student.
Where this gets interesting is,
can you have a Reference,
Person point to a Student Object?
What I want you to do is think about this,
just for a few seconds.
Do you think this should be allowed?
I hope you said yes.
This should be allowed.
Now, this is new.
You've likely always ran code where
the Reference was the exact same thing as
the Object, but
you're actually allowed to do this.
And the reason you're allowed to do
this is because a Student is a Person.
All the capabilities that a Person has,
a Student has to have,
because it's derived from Person.
This is fantastic,
because what this allows us to do now,
is keep one single array of Student and
Faculty objects.
So this code where I create a array
of Persons, a references to Persons.
And then I can fill it with
references to a Person object,
to a Student object, and
to a Faculty object.
This code compiles and
will work just fine.
So we can now keep,
whether your person is Student or
Faculty, all in one data structure.
This is fantastic.
And we haven't finished
our matching game yet.
Can you have a Student Reference
point to a Person Object?
The answer here is, no.
Why?
Well, not all the features of a Student
are necessarily within a Person.
And you could think about it kind
of loosely as an analogy of,
if you walked up to a random person on the
street and asked them what their GPA is.
Well, that's probably not a very polite
question to ask in the first place,
but if you were to ask it,
most people would say, I'm not a student.
What are you asking me?
This is why you can't do this.
Now, why I brought up this example
is because we get to polymorphism
in just a few videos.
References and
Objects are gonna become front and center.
We're gonna talk about what decisions are
made of compile time, based on reference
type and what decisions are made at
run time based on object actual type.
But before we can get there,
we have a few more details to work out
with inheritance in the next videos.