[MUSIC]
So one of the problems I had when learning
about inheritance is relationship.
And my professor used some analogy
along the lines of animals, and
like a lion is an animal.
And for whatever reason that
went right over my head and
it really frustrated me because I felt
like all my peers quickly picked it up.
And so
I reached out to my professor after class.
And, he just twisted
the analogy to be cars.
And he asked me what kinda car I drove,
and I answered, I drove a Toyota.
And he just relayed that same analogy,
but back to cars and Toyotas.
And he said, a Toyota is a car,
but not all cars are Toyotas.
And for whatever reason, that really
clicked with me, and that's what it took.