[NOISE] All right, you've learned
a little bit about inheritance.
And you've played that matching game
with Leo where you learned what kinds of
references can refer to
what kinds of objects.
It turns out that is a really,
really tricky idea to get.
So, we've got a concept challenge for
you that's gonna exercise your
ability to make those matches.
Don't worry if this is
a little bit tricky.
It takes a while to get it.
So work through it, you know the drill.
Work through it on your own, answer
the end video quiz, discuss with others,
watch our learner videos, and
then watch our explanation.
Here's your challenge.
You've got three classes.
There's a Person class,
it has a name, member variable.
And it has a getName, method.
There's a Student class
which extends person.
It has an ID member variable that's
an integer, and it has a getID method,
it returns an integer, and there's
a Faculty class which also extends Person.
It also has an ID variable, but
this time it's a string, and
it has a getID method
that returns a string.
We have five statements over there on
the right that create new objects and
assign references to refer
to those new objects.
All of those statements compile and
run just fine.
Your question is going to be to answer
questions about which of an additional
series of statements work, and which cause
errors at either compile time or run time.
>> Okay, my name is Linda.
>> My name's Mustafa.
>> My name is Jason.
So how did you guys answer question one.
>> I seem to think that question
one didn't have any issues.
S is a student, and they're trying
to get the name from the student, and-
>> Well I
thought there was a problem with that
because when I look at the class of
Student I realize there is
no method called getName.
>> That's true, but
Student extends from Person.
>> So it will inherit all
the parent class methods.
>> Yeah, it's a public method.
>> Oh so, it will inherit
the Persons getName method.
>> Right, yeah.
>> Oh okay, I see.
What about the second p = s?
>> For the second one,
I also thought it was fine.
>> That's fine?
>> Cuz Person p is a new Person.
And if you change the reference
of p to become the object created
from Student s equals new Student,
then every Student is a Person.
>> Okay, so that's the part that I missed.
I was thinking it would be a problem cuz
Student and Person are not the same type,
so I wasn't sure if you
could cast it that way.
>> Oh, right.
>> So too much p instead of
referencing to Person,
I was referencing to Students.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Okay.
>> If that makes sense?
>> Yeah, okay.
>> Now look at the next line of-
>> I don't think that would work because
Person doesn't have a getID method-
>> Right.
>> So
where would it be looking to get that?
>> I thought that during compile time
error since p is still a Person,
it'll go into the Person class and then
look at, oh, where's the getID method?
>> But didn't we just updated a Person
class with pointing to a Student class?
>> Mm-hm.
>> The compiler doesn't know that.
The compiler still sees it as a Person
object because it was originally set up
that way.
>> It's only at run time that the compiler
will see that p is actually a Student.
>> Oh, okay.
Even that I believe we have
to cast it I guess.
>> Right.
>> Mm-hm.
>> How about the third line of code,
faculty equals Person?
>> Person?
>> Well person isn't
necessarily a Faculty member.
So like he was saying that
if you go around and ask
a random person on the street, they might
not have the information for faculty.
So I'm not sure if you can cast
the faculty as a broad term person.
>> Right, not every person is faculty.
>> Right.
>> Yeah that makes sense.
And then the last one,
o equals a Student, or
object class equals Student class.
>> I think we've previously learned that
every object inherits from the object
class, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, I see.
>> So s is a Student.
>> Okay, I like,
every class would inherit object meaning.
There's implicit extent.
>> Yeah, yeah exactly.
>> Perfect.
>> All right let's step through these
lines one at a time to figure out which
ones work and which ones cause errors.
This first line here,
it's pretty straightforward.
It creates a new variable
of type String called n,
and it's gonna set it
equal to s.getName().
Well first we need to
figure out what is s.
Well s is a Student reference,
it's a reference to a Student.
And it actually does refer
to a Student object.
And you can see that right here,
when we created that Student object and
assigned the reference s to point to.
So now we can look in the Student class
and see if there's a getName method.
We look here, no getName method, but
that doesn't concern us too much,
because Student extends Person.
So now we can go up in person and
look at those getName method there.
And sure enough, there is.
It returns a string.
So this will run just fine, again,
because this getName method is public.
So everything is good.
This line will work just fine.
The next line says that the reference
p should be set to refer
to the same location as
the reference s refers to.
Now s refers to a Student object.
What we're saying is that now p
should refer to a Student object, and
we have to figure out if that's okay.
Is it okay for a Person reference to refer
to an object that's actually a student?
So you ask the question
are all students people?
Is a student always a person?
And I hope the answer is always yes.
So that should be just fine.
That line works as well.
Next line here says that int
m gets the value of p.getID.
Now, we have to think about
things a little more carefully.
So what we're asking, assuming that
this line has already completely, and
p now refers to a Student object, we
wanna know is it okay to call p a getID.
There is a getID method
inside the student class, but
the problem is that p
is a Person reference.
So the compiler doesn't know that p
actually refers to a Student object.
The compiler is gonna complain
about this statement here.
It's gonna say it's a piece of reference
to a Person, I don't know about this getID
method, there's no getID method in Person
class, and so I'm gonna cause an error.
We can fix this with a cast.
So if we wanted to fix this problem,
we would just insert a cast here.
We could cast p, so
instead of just p, we'd say Student,
and then p right there, and then .getID.
Because we know that object
is actually a Student.
So that's fine to do, but again,
be a little careful with your cast
because your compiler will trust
you no matter what you say.
We can do this in this case
cuz we know that's the term.
All right, so the next statement there, so
going back actually to the last statement,
this statement right here.
This statement right there
does not work as written, but
it will work if we add that cast.
Let's consider the next line,
where it says f gets the value of q.
So what is f?
F is a Faculty reference.
It's a reference to some
sort of Faculty object.
And what is q?
Well, q is a reference to a Person.
So now we need to figure out if a Faculty
reference can point to a person object.
And again we will ask the question,
are all people faculty?
And the answer to that
question is of course no.
So we can't set a Faculty reference
equal to a Person object.
That will cause an error.
And there's nothing that we
can do to make that work.
If we try to cast q to a faculty,
compiler might accept it,
but at run time we're going to get
what is called a class cast exception,
because it's illegal to cast
a Person object to a Faculty type.
That line will not work.
What about this next
line where we say o = s.
So o is an Object type reference,
and s is a Student object, up here.
Well, that should work, right?
Because everything in Java is an Object.
The Object text references
are allowed to point to any kind of
Object that they want.
So that one's pretty straightforward.
That works.
So now we're done.
And to summarize what we found was
this first line here was just fine.
The next line here was also just fine,
because all students are people.
The next line is not okay.
But we could make it okay with a cast.
The next line was there not okay and
there is nothing we could
do to make that line work.
And finally this last
line here was just fine.