[MUSIC]
Welcome back.
At this point we've been
talking about what's inherited?
We've used the terms private and
public and
those visibility modifiers impact what
gets inherited from one class to another.
What we're gonna do now is spend
a little more time looking
at the different visibility modifiers and
how they impact us.
Particularly in relation to inheritance.
By the end of this video, you should be
able to use the appropriate visibility
modifiers when you're writing your class.
Up to this point,
your comfortable probably with public
which is less restrictive and
private which is more restrictive.
So public gives access to any other class.
Where as private gives
access only the same class.
Well there's two, well at this point you
likely have learned this rule of thumb.
Make all your instance variables private,
you should make your public interface,
you're public methods public.
You can also have private methods,
those are your helper methods.
This rule of thumb is
actually still gonna apply.
Even if we talk about the other
visibility modifiers,
it's important to know how they apply.
The other visibility modifiers
are protected and package.
So protected gives you access to any,
so within the same class, anything
within the same package can access it,
and any sub class can access it.
Package, also sometimes called default,
you have access from the same class, and
you have access from the same package.
The only difference really
between package and
protected is that package
loses access by any sub class.
So, sub-classes that are still in the same
package, you still have access to.
The sub-classes outside your
package you're gonna lose.
To really understand this
it helps to see an example.
What I have here is a sample class.
And that sample class has a pubic
variable, a protected variable,
a package variable or
default variable and then a private room.
Let's add a whole bunch of other classes.
Some within the same package,
the dotted line denotes package, and
then some are sub classes.
We have sub-class one in the same package,
we have sub-class two,
which is outside of the package.
We have Other1,
which just happens to be another
class in the same package as Sample.
Then we have Other2,
which is a class not in the same package,
it has no relationship in terms
of inheritance with Sample.
If you have the public visibility, so w.
W is accessible from anyone else.
And notice that I'm just saying public w,
I'm not putting the public int,
you can fill in the value there yourself.
So, public anyone can access.
Protected, you only essentially
take away access to Other2.
Things within the same package, as well
as sub-classes, can access this variable.
Now, What I'm concerned about here, is why
does Other1 have access to my variable X?
Is it because it's in the same package?
Does that really make sense, is that who
we want to have access to our variables?
In general,
this is not a very good idea, and
this is why we don't
recommend using protected.
If we look at package access,
what you see is that we've now taken away
access to the sub-class 2, and
what we had from protected.
Which you'll notice that
Other1 still has access to y.
And why is some other class in
the same package happen to have access
to my variable?
It doesn't make much sense and this is why
we don't recommend package access, either.
Lastly, we have private access,
which you're comfortable with,
just means within this class
you can access this variable.
Now that we've walked through
the different levels of access, you see
that public is the least restrictive and
private is the most restrictive.
But we still are gonna apply
the same rule of thumb.
Always use public or private,
there's only rare cases that you'll
ever wanna use protected or packaged.