[MUSIC]
So when I was working on a really
large project in graduate school,
I hit this point where I was
changing all of my code and
I knew the right thing to
do was to do inheritance.
I was basically making three objects, but
I was a little bit lazy with
the software infrastructure.
I was like you know what,
I'm just gonna do this in one class.
I can make this work.
And it worked for little while.
So I worked on it for a few weeks,
got the code working.
But over the next couple of months,
I kept running into bug after bug
after bug related to this code.
And finally one day I had to go to
a group meeting for a research group and
say, I'm gonna need to take two weeks and
rewrite the code properly.
I did.
I lost two weeks of my life doing it, but
it worked out after that, no more bugs.
So I learned inheritance the hard way.