[SOUND] As we continue on in
this module on Inheritance,
what we're gonna do next is look
at object construction in Java.
Now, you've already reconstructed before,
so you might say,
well, wait a second why
are we revisiting this?
Well, the reason we're revisiting this
is because now we know inheritance,
we now know some more details about
how objects actually get constructed.
So the goals of this video
is to recognize that
all objects actually are derived
from the object class.
And you may already know that but
we're gonna dive into
some details about how that actually works
over the course of the next few videos.
And we're also gonna look at
how Java actually constructs or
initializes its objects
really from the inside out.
We'll talk about what we mean
by that in just a moment.
We're gonna keep working with this
in hierarchy that we've been working
with before, where we have a person class,
a super class, and the student and
the faculty classes is drive classes.
And we're gonna focus in on
essentially one line of code,
Student s = new Student();.
We know the new statement,
new is actually an operator.
That operator means allocates space.
And a second piece to this
is once given that space,
pass a reference to that space to
the constructor for initialization.
In fact constructors really should
be called Initializers, and
you'll see in other programming languages
that they're actually called init.
So really what the student
constructor does is just initialize
the variables associated with student.
And the way that's gonna do this is
essentially from the inside out.
So you can go all the way up the
hierarchy, all the way up to object and
then you can come back down.
As you come back down you're gonna
initialize all those variables.
And what we're gonna do is step
through this step by step to
understand how this works.
So first thing you do after you've new,
you've created the space object you've
passed that space through the constructor.
The student constructor then,
it's very first line of code is gonna
send you to the superclass constructor.
In this case, Person.
The very first line of code of
the person constructor is gonna
immediately send you to it's indirect
superclass or in this case, Object.
Now, the object constructor can initialize
the variables associated with object,
essentially filling in
that part of the object.
Once it's done, it returns back to Person.
Person now can initialize it's variables.
And then it's gonna
return back to Student.
And Student now is gonna initialize
the variables associated with Student.
And through this process we've essentially
initialized all these variables,
went all the way up to object,
and all the way back down.
And that's what we mean by
initializing inside out.
What you may be thinking at this point is,
Wait.
I don't remember ever extending
from the object class.
And you may not have done so
explicitly, but it still happens.
And we'll talk about how that
happens in the next video.