[SOUND] In the last video,
we saw how objects
are constructed from
the inside out in Java.
And the way this happens is
really through compiler rules.
We're gonna talk about what those compiler
rules are and how those compiler rules
work, in order to ensure, again, that
the object is created from the inside out.
Where we left off in the last
video is we'd seen the process,
we'd seen how student calls
person which calls object.
And those constructors return back and
in the process of returning back they
actually initialize the variables.
But you've said at the end but wait,
I don't remember extending object.
Where did we do this?
This introduces our first rule
associated with a compiler.
So let's revisit where the compiler
plays a role in our process.
You write code, human-readable Java code,
and that gets sent off
to the Java compiler.
The Java compiler's going
to do a number of passes.
In fact, there's a number of potential
specializations you could write instead of
just on how the compiler works.
What we're going to focus in on
is essentially a couple of passes
the compiler does as
terms of inserting code.
When the compiler is all said and
done we know it produces
the Bytecode which we then
run our java virtual machine.
So what is a Java compiler doing and
what are these rules?
What it does is its going
to change the code.
So, if you wrote this class, public
class Person, and you just have your
single instance variable, and
I've done away with any other code,
it's just this class,
is this actually what gets compiled?
In a sense,
no, cuz the compiler takes this code and
it's gonna change the code a bit.
What it's gonna do is follow three rules
that we're gonna talk about in this video.
First rule is,
if you don't have a superclass,
the compiler's gonna give you one.
It's gonna give you Object.
So even though you wrote
public class Person,
the compiler's gonna insert the terms,
extends Object.
By doing this, now you see how
person inherits from object
just because it inserts those
lines of code implicitly.
But where then, do we call the person
constructor, or the object constructor?
We know now that object inherits, or
sorry person inherits from objects,
but we don't know where those
constructors are getting called?
That's where the next set of rules come.
So first off,
if you don't have a constructor,
Java's gonna give one for you.
It's gonna give you a default
constructor so no arguments.
And then it's gonna apply
another set of rules
which are associated
with all constructors.
This set of rules or Rule #3 is
that the 1st line of a constructor
has to say either this,
and then some arguments.
So call another constructor
within the same class.
Or it has to call one of
the parent class instructors,
a super class constructor call.
It has to do one of those things.
And if you don't do it,
Java is gonna insert super.
So it's gonna call,
It's gonna insert a call to the default
constructor of your super class.
So now we see that we've added this
line to the person constructor.
In a sense you've the code on the left but
the compiler is gonna insert all those
elements on blue on the right and
that's what's really gonna get compiled.
So now we have an idea of
how this work for person.
I want you to pause and think about
what would happen to the Student class
On the first pass by that compiler.
All right, if you were thinking
we should add a very similar
constructor to student that we did to
person, you're on the right track.
It already extends from person,
so we can't extend from object.
It already has a super class so
there's no need to do that first rule.
The second rule applies,
it has no constructor so
we have to insert a default constructor.
And then the third rule applies of I
have to make sure I call the default
constructor of my super class as the very
first line of my default constructor here.
So you're gonna take that
code in black above and
it's gonna get transformed
into the code in blue below.
So when we were curious how is
the compiler making sure that
this construction and the initialization
of our variables happens
essentially from the highest level of
the hierarchy all the way back down.
So it is the compiler makes it happen.
Now there's still one leftover problem and
that is,
we haven't actually initialized anything.
Right all of our default constructors
have done no initialization.
They've just made sure they go
all over the up to object and
all the way back down.
We had at least one variable and that was
name, the instance variable with Person.
In our next video we're gonna
see how to initialize that.