[MUSIC]
In the past couple of videos, we've been
starting to look at how class creation, or
object creation happens in Java,
specifically how does inheritance
apply to object creation.
In the last video, we actually looked
at a number of compiler rules.
Now these compiler rules are what the
compiler does when it looks at your code.
Now the reason we want to
know about these rules,
is because it's going to
help us trace our code.
In fact, we're going to see an error
in our code here in just a little bit,
which comes about because of these rules.
We're also going to use
same-class constructors, and
super class constructors to
help with class creation.
Now we started by saying all objects
are created from the inside out.
In the last video we saw how
the compiler rules make this happen.
But what we did with the last video was
essentially just create a number of
default constructors without
actually initializing anything.
So what we're gonna do now is modify
these to initialize the name variable.
Again, you've likely initialized
a variable before in a constructor.
What we're focusing on are the elements
that apply to inheritance.
So let's start off with our person class.
Remember that the extends object was
automatically put there by the compiler.
And what we're gonna do instead of
having it automatically put there,
is we're gonna explicitly put it here.
Likewise, I'm gonna explicitly
put the default constructor which
would have been inserted
by the compiler anyway.
And what we're gonna so
now is modify this default constructor
to initialize the name variable.
So let's add a string
argument to the constructor.
Let's add this.name = n and
just do what we would of done before.
Now, to be honest if we didn't have
that call to super we'd be fine.
But because I've now inserted this line,
I've got an error.
Remember that rule.
The very first line of instructor has to
be a call to your same class constructor
or a super class constructor.
I have broken this rule
by saying this.name = n.
And because I have a call
to super() after that,
this is going to produce
a fairly cryptic compiler error.
Now you know what that error means and you
can fix it by just switching the order.
So now i'm calling my superclass
constructor correctly and
now I can initialize my variable.
Let's modify the student class now to
initialize the variables there as well.
So i'm gonna take default
student constructor and
i'm gonna make changes to it.
I'm gonna insert String n.
I'm gonna insert as a parameter, and I'm
also going to initialize that variable.
Is this gonna work?
I want you to pause and
think about this for a few seconds.
Look at the code and
see if there's any errors here.
If you start to recognize that I'm not
allowed to say this.name, you're right.
That's a private variable
in the person class.
I'm not allowed to direct the access
of that in the student class,
I'd have to use a getter or
a setter to do so.
But I don't have a getter or a setter.
Is there a way for me to do this?
Can I initialize name without
having the public getter setter?
The answer is yes.
All I have to do is change this now
to call the superclass constructor
that takes an argument,
which is gonna initialize to be named.
Perfect.
So, just cross out those two lines,
replace it with super,
with that name variable being passed in.
And it's gonna initialize
everything properly.
Let's go a little bit further with this,
though.
Let me add one more constructor
to that student class.
Let me add in, so this is our code
from where we just left off, and
now let me add in that
no-arg default constructor.
Now you should might be tempted to do
with a no-arg default constructor and
let's just throw in some
kind of default name here.
Is to just say super student.
This will work, it's not the word idea but
is there a better way to do this?
Yes, there is.
There is no reason I should be
calling these super classes.
Argument constructor when I
have one in my own class.
A better way to do this
would be to do it like this.
I should use my own same class
constructor if it's available to me,
because they maybe code within
my same class constructor
which does things that I wanna
initialize based on this.
I shouldn't just jump
straight to the super class.
But having done all these pieces, we now
see how object creation happens in Java.
We see that it happens
from the inside out,
we see that everything inherits
from object, and we now know how to
use Superclass Constructors and Ownclass
constructors design our classes better.