All right in Leo's videos you learned how
objects are created from the inside out.
So in this concept challenge you're
going to be tracing through some code
that calls some constructors.
And the goal is to figure out what gets
printed as these constructors run.
So you know the drill.
You've done these before.
What you're gonna need
to do is you're going to
go be somewhere where you can spend
a little time on this and pause the video.
Answer the quiz by yourself first.
And then find some friends.
Find some people you're taking
the class with ether in person or
on the online forums.
Try to discuss this question.
See if you all agree.
And then watch our learner video.
And finally watch our explanation.
So if you're ready to go
here's the challenge.
You can see over here that
we've got two classes.
There's a person class and
a student class.
And those classes have
a number of constructors.
The person class has a single constructor.
It takes one argument, a string.
And the student class has
two different constructors.
A no argument constructor and then public
constructor that takes one argument.
So what we're gonna do is we're gonna make
a single call to the Student constructor
to the default constructor right up here.
And it's gonna create a Student object.
And the question for you is what
gets printed when we make that call?
So go ahead and pause the video and
take the online quiz that's coming up.
I'm Linda.
>> I'm Mustafa.
>> Hello, I'm Jason.
>> Okay, so for this first question,
I was a little unclear on the answer.
My instinct was to go for E for
lets just say #2, because the new student
is the the no-argument constructor in
the student class, it just prints out #2.
>> I'm not,
I was really confused about this too.
>> My first system was like,
probably three, two, one.
Because when you have a class and
it goes through constructor it goes
from inner one into most other one.
>> Right.
>> But
then I look at it more carefully and
I realized
>> When you go to students
there's a super implicitly inserted.
>> I was confused cuz the no
argument constructor,
the first cold and the other this
constructor with the student.
So I didn't know if it went
first to the super class or
to the other constructor
within the one class.
>> Cuz it would construct within the one
class called super, as well, so.
>> All right, so
now that you've had an opportunity to
work through this problem yourself and
hopefully discuss it with some people,
let me go through our explanation.
So what we're doing is creating
a Student object right up here,
Student s = new Student.
And you can see that we're
calling the default constructor.
So we're gonna jump right over here to the
defunct constructor for the Student class.
So public Student,
no argument constructor.
But if you look at the first
line of this constructor,
you can see what it immediately does is
it calls the one argument constructor for
the Student class, which has one argument,
which is the string Student.
So we're gonna jump down here to
the one argument constructor and
start executing there.
We start executing there but again,
the first line in that constructor says to
call the constructor of
the super class which is Person.
We pass in an argument, which is what
it requires qnd we go up here and
start executing the constructor for
the person class.
We haven't printed anything yet.
We haven't really executed
any lines at all.
We're just sort of getting ready
to call these constructors.
So, we're gonna go over here.
Get ready to call the one argument
constructor for the person class and
the first thing that it says
is that it sets this.name.
So, the name field in this object
we're creating equal to n,
the string we pass in.
That's fine, and then the next
line here is a print statement.
So System.out.print("#1 ").
This is the first print
statement we've encountered.
So we're gonna print #1.
That's the first thing that gets printed.
So where does it go now?
Well, we're finished
with this constructor.
Here's the end of it.
So we have to remember where we came from.
Well where did we come from?
Well we came from down here,
the one argument constructor for
the student class.
And we just finished calling the
constructor for the super class and we're
now here on this line that says to print
out #3, so that's what we'll do next.
Print number #3, so
that's the second thing that gets printed.
Finally, this constructor ends.
I will go back to where we came from,
which was the first constructor,
the default constructor for
the student class.
We just finished the call
to the one constructor.
We're down here at this print statement
and we're going to print out the #2.
And that's all there is to it.
So this is what gets printed, #1, #2, #3.