[NOISE]
>> Okay,
here's another concept challenge for
you, all about constructors,
what happens when we call
the constructor of the Student class?
We've got our familiar classes, here.
We've got our Person class, and
we've got our Student class.
And the constructors, check them out,
they're a little bit different.
We've got a one argument constructor for
the Person class.
A no argument constructor for
the Student class.
And then this additional method
here in the Person class,
which is setName, which will set
the name field inside the Person class.
So, we're gonna ask you to
reason about what happens
when you call the Student constructor.
And, this is a concept challenge, so
we want you to do the same procedure that
you're used to, just take that video quiz,
first by yourself, then find some people
to chat about this question with,
and then watch our learner video, and
come back and watch our explanation.
>> Hi, I'm Alicia.
>> Hi, I'm Joanna.
>> Hello, I'm Justin.
>> Okay, so what did you guys put?
>> I think it's a compiled time error,
because Student doesn't have a name.
So how can you set a name it doesn't have?
>> Yeah, but I thought that
since Student extends Person,
it actually inherits the name from Person.
>> Oh.
>> So then, I actually put Student,
because I thought that now it
goes into the constructive for
Person and sets the name to Student.
>> Yeah, I also thought the same.
One thing I did notice was that Student
calls Person, no argument constructor.
And I noticed that there was no
argument constructed in Person,
so I think that's the reason why
it causes the compile error.
>> Yeah, okay, so yeah,
it's probably a compiled time error, then.
>> Yeah.
>> All right,
now that you've worked through this
yourself, let's work through it together.
All we're doing here is we're calling
the Student default constructor.
So let's trace the code and
see what happens.
So we go over here to the Student
default constructor, and
you might be tempted to just directly
go and execute this line that says
this.setName to the string Student,
but the problem with that is, you'd
be forgetting that the compiler actually
inserts some code into this constructor.
If the first line of the constructor
is not either a call to the superclass
constructor or
a call to a constructor within the class,
the compiler is going to insert a line
to the superclass constructor
that takes no arguments for us.
So, in order to trace through this code,
we need to insert that line so
we know exactly what's happening.
So let's do that now.
So now that we see this call to the
superclass constructor, we know that we
have to go up to the Person class and
find the constructor with no arguments.
So we go up to the Person class and we
look for a constructor with no arguments.
I don't really see one, do you?
It's not there, and it turns out
that Java will not insert one for
us if we already had a constructor
that takes an argument.
So this is gonna cause a compile error.
So if you choose compile error,
you'd be correct.
And the reason we're going
through this example is,
it turns out it happens a lot that
you have a situation like this.
I have it happen to me all the time and
the compile error that you're
gonna get is very, very cryptic.
You're gonna read it and be like,
what are you talking about,
there is no constructor with no arguments?
I didn't try to call
a constructor with no arguments.
Well, you didn't.
But, Java did, and
that's what's happening.