[MUSIC]
Hi, and welcome back to our module
on Polymorphism Inheritance in Java.
Today we'll be talking about method
overriding and you've already used method
overriding when you did draw and
set up methods back when you designed
your GUI but here we're gonna dive into
method overriding in a bit more detail.
So goal here today is where the create
methods are override from superclass
methods and will the contrast
overloading from method overriding.
Back when we first started talking
about inheritance we had three goals.
And overriding really
helps us has all three.
So we wanna have common
code in one pairing class.
We do this if we don't override a method.
So if a method just exists in
the superclass we get back common code.
But if we want our subclasses
to behave differently
all we have to do is override a method and
now we get that different behavior.
And because polymorphism which we'll
get to in the next set of videos
we'll see that this allows us to have
all of our object in one structure and
still be able to call
the appropriate method.
It's really common for
new learners to mix up overloading and
overriding so I want to talk just real
quickly about overloading and overriding.
Overloading is the same class that has the
same method name but different parameters.
So this is a different method signature,
within the same class.
This is different then method overriding,
where you have a subclass that has same
method signature, which means same name,
same parameters as a super class.
So now let's start looking at some
more detail with a few examples.
So first example is to look
at the object class itself.
So we have a method in the outer
class called toString.
And the odds are you probably already
ran toString method before, but
if you haven't,
toString prints the contents or
string representation of an object.
Because it's in the object class,
all objects in Java can override it.
So let's do this for our hierarchy.
So we have our person class at the top,
It has a name and
a getName and we're going to
add the toString method to it.
To do so we're going to override the that
object method's toString method.
Now, a really basic way to do this would
be to just return the name and since we
already have right now in our person class
is name, this is really all we can do.
And then in our code that calls it,
we're gonna create a Person p, we're gonna
create a person that has the name Tim and
then we're gonna call this method.
So you just do System.out.println and
put p.toString and
that will return a string and
that is what we want.
And it doesn't call
the object two string method,
it's going to call the person two
string method because of override.
Now it turns out that two string here
in this context is unnecessary because
print line actually automatically
calls toString if you ever pass
an object as a parameter to print line.
So I'm gonna just display
it this way from here on.
Now if we run this code, what's going to
happen is it's just going to print Tim.
All right, well let's add to
our inheritance hierarchy.
Now I'm gonna go to my student class
where we've already added a student ID.
And I get student ID and now we're
going to add the method toString.
Here's the code to essentially
have that student ID and
the ability to get access to it.
And now what I want, is I wanna be
able to print a student ID number
followed by the information
about the person.
And my first version of this code
will look something like this.
So return this getSID then a colon,
and then this.getName.
And the concern I would have here
is what if the person changes.
So the only reason I wrote this dot
getName right now is because I know
that's person does.
So if you try to call toString on person,
it prints the name.
But Person could change.
So this really isn't
the right way to do it.
What I want to do instead is call
the toString method within Person and
to do that I wanna use that super keyword,
just like we saw from the constructors to
say, I want the method from my superclass.
So now, if we walk through this code
I'm gonna use Student s = new Student.
I'm gonna print out that which is
gonna call the toString method.
A question is what do we
expect to see happen.
Well, we expect to see the student
ID number now followed by the name,
which is exactly what we
wanted to have happen.
What happens now if I
change the referencing?
What if I make the reference
a Person instead of a Student?
And I still pass, I still try to
call s.toString, on that Person.
Is it gonna call the Student
to string method or
is it gonna call the person
to string method?
Well what do we want to have happen?
We want to have it print out
the student information,
which is exactly what it does.
Why is it gonna print the student method?
Because of polymorphism, and
we'll get into that in the next lesson.