[MUSIC]
Okay, so now that you've learned how to
create classes and objects, in this video
we're gonna show you a powerful way
of reasoning about your code and
the variables in your code that's
called drawing memory models.
So by the end of this video,
you'll be able to draw memory models for
variables that contain primitive type
data like ints and double and floats.
And you'll be able to update those memory
models to reason about the values of those
variables in your code as your code runs,
to try and
figure out what is your
code actually doing.
Now this is a really interactive lesson.
So we want you to get out your pencil,
get out your paper, and
draw these memory models
right along with us.
Now, when I ask my students to get
out pencil and paper in class,
they kind of look at me like I'm crazy.
Like, this is computer science.
Why do I need a pencil and
a piece of paper?
And I actually usually walk around the
room and say, hey, get out your pencil.
Get out your paper.
Now obviously I can't do that with you,
but, you know, if it helps, imagine me
kind of knocking on your door, knocking
on your car window, asking you to get out
your paper and your pencil, to draw
these memory models right along with us.
It will be a lot more interesting, and
you'll learn the concepts a lot better.
So, to warm us up let's
look at this piece of code.
And what I'd like you to do is just
trace through this code and tell me what
are the values of the variables var1 and
var2 at the end of this code.
In other words, what does this code print?
All right, so
if you got that example right, great job.
This actually turns out to
be a somewhat tricky example
that a lot of people have trouble with.
So if you did have a lot
of trouble with it,
don't worry because what we're going to
do now is we're going to use this example
in order to illustrate this
idea of drawing memory models.
So that you'll be able to get questions
like this right forever, so for
all of the future.
And why is it important to be able
to reason about code like this,
rather than just write code?
Well it turns out that people who are
better at writing code are also better at
reasoning about their code and vice versa.
So practicing reasoning about
code is a really important skill
in order to become a better coder and
software developer.
So, let's step through this code,
line by line and draw the memory model for
this code as it runs.
Let's start here on the first one.
That first line is a variable declaration.
What we're actually telling Java is hey,
Java, I want some new space to
store a value of type integer.
And that space I'm gonna
label with the label var1.
So in my memory model what I'm going
to do is I'm gonna draw a box.
That represents the space that I'm gonna
have to represent this variable and
label it with the name of the variable.
So there we go.
And you should do the same
on your piece of paper.
The next line of code here
is an assignment statement.
So what that's telling Java is,
hey Java take the value on the right
hand side which in this case is 52 and
place it into the variable in the left
hand side which in this case is var1.
So in our memory model, we'll take that
52 and we'll put it in the box for
var1 which is where var1 sorts it's value.
All right, next line.
Another variable declaration, so
we need another box labeled with
the new variable name which is var2.
The next line is another
assignment statement.
Now this is slightly more complicated than
the last assignment statement because
the thing on the right hand side
is not just a number like 52,
it's another variable.
So what we need to do is we need
to get the value out of var1 so
we can then place that value
into the variable var2.
So we look in the box for var1,
we see the value there is 52.
So what we'll do is we'll copy that
value over here into the variable var2.
So now var1 and
var2 both store the value 52.
Now this is a really
important point that var1 and
var2 are not the same variable,
they're not tied together in any way.
They just temporarily
store the same value.
Because its assignment statement told
Java to take the value that's in var1 and
put it into var2, but there's no
connection between these two variables,
which you can see in
the memory model diagram.
So now when we go onto the next slide,
which is another assignment statement, and
take the value 127 and put it into var1,
you'll see that only the value
of variable var1 will change.
So I'll take that 127,
replace the 52 that was already there,
and the new value of var1 is 127.
Now we're down here at the last line,
which is this print statement.
And, all that's left to do is read
the values out of those boxes for
the variables.
So, when I print out var one and var two
they'll have the values that you see in
the boxes of 127 for
var one and 52 for var two.
And, this is what prints.
So those are some simple memory models
using just primitive type data,
and in the next video we're gonna show you
how to get more complicated using objects.