[MUSIC]
All right.
Something I struggled with when I
was learning computer science, and also
I still really kind of struggle with it
today, is just simply compiling and
running and testing my code.
I'm not really sure why, but
when I started out programming
I was just terrified to compile, and
I was terrified to run because I was so
afraid of the errors that
were going to be in my code.
And, of course, we all have errors in our
code, but it just, it was a visceral fear.
And I always thought, oh, my God, like the
computer is going to explode or something,
and I would just not do it.
So it would lead me to write
these huge methods and
these huge programs before I compiled or
ran anything, and it was a big mistake.
So I got over that just by
kind of practicing more,
hitting the compile button and the run
button and realizing that nothing happens.
Your code breaks and you fix it and
it's not a big deal.
So that's what I've learned, but,
you know, it's still kind of scary for
me sometimes.