[MUSIC]
So the last video, we drew memory
models using only primitive type data.
In our case, last time it was integers.
But this time we're gonna add
objects into our memory models.
So our goals for this video are the same
basically as the last time,
only this time you will be able to draw
memory models using object type data and
primitive type data, and reason about code
that uses both primitives and objects.
So before we begin,
let's just give an example of
the two different types of data.
You're probably already familiar with this
from your earlier courses in Java, or
course, or courses in Java, that Java has
two fundamentally different kinds of data.
It has primitive kinds of data,
which consists of only eight types,
so boolean, byte, short, int,
long, float, double, and char.
Those are the eight primitive
types of data in Java.
Everything else is an object, whether
it's an array or a user-defined class,
or a class that you find in a library,
everything else is an object.
So obviously, learning how to add objects
into our memory models is going to be
really important to reasoning about code.
So here's a short snippet of
code right there, just two lines
that show an example of both a primitive
type, the integer and an object type,
which is our class SimpleLocation,
which we defined in the last lesson.
We're gonna reason through a short snippet
of code that combines both integers,
primitives and
these objects of type SimpleLocation.
We're gonna step through this code
the same way we did in the last video and
draw the memory model as we go.
So to get this started, we've got a nice,
easy variable declaration and
assignment statement.
And you already know
how to handle this one.
This is just an integer just
like we looked at before, var1.
We create a box.
We put the value of
the variable in the box.
In this case, it's 52.
So, that was easy.
No problem.
Let's go onto the next line.
The next line turns out
as pretty easy as well.
All it is is a variable declaration.
So, we handle this in the same way,
regardless of the fact that it's
actually an object type variable.
That doesn't matter for
our variable declaration.
So, we're gonna make a box and
label it with the variable's name.
There it is.
It's this next line where
things get interesting.
This is an assignment statement.
And what we're doing is we're
creating a new instance, or
new object of type SimpleLocation.
And then we're setting
the value ucsd equal to
whatever happens when we
create that new object.
So now to understand what's going on here
and how it's going to effect our memory
model, we need to look a little more
closely at what happens when we
create a new object in Java and
what's going on in your computer's memory.
So when we say new SimpleLocation,
what Java's doing is it's creating
a new object, which means it's
allocating some space in your
computer's memory to store that object.
So let's take a closer look.
What it's doing is creating that object,
which is allocating some space, and
it's doing that in a part of your
computer's memory called the heap.
It creates the new object in the heap,
and then what it does is,
it puts that object at some location
in the heap that has some address.
It's not necessarily, we don't know where
Java chooses to create that object,
so we'll just represent that address
where Java creates that object with
this little at sign 34.
So that object is at location 34.
It's just a random number that I
picked off the top of my head.
It's wherever Java happened to
create that object in the heap.
So now, what happens is,
when we've created that new object, and
Java creates it at location 34,
what it actually does is,
it doesn't place the whole
object inside the box for ucsd.
It places a reference to that
object in the box for ucsd.
In other words, it places
the location of the object wherever
it's stored in the heap into the box for
ucsd and that's called a reference.
So now I said 34 is just kind of a made up
number, I don't necessarily know that this
SimpleLocation object
exists in location 34.
So typically in my memory and location,
sorry my memory model diagrams,
rather than making up arbitrary
locations for all of my objects,
what I'm going to do is I'm going
to draw an arrow from the box for
the variable ucsd to the object
that's created in the heap.
But remember that this arrow really
just represents this reference,
this number that represents the address or
something like an address of where to find
this newly created object in the heap.
So it's actually a number in the box, but
that number effectively represents
the location of the object in memory so
we draw an arrow from the box
to that location in memory.
And that arrow is actually
the value of the variable, ucsd.
All right, so now we've got our
new object, we've got the value
of ucsd which is a reference to that
newly created object in memory.
Now let's look a little bit closer
at what that object looks like
over there in memory.
So this class SimpleLocation
has two member variables and
both of these member variables
are stored inside the object.
So we can open up that object,
look inside, and
we can see that inside we actually
have two variable declarations.
There's latitude and longitude.
So we're gonna draw boxes, just like
we did before, with that integer var1.
We'll create a box for latitude and
a box for longitude, and
label them both with their names.
Those boxes are going to store
the values of latitude and
longitude when that object is created.
And where do they get their values?
Well they get them from the constructor.
Those values that get passed in are the
values that go into the latitude and
longitude variables inside that object
which is over there in the heap.
So this is the complete memory model
after these first three lines of code.
We've got our primitive variable,
var1, storing the value 52.
We got our object type variable ucsd which
stores a reference, which is essentially
just a number representing the location
of this newly created object in memory,
which we represent in our memory
model diagram as an arrow.
And then we have our object, which has
two variables inside of it, latitude and
longitude.
The next line down,
creates another new variable, and
it creates another new object, and
then will create a link between the two by
storing the reference to the new
object in the new variable.
So let's take that down piece by piece,
in order to draw this part of the memory
model, what you would do is you
would handle the declaration first.
Draw that box.
Label it with the variable's name,
which is lima.
Draw the new object over here in memory.
Put the two member variables
that are inside that object
as boxes labeled with their
names inside the object.
And then link the variable lima to
the newly created object by placing
a reference inside the box for lima, which
again is the value of the variable lima.
All right, so we're almost there.
This is the last line.
Let's look at this last line of code which
actually changes the value of latitude
inside the variable lima.
So let's say, for example, we wanna tweak
the value of the latitude variable,
make it a little more precise.
What happens in our memory model when we
make this change to the variable latitude
inside the object lima?
Well, what Java says, when it sees
a statement like this, lima.latitude,
what that means is it wants us to
follow the arrow from lima into memory
to the object to finds there and find
the variable latitude inside that object.
So that's how that we know we're
not talking about latitude up
there in the ucsd object,
we're talking about latitude down in the
lima object because we say lima.latitude.
So we go to the box for lima.
We follow the arrow and then look in that
object to find the variable latitude.
We find it and that's where that
value -12.04 is going to go.
So, we change the value of the variable
latitude inside that object and
that's all there is for this code.
And here we have the final memory model,
representing the state of all
the variables and all the memory in this
code, when the code is finished running.
So now that you've mastered
these memory models,
you should be able to reason about lots
of different examples involving both
primitive variables and
object type variables.
So we've got a sequence of challenges and
practice videos for
you to try out your new skills.