[SOUND] Welcome back.
We're gonna do a challenge
question at this point.
Now, you've learned a great
deal about memory models.
Let's see if we really understand it well.
What we're going to do in this video, is
we're going to walk through two questions.
The first one of which will be a question
where we just stop, come back.
And the second question is where we're
actually gonna walk through the full
concept challenge procedure.
Again, the procedure is you're gonna
pause, think about the problem, solve it
yourself, discuss it, potentially,
with other learners, watch a video of UCSD
learners discussing it, then confirm
your understanding with our explanation.
So first, to get things started, what I
wanna give you is an example is a code.
I have the SimpleLocation class
we've already been working with.
And then I'm just going to create
a main example of one of those objects.
So what I want you to do is pull
out your pencils and paper.
Pause, draw the memory model as it
stands right now, and then come back.
So if this was the model that you drew,
you were spot on.
And this gives us a good starting
point now for our next question.
We're gonna scale the question a bit.
We've got a single
variable now within main,
we've also got two objects that
we're creating within main.
The question here is,
what memory model is gonna result?
Again, pull out a piece of paper and
a pencil, draw this yourself, and
then we'll come back together.
>> Hi.
My name is Aziel.
>> Hi, I'm Julia.
>> And I'm Monica.
>> And let's just get started.
Okay, so far, looking at this,
I notice that there are two objects.
So, we can immediately cross out c.
>> So how are there two objects?
>> But why?
>> They're both simple location objects,
so wouldn't they point to a simple
location inside the heap?
>> Yeah, but
each one is a new simple location so
they don't point to
the same area in the heap.
They point to different areas
because they're both new objects.
>> So Washington DC gets it's own place?
>> Washington DC gets it's own place.
>> So there are two objects
because there's two news, right?
>> Right.
There's two news.
>> So that means C is not the answer.
>> Yeah, that's what I thought.
>> Okay.
>> But
the part where I got a bit confused on,
was when I tried to look at each of
the different locations in memory.
And I understand why latitude is -12 for
each one of these, but
I don't really get why d
doesn't point to -77, or
whether it actually is
just -77 in the box.
>> So we know that d is primitive, which
means that it's just a constant number.
>> Right, so-
>> So, primitive types,
which are constant numbers,
do not need an arrow, that's what I think.
>> Why don't we need an arrow though?
I mean,
it's inside the object's memory area.
>> But, the item itself, is not an object.
>> Oh, okay, I see.
>> So, then you just write it
directly into the box for both cases.
>> All right, now that you've heard
an explanation about this for
our UCSD learners,
you're already seeing how this works.
And really, the only way to do this is
to trace the code just as they did.
I'm going to do that for us here.
We will start at the very top of main,
as we always do.
And we're gonna have a double-variable
d that is assigned the value -77.
And you can see that's within the scope
of main in the drawing below.
And when I create a reference for lima,
and just like we did at the very start
here, is I'm gonna actually
now create this object.
So when I call new simple location
that allocates space on the heap,
you can see that on the right.
And then I'm going to pass in
as parameters, -12, and -77.
That's the value of d at the time
that is passing as a parameter.
Perfect.
All right, now we can do the second piece.
Now we can create a second object, or
sorry we're creating a reference for
a second object, which is called washDC.
And now I'm actually create the object
by calling that new simple locations.
Again, new simple location allocates
based on the heap for a new object.
And I'm now gonna call this method,
passing in these two parameters.
And the key part to this problem is
really what happens with lima.lon.
When you call a constructor and
you're passing these values as parameters,
parameters in Java
are always passed by value.
So 38.9 is gonna be copied
over as exactly 38.9, and
lima.lon is gonna be evaluated
to be the minus 77 that it is.
And then that minus 77 is
what's passed to lonIn.
Now we're gonna copy the values
over just like we did before.
We're gonna copy into this.lat.
We're gonna copy into this.lon.
And then at the very end of this
constructor, and we're going to hook up
washDC to that lat and that lon.
Or that object that contains the lat and
the lon.
So, this is our memory
module at this point.
Is this close to what you got?
I hope it was.
It's worthwhile walking through a couple
more of these memory model problems.
Keep in mind that when we
are drawing memory models,
the purpose of this is to
really understand your code.
It's difficult to reason and
debug code if you are not drawing
the memory model associated with it.