As we can see working through this module,
it's important that we have
this concept challenges.
So, the reason we're
doing these again is that
it's important test on
your own understanding.
You can listen to us talk about
the material but till you really tried to
apply it, you don't know for sure
whether your understanding it correctly.
So this is an opportunity for you to
identify potential misconceptions in your
standard or to gain confidence in the fact
that you're understanding it properly.
Process again, we're gonna pause,
you're gonna try to solve it yourself.
You're gonna discuss it with
potentially other learners around you.
You're gonna watch UCSD learners
talk about the concepts and
then you're gonna confirm your
understanding with our explanation.
So the problem for
this one is to walk through this code.
Again, always start executing in main.
In the very end of main,
there's going to be a print.
The question is what gets printed?
>> Hi, I'm Tenki.
>> Hi, I'm Peter.
>> Hi, I'm Joe.
>> All right.
So let's go ahead and get started.
So, I guess we can all agree.
So location one is going to create a new
SimpleLocation with those values, and
location two is going to create another
SimpleLocation with those values as well.
>> And
we're talking about objects right here?
>> Yeah, so we're gonna have two different
objects, location one and location two.
And what I got stuck at was when
location one equals location two.
So what I was thinking was
that the values inside loc2
are actually going to copy over into loc1.
>> Oh, like a whole new object?
>> Well, not exactly a whole new object,
but just the values of the latitude and
the longitude into loc1.
So, currently.
>> So
it would look like rewrite the object.
>> Yeah, yeah, so currently loc1 has 39.9.
For the latitude.
And well I was thinking that
location two's latitude,
55.8, would overwrite that.
Am I right or?
>> I think those are like
two objects right?
Like they're separate.
So I think the third eye is
just change of reference here.
So it won't like overwrite like
the every member variable here.
>> So rewrite the arrow?
Where location one is pointing?
>> Right.
>> So location one is now going to
reference to the same object that location
two is referencing.
>> You just follow the arrow.
>> So that means that location
one's values do change, but
it's just because it's
referencing a new object.
>> Correct.
>> Yeah.
>> All right.
So when loc1.lat gets -8.3 that means that
the latitude of loc1 changes to -8.3 but
since that's the same object
referenced by location two.
Does that mean location two's
latitude changes to -8.3?
>> Yeah, I think so.
>> Yeah, because it's all just one object.
>> That was a great discussion
by the UCSD learners.
Let's walk through the code
again one more time.
So you're gonna start in main.
You're gonna create a simple
location reference,
loc1 that's gonna point to an object.
And we just did those memory models so
we'll do this one a little
bit more quickly.
We're gonna recognize that this is
gonna create a reference loc1 pointing
to an object on the heap
which has these values.
We're then gonna create a second object.
This one's going to be loc2, and
loc2 is pointing to
a different object on the heap.
The key part of this problem is what
happens in this next statement.
What happens when you assign
loc1 to be equal to loc2?
What really happens there?
To understand that,
we're gonna have to think about
what those references really mean.
So loc2 points to this object, and
what that really means is that
loc2 has a numeric value,
which is an address for
that object on the heap.
And that object on the heap
actually has that address.
So you can think of loc1.
We're throwing in
arbitrary addresses here.
But loc1 has address 1,
it points to that object on the heap.
Loc2 has address 2, and
it's pointing to that object on the heap.
When you do loc1 equals loc2, you're
really copying essentially the reference.
That means is you're copying the address.
So loc1 is now gonna point to
the exact same thing that loc2 does.
Now I'm gonna do loc1.lat
equals this negative value.
And that really is loc1 points
the same thing that loc2 points to.
And it's gonna change that
object point2 by loc1.
Then we're gonna go to print this we're
gonna print using the loc2 reference but
again loc2 and loc1 are pointing to
the exact same thing on the heat so
when loc2 prints out its lat and
lon it's gonna print out -8.3, and 37.6.
Again, drawing these memory models helps
you understand how to work through these
problems.