[SOUND] In this support video,
we'll be practicing two
really important skills.
First we'll be tracing code using
the memory models that we've been talking
about before, for
both object and primitive data.
But we'll also be developing a skill
of tracing code and talking about
it in high level terms, beyond step
by step what each statement does.
Now you want to make sure that
you are ready to participate.
Get a pencil out and
work with me through this.
You'll learn much better if you're
working through it yourself as well.
So let's start with a piece of code
that we'll be thinking about and
take a few seconds to read it carefully
and try to explain, in your own words,
what this piece of code does.
All right, welcome back.
It's very useful to try to
think about how the code and
the syntax that we have in
Java translate to steps and
procedures that we can understand
as high level human beings.
So for example,
if we're thinking about this in words.
What we might say is that we
create a couple of objects and
then we try to assign those
objects to one another.
When we say assign objects to one another,
that's very imprecise and so
this gives us an added perspective
on the benefit of tracing code and
on the benefit of the precision
that comes with memory model.
All right, so let's see what
we do when we trace the code.
We remember that in order to declare
SimpleLocation type objects,
what we need is to think about
the SimpleLocation class.
And we're using the class definition
that you've seen in the core videos for
this module.
So you'll be fairly familiar
with this definition, but
you can look at it here as well.
The first line of code that we have is
a declaration and an assignment statement.
We're reserving some space and
memory, we're labeling it ucsd, and
what we would like to have there
is a reference to a new object.
That new object is of type SimpleLocation,
and
it's initialized using
the constructor to some values.
So what that means is we have
a box in our memory model.
It's labeled by the name
of the variable UCSD and
we point to this new object that we've
created whose instance variables,
latitude and longitude are set to 32.9 and
negative 117.2 respectively.
And that's all there
is to that first line.
Shall we go on to the next line, and
that next line has exactly the same form.
We're declaring a variable,
that variable is of type SimpleLocation,
and so
we have a reference to a new object.
That object is being created
by the constructor and
those instance variables
have their own values.
And notice that those instance variables
for this new object are completely
separate from the variables that
we had for the previous object.
We've constructed completely
new copies of these objects.
All right, now we get to the third line.
In this third line we're not
creating any new objects,
we're not declaring any new variables.
What we're going is we're
doing an assignment statement.
And an assignment statement, what we
would like to do is to assign the value
on the right-hand side to
the variable on the left-hand side.
And so let's think a little bit
more about what's actually stored
inside these variables.
So UCSD, that box in our memory model,
has an arrow to an object but
remember that arrow to the object
is our visual shorthand for
saying we have stored the address
in memory of that object.
So something like @15.
15 is a made up number here,
it's to indicate some address,
the address of the object
that we created before.
Similarly, the box associated with
the variable kumamoto stores an address,
which is the address that the reference
to a new object of type SimpleLocation.
So it's got a different address,
because we've got two different objects.
Now what we need to do in this
assignment statement is we need to copy
the contents of the box
kumamoto to the box ucsd.
And so that means that the @34 reference
gets copied into the ucsd box.
And so if we think that in
terms of our memory model,
what's happening here is that now both of
these variables refer to the same object.
The object of the address @34.
Okay.
So that's what
we've done with this assignment statement.
But now what happens when we go to
the last statement in this code snippet?
Here what we're trying to do is,
we're trying to assign the value
that's stored in the variable
ucsd to the variable kumamoto.
But if we look at that value that's stored
at the variable ucsd, it's the address
of the object that we had before that
was also pointed to by kumamoto.
So actually executing this
assignment does nothing at all.
It's saying copy @34 to kumamoto and
that was the previous value
of kumamoto before as well.
So at the end of executing this
line of code, if we were to
test it using the strategy we talked about
before by throwing it into a class and
executing into the main method of class
and then running that piece of code.
Then we see both UCSD and
Kumamoto both of those variables
pointed to the same object.
With the latitude and
longitude variables set as we did when
we constructed the Koumoto object.