So Leo introduced binary search
trees in the previous video, and
what we'd like to do now is really focus
in on the performance of algorithms that
use binary search trees,
because with all of these data structures
that we're talking about, one of the big
motivations for introducing a data
structure is to get better performance.
So let's see if we do that
with binary search trees.
So in particular,
by the end of this video,
you'll be able to explain the running
time performance of looking for
a word in a binary search tree and
comparing this performance with other data
structures that we have where we
might want to search for words.
So, in particular, for linked lists.
All right, so let's think back to
binary search trees and, in particular,
in the programming assignment that you
were working through we'll be using
binary search trees to store dictionaries.
So we are storing lists of words and we
like to be able to lookup and search for
words in this data structure.
So we're gonna do just a small
example with these words, and
let's think about what
binary search trees we might
get if we start building
a tree using these words.
So it turns out that it's not just
a single binary search tree that
might result.
We could get any of these three or
others potentially.
Depending on the order in which
we insert words into the tree.
And so you can follow along and
each one of these trees and confirm that,
in fact, when you look at a node
that's to the left of a node,
and a node that's on its right,
each time you're going to get the one
that's on the left is alphabetically
before the one that's on the right.
Whether it be in the green,
binary search tree where we all have
just a single path going down or
in one of the bushier trees that you
see on the right hand side as well.
All right, so we have these three
different binary search trees.
All try to capture that same set
of words that form our dictionary.
And that's going to be interesting when
we think about performance because we
have to think about each
of these different possible
binary search trees that
we might be working with.
So let's think about the isWord method for
looking up a word
in the binary search tree, so
looking up a word in the dictionary.
You can think about an application where
we were just building the tree and
we're trying to add new words to it.
And so every time we're looking up
to see if it's already in there and
then perhaps adding to it.
Or you can think about searching
through a big collection of data and
trying to find some particular
piece that we care about.
In either situation what we want to
do is we want to start at the root
of the tree, and
we want to compare the word that we care
about to the value at the current node.
Now, if at the current node we actually
don't have a word, if the current is null,
then that means that we haven't
found our word that we care about.
It's not in the tree and
so we return false.
On the other hand,
what we want to do is we wanna compare
the word that we care about to the current
word, and if it actually agrees with it.
Then we wanna return true.
And so if we found the word,
then we're happy, and we can return true.
On the other hand, we have two
possibilities for what happens if our node
isn't null and if the current word doesn't
agree with the word that we want to find.
Either the word that we want to find is
alphabetically before the current word, or
it's alphabetically
after the current word.
And if it's alphabetically
before the current word,
then we only need to look at the sub
tree to the left of the current word.
If the word that we care about is
alphabetically greater than or
after the word that we're
looking at right now,
then we need to look at the right
sub tree of the binary search tree.
All right, so, let's think about
what that might look like and
remember when we're analyzing performance
we want to think about best case and
worst case performance,
you want to think about average case.
And with each situation it's useful
to work through some examples and
see what does it mean to get lucky
when we're running this method on
particular inputs, and
what does it mean to get unlucky?
And also we need to think about
what size of input do we,
what does it mean to talk
about the size of the input?
What input do we have to this method?
And when you think about
this isWord method,
what we're doing is searching
through a collection.
And so the relevant input size,
is the size of the dictionary.
The number of words we're looking through.
It's not so
much the length of the current word.
much how many words we're looking for but,
it's the size of the dictionary,
the number of words
that we're storing that we're looking
through in order to find the word to find.
Okay, so our input size, or n,
is the number of words in our dictionary.
And what we'd like to think about is how
to relate the performance of this method
is word, to that size.
How does our performance change as the
number of words in the dictionary changes?
So let's, for example,
look at what happens when we
run isWord on the word east.
And what we have to do using our
algorithm is look first at the root
of the binary search tree.
And oh yay, we're lucky,
we hit our desired word, east, right away.
And so that means that for this particular
run of the algorithm, we've got just
a single comparison that we make between
the argument and a value of the tree.
And so, well that comparison
might take a few operations, but
if we are lucky in the very first probe
of the binary search tree, the very first
comparison we make, that's going to
take a constant number of operations.
It's not going to depend on how
big the tree was if we already
were successful when
we looked at the root.
So in the best case, the case
where we find our word right away,
the performance of this algorithm
is big O(1), constant time.
But, we're not always lucky.
So, let's look at another case where
the word that we're looking for
isn't at the root.
So let's think about what happens
when we look for the word, a.
So we start at the root.
And we compare east and a, and we notice
that a happens alphabetically before east.
So we have to look at that left
sub-tree of the binary search tree.
Now we're looking at comparing a with at.
All right,
a is still alphabetically at at.
It's a prefix of at so it comes earlier.
So we look to the left.
And now we're comparing a with am.
All right, now again a is
alphabetically before am, and so
we have to look to the left, but
we didn't find anything there.
The children of am are null.
And so what we notice is
we've fallen off the tree.
A does not occur in our dictionary.
And so we can return an answer that says
It is not a word in our dictionary so
false.
Now that's okay, it's okay if we
don't always find the word, but
what we are curious about
here is the performance.
How long did it take us to
come to this conclusion?
And notice that we compared here our words
to find a with three out of a seven words
in the dictionary and so we're working
through examples, but we really care about
the general case so can we extrapolate
what it means to think about three out of
the seven words to a general case
as the dictionary gets really big.
Well, that seems hard.
So, let's think about maybe some
more examples that will give us
insight into the general case.
And in particular we have to
remember that our binary search tree
might be organized
a little bit differently.
So let's think about the exact
same input a but with a different
characterization of the binary search
tree so a different organization of it.
And so if we had that linear version
of the binary search tree what happens,
how many comparisons we need to do as we
look for the word a amongst the seven
words in the dictionary that we
populated the search tree with.
So again, we compare first to the root and
we see that a comes before e, so
we go to the left.
We compare with the next word.
A is still before e and
so we go to the left.
We compared a with e here, and
we see that we still have to go left.
We compare a with ate,
we still have to go left.
We compare a with at,
We compare a with m, and we notice
that now we fall off the tree, and
we see that a is not in there.
But we have to compare with every single
one of the words in our dictionary
in order to come to this conclusion.
So notice that this was
even worse than before
in terms of the number of
comparisons that we had to do.
And so if we're doing worst case analysis,
then this is the kind of tree
that we need to think about.
So, not only did we have to think about
the number of elements in the dictionary,
so here, n was seven, we also had to
think about how the tree was organized,
and what organization would lead
us to the worst case behavior,
the worst possible behavior.
And, so, we see that in this linear tree,
when we're looking for a word
that's not on the tree, in the worst
case we have to make o of n comparisons.
We had to compare our word with every
single one of the words in the dictionary.
Okay, so, that leads us to this analysis
of how can we avoid the worst case?
So in the worse case we
had this linear tree.
And we had to go all the way to
the bottom to the first time that we fell
off the tree.
And then we're only then we'll
be able to return false.
But maybe we can think of
a modification of our data structure,
that will help us avoid the situation.
And so what we'd like to do is think
about how the path that we have
to travel until we fall off
the tree can be controlled.
Or if there is a property of the tree that
we can impose that will make sure that we
don't have to go too far.