[MUSIC]
Welcome back.
In this lesson, we get to start
working with polymorphism in detail.
Now, polymorphism, along with inheritance,
is one of the most powerful features
that we have in the java language.
So what we're gonna do here is just
revisit why we have polymorphism.
So you're goal from this video is just
to be able to explain it's purpose, and
why we have it.
Now, we've already done some polymorphism.
You've already had a different super class
reference pointing to a sub class object.
That's very hard, this polymorphism.
What we're gonna do then,
is give a couple examples then,
with the hierarchy that we already have.
So our hierarchy, again is
the Person class, the Student class,
the Faculty class.
And now you notice that I've
added to this Faculty class, and
now it has an employeeID number,
which is a string.
It has toString method just like
Person does, just like Student does.
So all three of our classes
now have toString methods.
We're gonna use this in the next context.
We said in the very first
videos on inheritance,
that one of the nice features is that
you can have a single data structure
point to multiple objects of that type.
So I'm allowed to have a person array,
which has room for three references.
And have one of those
references be a person,
one of those references be a student,
and one of those references be faculty.
And the reason I'm allowed to do that
is because a person is a person,
a student is a person,
and a faculty is a person.
So I'm allowed to have this array,
and what I'd like to do then,
is just iterate through the array.
And call the toString method
on each of the elements.
And what you do is,
pause for a few seconds and think about
what should happen when I do this.
All right, if you were saying,
I hope it calls the toString method for
each of the objects based on their
dynamic type, you're spot on.
That's exactly what we wanna have happen.
I want the toString method for person
to call the person's two string method.
And I want the toString method for student
to call the student's toString method.
And I want the toString method being
called on that third element to be called
on the faculty member, and the faculty
object, and that's exactly what happens.
So.
What polymorphism gives us,
is the ability to keep all of our
objects in one big collection.
And then call methods on every
single one of our elements and
the appropriate method is
what actually gets called.
But this does get a little
confusing at times,
because we have a different reference
point to a different type of object.
To understand this in more depth,
we have to look at compile time rules and
run time rules, and
we'll do that in the next video.