[MUSIC]
Hello, I'm Ken.
One time when I struggled during
a program assignment was with,
it was based on polymorphism and
inheritance.
What you had to do was create
classes of different animals and
connect them through inheritance and
polymorphism.
And what was hard about it when
I first opened the assignment,
it was just a blank screen, a blank
text editor, and I was overwhelmed.
I didn't know where to start.
What really helped was
the online posting and
everyone conversating on Piazza and
that forum.
What also helped was just really stepping
away from it just a little bit and
giving it some time just because I was so
overwhelmed by it at that moment,
just really calming down and
taking a break from the material.
And then revisiting it allowed me to,
I think, get it done.