[MUSIC]
Hi, welcome back to our
lessons on polymorphism.
So with the lessons today,
we're gonna focus on compile
time rules versus runtime rules.
And once you understand that,
all the magic that might appear to be
associated with polymorphism goes away.
There's a saying here in our
integral classes at UCSD,
which is think like a compiler,
act like a runtime environment.
That phrase comes from one of our really
popular lecturers here, Rick Ord.
And why I like that saying so
much is that there are two pieces that
happen whenever you execute code.
The first step is a compiler has
to interpret the code you wrote.
In the second step,
that's when the runtime environment
gets to execute that interpreted quote.
So you have to be able to
see your code in two lights.
You have to do this especially when
we're thinking about Polymorphism.
The truth is you've already started to
wear these two hats when we started
talking about constructors.
So let's continue with this by
looking at the compile time rules and
the runtime rules when it
comes to polymorphism.
So what this is gonna allow us to do then,
is to step through the decisions made
both at compile time and runtime.
So the rules, first off, compiler rules.
Compiler can only know the reference type.
Doesn't know the runtime
type of the object.
It only knows the reference type.
Which means when you try
call a method on object,
it can only look in that reference
type class for that method.
The goal of the compiler is
to output a method signature,
which will then be executed at runtime.
So let's walk through this
in detail with our example.
So we have our Person class,
we have our Student class.
I've got a Person reference
point to the Student object, and
I'm gonna call the toString
method on that Student object.
The compiler only knows that
this is a Person reference.
So when you try call toString it's
gonna look in the Person class, and
find that toString method.
Then it's gonna emit a compile time,
a method signature.
A compile time,
which is a no parameter toString method,
which is to be executed at runtime.
That leads us, then, to our runtime rules.
At runtime,
you have to follow the exact runtime type
of the object to find that method.
So what you're gonna do is match
the method signature, which was emitted at
compile time, to the appropriate method
within the actual runtime class.
Let's walk through that.
Where we left off was the compiler had
already emitted a method signature,
which was toString with no arguments.
And when we attempt to do s.toString,
now at runtime, it knows that s
is actually a Student object.
So it's gonna find the toString
method in Student, and
that's what's gonna be
executed at runtime.
So, now that we know these rules,
let's look at a couple more examples.
So first,
let's say I have a Person reference,
s, pointing to a Student object.
And what I want do is call
the getSID method on my Student.
What I want you to do is take
a few seconds to think about this.
What do you think's gonna happen?
All right if you said this was
gonna cause problems, you're right.
The reason it's gonna cause problems
is because the compiler can only know
that s is a Person reference.
So the compiler can only look in
the Person class for that method.
It's gonna look there and
it's not gonna find a getSID method.
Which means the compiler is
gonna give you an error and say,
I can't find this method
in the Person class.
Now you might say, well wait a second,
I know that this is always gonna be
a Student object,
it should be allowed to call SID.
Well, we're going to be able to do that,
but
we're going to have to do that
through explicit casting.
We're going to cover
casting in the next video.