[MUSIC]
Continuing working with
Polymorphism in Java.
Specifically, continuing with
the compile-time decisions and
the runtime decisions that are made.
To help aid a compiler,
we can sometimes use the term casting.
So the goal of this video is to be able to
walk through those decisions that compile
time and runtime and
also be able to cast objects.
Where we left off in the last video,
was we had just done this example.
Where we attempted a call to
getSID method on a Student object,
but we were unable to because
s is a person reference.
What we'd like to be able to do is tell
the compiler, hey I know this is gonna
be a student at runtime,
could you let me call this method?
The way you do that is casting.
Now casting of objects works
very similarly to the way it
works with primitive types.
So we always have automatic
type promotions, so
you can always go from int to a double.
And likewise, you can always go from
a Subclass up to a Superclass reference.
This technique is
sometimes called widening.
Likewise, we can explicitly narrow.
So we can explicitly cast
from a double to an int.
And likewise, we can take a Superclass and
explicitly cast it down to be a Subclass.
This again is known as narrowing.
Now I can't stress this enough.
You have to be careful when you narrow.
The reason why is because you're
telling the compiler to trust you.
You're saying trust me, compiler,
I know this is gonna be
a Subclass reference at runtime.
And then the compilers
gonna believe you and
then you're gonna try
to do this at runtime.
So let's walk through this again now,
let's fix this with casting.
So I've got my Person reference,
Student object.
I can't call getSID,
because it's not in Person.
But the way I can fix this is by
casting it to be a Student reference.
And by doing so, now the compiler
will look in Student, find getSID.
And it will let you execute this code.
This is gonna work just fine.
But what if I change this and I make it so
that it's a Person reference
pointing to a Person object.
I'm still gonna cast to Student and
I'm gonna try a call getSID.
And I want you to do is pause for
a second and
think what do you think
should happen here?
If you're thinking that this is gonna
cause problems, you're on the right track.
There is no getSID method in Person.
How could it possibly call that?
And the problem's really gonna come
about at the point of the cast.
If you try and do this,
you're gonna get a runtime error.
And it's gonna say ClassCastException.
What it tried to do is it tried to
cast your Person to a Student and
it couldn't because its a Person object.
In a sense you've broken
the compiler's trust at this point.
Again you told the compiler,
I know this is gonna be a student and
it didn't turn out to be.
What would be really great is
if we could just test this.
Say, is this a student?
Before I do the cast.
And the way we can do this is
using an operator instanceof.
So this performs a runtime check of
whether or not there is a relationship.
So if you say s instanceof Student,
what it's gonna do is gonna check,
is s an instance of a Student.
Or does s is a relationship
with Student at runtime?
Now if you do this check
with a conditional,
you'll then be able to only execute this
when it actually is a Student object.
At this point, with the Compile Time
Decisions we've discussed and the Runtime
decisions we've discussed, polymorphism
should make a great deal of more sense.