In this concept challenge we're gonna
have some fun with polymorphism and
dynamic binding.
We want it to be a little bit challenging,
but hopefully not too far beyond the reach
of what you can do with your new
knowledge about how this works.
So you know the drill.
You're going to pause,
answer the question on your own,
discuss it with people around you or
online, watch our learner videos, and
then confirm your understanding
with our explanation.
So what's the problem?
Here it is.
We two classes for you,
the student class and the person class.
The person class is the base class.
It has a private member variable name and
then the number of methods.
There's one constructor.
It takes an argument.
There's a method called isAsleep.
It takes an integer argument,
and it returns a boolean.
The integer argument indicates the time of
day, in term of hours on a 24 hour clock,
and a person is asleep between
the hours of 10 PM, or 22, and 7 AM.
So between those hours,
isAsleep will return true.
It also has a two string method
which just returns its name, and
then it has a status method which also
takes an integer argument for the hour.
And what it's gonna do is it's gonna check
to see if the person is asleep at that
hour, and if it is,
it will say the person is offline or
print a message to that effect.
And if they're not asleep then it'll print
a message saying the person is online.
That's the person class.
The student class extends
the person class.
And so it inherits a bunch of things from
the person, and then what it does is it
overrides the isAsleep method to slightly
change the hours that a student is asleep.
So a student in our world here is only
asleep between the hours of 2 AM and 8 AM.
So if we call isAsleep between those hours
then the student will report being asleep.
So the question for you is, what happens
when we create a reference to the person,
set that reference equal to
a new student object, and
then call the status method on that
object at time 1 in the morning?
>> I'm Alicia.
>> I'm Joanna.
>> And I'm Justin.
>> So actually when I looked at this code
I was wondering if person can
actually even be a student.
>> I think student can be
a person since it extends person.
So.
>> I agree with Justin because student
is a person, and you know it's a person.
So it's just a more
specific type of person.
>> What do you think it prints out?
>> Mm..
I don't know.
Will it even print out?
Because there are two,
if you look in the public class person and
in the class student,
both of them have method is asleep.
Which is called in the second
line of the of the method status?
So, how does the compiler know,
which one to call?
So wouldn't it just freak out,
and stop, and be an error?
>> I think it has something
to do with the this call.
>> Oh.
>> So,
maybe this this tells it
which method it's calling.
And I guess since we can
have it be a student,
it's probably calling students is asleep.
>> Yeah, I think that's correct, yeah.
>> What I was confused about
was within status [CROSSTALK]
>> Yes.
>> It calls is asleep.
In this well,
it calls isAsleep when it's in person.
So shouldn't this be a person?
>> It's a good, it's pretty tricky.
>> But we assigned person to be a student,
right?
Oh.
>> So at this point perhaps at compile
time maybe it'll call is asleep in
the person class, but maybe at run time,
it'll say this is a student, and
then call students is asleep.
>> Okay.
>> All right,
there's a lot going on here so
let's trace through this very carefully.
The first thing we have to
think about is even though P
is a person reference, the actual
object it refers to is a student.
So when we call p.status
at one in the morning,
we're calling that dot
status on a student object.
This is what Java does at run time.
It determines that P refers
to a student object and
that's the type that it's going
to call the status method on.
So we're gonna look in the student
class for the status method.
And so we look here,
well we don't see a status method.
But that's no problem because student
extends person, so Java will just go ahead
and look in the superclass to see
if there's a status method there.
And it turns out there is.
Here's our status method.
So we can start tracing through the status
method to see what actually happens.
The first thing we do is
we have an if statement.
And that If statement asks this.isAsleep.
So the question is,
is this asleep at the particular hour?
Now what is this?
Well even though we're currently in the
person class, that's where the code is.
This is at run time determined
to be a student object.
Because the student object is the one
that called this method originally.
So this dynamically binds
to the student object.
And that's the class where
there is asleep gets called.
So we go back down here and
we use the student's version of is asleep
to determine if the student is
asleep at one in the morning.
Now I already said the student only
sleeps between two in the morning and
eight in the morning.
So the student is not asleep
at one o'clock and so
we'll fall through to this else condition.
And print out that this student is online,
says now online,
this is what it'll print, now online.
And the students name is Sally.
That's it.