All right.
If you thought that last Polymorphism
concept challenge was fun,
you are gonna love this one.
This one is gonna bring
it to a whole new level.
It's more challenging than the last one,
that we just gave you.
In fact, it's beyond what we've
even explicitly taught you.
So, we want you to really push the bounds
of your reasoning and, understanding.
You know the drill, do it yourself,
discuss it with your friends,
watch our videos,
confirm your understanding.
So, here's the challenge, we now have
three classes in an inheritance hierarchy.
So, base class that we're
working with here, is a Person.
And, it has two methods,
method1 and method2.
We have a class that extends the Person
class, which is the Student class.
It overrides both method1 and method2.
And then we have the Undergrad class,
which extends the Student class and
it inherits the method1 method, but
it overrides the method2 method.
So, that's in a nutshell
what we're working with.
Here's the code in more detail, and you're
gonna need to work through this code and
look at it carefully as you
work through this challenge.
And, what the challenge is, is when
we create a new undergraduate object,
refer to it as a reference of type person,
and
we call method1 on that
newly created object.
What gets printed out?
>> Hi, I'm Steven.
>> Hi, I'm Joanna.
>> Hi, I'm Justin.
>> So, what do you think?
>> I don't know,
I was getting caught up on this first one.
So, it says it calls for method1.
But I don't see a method1 in Undergrad.
So I think it would be a compile error.
>> I don't think it would
be a compile error.
If you notice Undergrad extends Student.
So, in the Student class
there is a method1, so
I think it inherits that method.
Yeah, I agree, so.
>> Yeah.
>> It does print Student 1.
What I got a little bit tripped up on was,
I wasn't sure which,
when it calls super.method1 in
the method1 of the Student class,
I wasn't sure which method1 it would call.
Because isn't it in Undergrad?
So wouldn't the super.method1,
it might just call Student and
go into an infinite,
like calling itself over and over.
Right?
>> Yeah, I can see how you
could get caught up on that.
But I think when super, it's always
talking about the class above it.
So I think it actually would be calling
the method1 and the person class.
>> Okay.
>> What about method2?
Does it call Students method2 or
which method2 does it refer to?
>> I think that since it is in Undergrad?
It will call Undergrad's method2 and
it'll print undergrad 2.
So, if it doesn't go infinitely,
like you said, then it should be D.
>> All right, let's trace this together,
because it's non-trivial.
We're gonna start our tracing up here,
where the method is originally called.
So the type of the object referred
to by you is an Undergraduate.
So at runtime, that's where Java is
going to look for this method, method1.
When we look down here in
the undergraduate, in the Undergrad class.
Class, we don't see a method1.
But luckily we can see that
Undergrad extends Student.
So Java is gonna go look in
the Student class for method1.
So looking up here in Student class,
it finds method1.
Great.
So now I can start executing.
So the first thing it's going to do is
execute that first line which prints
Student 1.
So what gets printed so far?
It's Student 1.
Now we keep going to the next line.
The next line says super.method1.
So what is the super class
of the Student class?
Well, it's the Person class.
So this happens at compile time.
When this code is compiled,
Java notices that there's a call to
the super class inside this method and so
it looks and sees well what
is the superclass of student?
It's Person.
So it's going to bind to the method1
inside the Person class.
And that's where we'll go now.
So we go up here to method1 and
we execute it's code.
It's code sized.
It should print out Person 1, so
that's what gets printed next.
So, so far we've printed Student
1 first and then Person 1.
But let's continue.
We now return back to where we were,
which was inside the method1 method
in the student class and
we say call method2.
All right, well where are we going to now?
Which method2 are we talking about?
In order to answer this question,
we first need to notice that since we
don't have a calling object at this point,
what Java is going to do is
to insert the keyword this.
So, we're calling method2
on the calling object.
Now, as you saw from the last
concept challenge on Polymorphism,
this is going to bind at runtime.
So, we're gonna look at the actual
type of the object disc at runtime.
This is what's tricky about this example.
So, the actual type of this
object at runtime, as you recall,
was an Undergrad object.
So we're gonna go down here
into the Undergrad class and
call the method2 inside
the Undergrad class.
So that's going to print out,
Undergrad 2, and
we have the following that gets printed.
First, Student 1, then Person 1,
and then finally Undergrad 2.
So the purpose of this example was
to show you the difference between
what happens with a call to super and then
a method and a call to this and a method.
Those calls to super and
then a method get bound to compile time.
So in compile time,
Java is going to look at the code and
figure out what class it's in and
what the super class of that class is.
But when we call this and then a method
name, that's gonna happen at runtime.
So Java is gonna use the actual
type of the object at runtime.
It's a little confusing but, understanding
these details can help you debug some
nasty bugs that you might
otherwise encounter in your code.
So, good Luck.