[MUSIC]
All right, welcome back to our module on
inheritance and polymorphism in Java.
In this video, we're gonna be discussing
abstract classes and interfaces.
Specifically, we're gonna be talking about
what it means to be an abstract class or
an interface, and how to use
keywords like abstract or interface.
We're gonna be comparing inheritance of
implementation against
inheritance of interface.
And we're gonna give you the tools to
help decide between abstract class, or
an interface,
when designing your class hierarchy.
To get started, let's look at our
hypothetical with our Person class.
So now we're still working in the
university, but let's change things a bit.
Let's change it so we're working for
the accounting department.
And here we're essentially responsible for
handling bills and paychecks.
Now in this context,
it doesn't really make sense to have
a generic Person object any more.
Right, we're only gonna be working
either with students or faculty.
And we're also going to change the context
in the sense that I want to be able to
send out monthly statements.
So, essentially,
I wanna a method in the Person class,
which sends out a monthly statement
to either students or faculty.
The features I'd like to have here is I'd
like to be able to force my subclasses,
both my student and my faculty class,
to override this method.
I'd like to stop having
actual Person objects,
because they don't make sense
in this context anymore.
But I'd like to keep
having Person references.
And I'd also like to keep that common
code we had, like the name of the person.
If I want to do all these things
I want to use an abstract class.
The way to define an abstract
class is essentially
just to use the keyword abstract.
So if I say public abstract class Person,
it means this class, you cannot create
instances of objects of this type.
So I can't actually create
an object of type Person, but
I now can create an objects of, say,
derived classes, which are concrete.
If I have any method within this class,
be abstract then I have to make
it the whole class abstract.
But what I can do then is say, have
a public abstract void monthlyStatement.
I can say, my derived classes
have to override this method.
It's a nice way of forcing
the subclasses to have methods.
With an abstract class,
you get two things.
You get to inherit both implementation and
interface.
And what I mean by that is that with
an implementation you get instance
variables or methods,
which essentially define that common
behavior that any person should have.
And you also get an interface.
You say what methods and interests have
to be overridden in my subclasses.
Now, there's gonna be times when
you don't necessarily want both.
You may just want the interface.
If you want just the interface,
then you're gonna use interfaces.
And if we go back to our example,
I really believe an abstract class is
appropriate for the hypothetical
that we were just talking about.
But let's say that you had no
common code in the Person class.
If there's something common there,
then you just use an interface.
And an interface will give us the ability
to force subclasses to have a method,
to stop having actual Person objects,
and will allow us to keep
having Person references.
Now interfaces only define
the methods that are required, and
classes can inherit actually
from multiple interfaces.
So you can inherit from
an abstract class and
also inherit from multiple interfaces,
all within one class.
So let's look at an example
of an interface.
So the most common one discussed
is the comparable interface.
Now comparable gives you
the ability to compare an object
to another object of that same type.
You're gonna notice some terminology here,
those brackets with the E,
that refers to Generics.
We'll discuss those a bit more later.
This allows us to compare two objects.
Now why would I want
an interface like this?
Take a few seconds to think about it,
I'll come back.
All right.
If you're thinking it's useful to be able
to compare objects in case you, say,
wanna sort them, that's exactly
the purpose for having Comparable.
So if you wanna have a data structure and
know some way of storing and
ordering among those objects, comparable's
exactly what you wanna do for the objects.
And the way that we would do this for
say the Person class,
is to say, have the Person class
implement a Comparable interface.
And then within that all I have to do
is override that one method, compareTo,
and then define the behavior I want.
In this case,
I define the behavior to be a comparison
of the strings using the compareTo method
in the string class, because the string
class implements the Comparable interface.
So if you're trying to design a class
hierarchy, you're often gonna be
wondering, should I be making this
an interface or an abstract class?
And the general rule of thumb is,
if you just want to require methods,
that's an interface.
If you want to potentially require
methods, you don't have to, but
if you potentially want
to require methods, and
you wanna require a common behavior,
that's where an abstract class comes in.