[MUSIC]
So one of the ways that Google is
able to tell some new application or
a service that you have successfully
logged in, is by issuing tokens.
And there are many different
reasons that an application or
website can ask for tokens.
From an identity provider like Google.
But when we started out,
they were far fewer.
And the different flows that determine
what kind of token you will get back
are determined by say
a parameter called grant type.
So I can ask for
a token with a grant type device or
with a grant type access token or
with a grant type code.
Or the grant type assertion.
Now as the years grew on, we got more and
more grant types that we
added to this same endpoint.
So whenever someone goes to
Googleapis.com/33/token and asks for
a particular grant type, they all make
a call to the same class in our code base.
Now obviously over the past two years,
that particular class has grown really,
really large.
But there is a lot of similarities between
each of the different grant types or
what needs to be done.
The overall processing of the request,
the validation
of the various other parameters
that are sent in to the request.
And the eventual creation of a response
that needs to be sent back to the user,
all of which will always contain a token.
So it's possible to pull out each
of these aspects, or to pull
out each of these into a separate method,
and put them into an abstract class.
So that each grant type can
be processed separately, and
they all get to do the same thing,
which is to create a token response.
And that's my project for this quarter,
and essentially that's inheritance.