[MUSIC]
In this video, we'll be talking about
two different programming paradigms.
We'll be talking about
procedural programming.
And we'll also be talking about
event driven programming.
And I'd like to start with an analogy.
So think about how you start your day and
try to make sure that you have
a great day feeling well and healthy.
So when I get up, I brush my teeth.
Then, I may take some vitamins.
Brush my hair, get organized, and I have
a sequence of events that I go through,
one at a time, at the beginning of my
day to start feeling fresh and healthy.
But some days that's not quite enough.
Maybe, I have a headache.
Maybe, I need to drink some extra water,
it's really hot out.
Maybe, I need to even take
some pain medication.
And so there's a qualitative difference
between the events that are procedural
that follow a sequence that's predictable
and happen everyday on a regular basis.
And then, the actions that I take in
response to events that are maybe, not
as predictable that happen every so often
based on some sort of external stimulus.
And so now, back in programming,
we have an analogy to both
of these kinds of behaviors.
So when we think about
procedural programming,
we think about code that's
executed line by line,
one statement after another potentially,
with some predictable control flow.
So this is akin to all of the programs
that we've been writing in this course
up until now and
the code that you probably written before.
So we'd execute one statement.
And then we come to a foreloop and
we'd go through that foreloop and
execute one at a time.
And what that means is that even though
the execution might be a little bit
different, depending on the values
of variables that we're using.
We still can trace through the code and
understand what is going to happen at each
moment based on the state of the program.
On the other hand,
what we'll be developing in this
module is event driven programming.
And what this allows us to do,
is incorporate the power of interactivity.
So, we'd like to be able for our programs
to respond to stimulus, from users,
from sensors.
We'd like it to be able to respond
to interfaces like mouses or mice,
keyboards, multi touch technology.
But also,
things like thermometers or timers,
if we're thinking about programs powering
remote devices or wearable sensors.
So event driven programming
is incredibly useful.
And we'll talk about more of how
to implement it in the next video.