[SOUND] In the previous video we
introduced event driven programming.
And what we'll do now is trace
through some code that uses events.
So by the end of this video you will have
experience at tracing the execution of
a piece of code that has both some
procedural elements to it and
also some event driven code.
Well I'd like to start with an example
that should be completely familiar
at this point.
We've been playing a lot with maps and
setting them up and displaying them.
And so when we have this piece of
code remember that what we see is
a map with a border around
it of grey in the canvas.
And when we think about how this
piece of code is being executed,
we set up our canvas once, as so the setup
method is executed once, and then
what our applet does is it continuously
loops and runs the draw method.
Okay, now let's try to jazz
it up a little bit and
add an additional method to our class.
So right after we've
defined the draw method,
we're going to stick in these four
lines of code and pause the video for
a second and think about what the impact
of this new method is going to be.
One thing to think about is,
when this method will be executed,
and the second thing to think about is
what the effect of that execution will be.
So let's start with the second question
because it's a little bit easier.
Let's think about what will happen if we
were to run this method and what we notice
here is that the key part is
the background color guest change.
So remember that the background method
that we're calling inside key pressed.
Is the way that we have through processing
to change the background color of our
canvas.
And what we're doing here is setting that
background color to 255, 255 ,255 and
that's our code for all white.
Because the three color channels
are set to their maximum.
R, G, and
B are all at their maximum value, and
that means that we have
a pure white color.
And so, if this method is executed,
what we expect to see is that
the background of the canvas is all white.
Something like this
picture that you see now.
But then we go back to the question of
when this method actually gets executed.
And if we think back about our
model of the setup method being run
once at the beginning of
running the applet, and
then the drama method
being continuously run.
Then it's not clear if keyPressed will
ever be executed because we don't
call keyPressed explicitly from
anywhere else in our application.
We don't call keyPressed for
example from the draw method.
The thing is though that our
application is acting as a listener.
Not only is it doing that flow of
execution of running setup and
then continuously leaping through drop but
it's also in the background listening for
user effects.
So it's trying to see if the user's trying
to interact with the program in some way.
And the kind of events that it's
looking for are keyboard presses,
mouse clicks, multi-touch actions.
And so the program is going to be able to
react to any of those kinds of events.
However, we don't need to worry about
handling all of those events ourselves.
In our unfolding maps library we
already have a default EventDispatcher.
So just by including this line
of code in our setup method what
we're telling our application is we'd like
our application to be interactive and
so, do what I'm telling you.
Set up the canvas the way I'm saying,
draw what I want, but also listen for
any of the default events
that you have in mind.
And the default event functionality
that the PApplet already works with and
UnfoldingMaps does.
Is for example if the user double-clicks
somewhere inside our map we're going to
increase their zoom level by one and
so focus in on whatever is
at the center of the map.
And we can also accomplish that zoom
level changes by hitting some plus and
minus buttons.
So that means the map that we're drawing,
the application that we're running, is
going to respond to certain user inputs,
but we could always customize the
interactivity by adding additional methods
or modifying the methods like keypress,
that we had before.
What we're doing when we're writing public
void keypress It like we did before,
is we're overriding the key press
method from the super class, PApplet.
And so, we're using the power of
inheritance that you talked about
already with Leo in the previous module.
Well, what we'll do in the future videos
is think about further interactivity and
how we want to indicate to the user
what they can tell the map to do and
how to design a good user interface.