[MUSIC]
What we'd like to do in this video
is customize our user interface and
use events in a slightly
more sophisticated way.
By the end of this video, you'll be able
to design your own user interface elements
and write the code to support them.
So let's go back to our example,
our friendly old map.
And remember those two methods that we
keep talking about, setup and draw.
But now we've added that extra twist
of having a Default Event Dispatcher
supporting zoom through mouse clicks and
keyboard presses.
And so what we're starting with
is our canvas with our map.
And what we'd like to do in this
video is add a couple of buttons.
We're going to add a couple of buttons
to control the color of the background.
So, we're going to have a white square
that will try to make that frame white and
a gray square to make the frame gray.
Okay, so
let's think about how we can do that.
And in terms of just drawing the buttons,
we already have all
the tools that we need.
If you think back to module three,
we know how to draw shapes in
an applet using the 2D primitives that
are given to us by the processing library.
For example, the primitive method rect.
Okay, so we've got these
rectangles that we can draw.
Remember that we're specifying their x and
y position and
then their width and their heights.
And we can also specify the color
that is drawn inside those rectangles
using the fill method.
But now, the question becomes
where we'd like to insert
these pieces of code to draw the two
buttons, to draw those two squares.
And there's two natural places, either in
the setup method or in the draw method.
So I encourage you to pause the video
now and think, where would you put it?
All right, come back together and
maybe you've even opened up Eclipse while
you're watching the videos, which would be
a great idea, and tried out both options.
And if you did that and
you tried out the option of sticking this
piece of code inside the setup method,
what you'll see would have happened
is that when the applet comes up.
You see the buttons very, very briefly and
then the map comes on top of them and
erases them and then the buttons
don't show up anymore, ever.
Whereas, if we put it in the draw method,
if we put those four lines of code in
the draw method, then we see them on top
of the map where they're supposed to be.
And what's happening is that
because setup is run only once.
As soon as our canvas gets overwritten
by the draw method, any code that was
designing the canvas from the setup
method doesn't get executed again and so
those elements are no longer displayed.
Okay, so we know what we need to do
in order to draw the buttons and
we know where to put those buttons, but
so far, they're not really buttons,
they're just squares.
And so we'd like to add in that
functionality to make sure that if a user
puts their mouse inside one of those
buttons or over top one of those buttons
and clicks then hopefully
the background of our map will change.
So now we get to override some methods
that are available to us because
our applet is a listener.
It's listening for mouse events and
so PApplet implements some sort of
default blank behavior to
correspond to mouse clicks.
But what we'd like to do now
is customize that behaviour
in the event of that those mouse clicks
happen inside one of those buttons.
Now there's a few different options of how
to deal with mice or with mouse clicks and
there's a few methods
that are available to us.
What we're going to use is
the mouseReleased method.
Which means that we don't
really care about when the user
starts clicking the mouse or
the fact that it was a click rather
than a click down and hold for a while.
We just want to think about
when the mouse was released and
make sure that when the mouse is
released it was inside the button and so
we wanted to react to that action.
So that means that when we think
about the mouseReleased method,
we're going to have to check
that the mouse released event
happened when the mouse was inside
the button that we want to implement.
And so
we have to go back to the coordinates
that are defining locations in our canvas.
So when we defined for example, the white
button, we said that it was a rectangle.
Whose corner was at coordinate 100,100 and
then this button is 25 pixels wide and
25 pixels high.
And so the four corner coordinates
are now up on the screen.
Which means when we're looking at the
mouse event to check that the mouse event
happens inside the button.
We want to check that
the X coordinates and
the Y coordinates of the mouse's location
are within the square that's defined by
the corners and those corner coordinates.
Now notice that we're doing
something kinda cool here,
we're accessing the coordinates of the
mouse, using a variable mouseX and mouseY.
And that's available again to us through
inheritance because those variables
are available to the applet superclass
that we're inheriting from.
So in the case where our mouse
was actually released from
inside the white button,
what we end up doing is setting the
background color of our canvas to white.
And in the other situation, when we've
calculated the corners of the gray button,
we can also set the background
color of the canvas to gray.
Of course, corresponding to a mouse
click inside the gray button.
And that's really all there is to it
to implementing a button inside this
class because we can listen for
mouse events and
we can record the location
of those mouse events.
So not only do we know that
a mouse was clicked and
released, we also know where it happened.