[MUSIC]
So, one time I struggled
in computer science.
Was actually at the end of high school.
And I had to just make one button and
have it respond to being clicked and
[LAUGH] it was the most frustrating thing.
Because I just remember,
we just got thrown into it and
I had to see what this event handler was.
There was so much terminology that
was coming in out of nowhere.
It wasn't until I sat down and
I kinda just I looked it up on YouTube and
I watched a few tutorials where I
watched them code it and explain it.
And that really helped me out.
And I realized that it wasn't as
complicated as I made it out to be,
because of all the big words.
It's actually pretty simple
when you look at it.