[SOUND] In this video, we're going to
tie together the notions of events and
listening for
user inputs with the inheritance
hierarchy in class design
in a close-knit way.
So by the end of the video, what you'll
be able to do is use the language of UML
diagrams to talk about the classes
that we're working with for
the event driven programming.
When we think about the PApplet listening
for user input, like most clicks and
keyboard input,
what we're doing actually is saying
the PApplet implements two interfaces.
PApplet is a class.
And it implements the interface which
means that it implements the methods that
are required by
the interface MouseListener.
And it also, implements the methods that
are required by the interface KeyListener.
It's fulfilling the promises
made by those interfaces.
So let's specifically think about
MouseListener as an interface.
The MouseListener makes a promise
that methods like mousePressed,
mouseClicked, and
mouseReleased will be implemented.
That we will specify what action we want
our program to take on these events and
when these methods are called.
And so our PApplet class implements
them in some default fashion.
But then when we go ahead and
create a MapWithButton class,
then we can override some of
these method implementations.
And say, not only do we want
a mouseReleased event to react in
a default way like zooming the map,
we also want to build in a functionality.
So that if the mouse is released in
a particular location in the map
we do some additional steps.
And so what we're doing here
is we're building in yet
another level of the class hierarchy.
In a similar way, PApplet implements
the KeyListener interface.
And so that means that it has to
fill in some default behaviour for
each of the methods that are promised
by the KeyListener interface.
So, are there other events?
We've been talking about mouse clicks.
We've been talking about keyboard events.
Is that all there is?
Well, we know there's still
a few other user interfaces.
For example, there's multi touch
now with touch screen displays.
But so far, that's all about the users
saying something to the program.
There are also qualitatively
different events and
qualitatively different listeners.
So for example, it turns out that, the Map
object itself can act as a listener.
Just slightly different kind of listener,
there's this
other interface called EventListener and
the UnfoldingMap implements it.
And what the UnfoldingMap listens for
is for
events to do with the map itself,
like zoom and pan.
The point of this is that
the notion of event driven program
can be used very generally, and
can help us design programs
that makes sense in the particular
context that we're working with.
Sometimes it's for UI, user interface,
but other times, it's for
interacting with more complicated objects.