[MUSIC]
In the previous videos,
Christine talked about some algorithms for
finding information in
large collections of data.
What you saw is,
if the data is organized, then it's
easier to do some of these algorithms.
So in this video, we'll talk about
ways of organizing data, and
in particular,
how to sort it in some order.
And then you'll see some
advantages of having it sorted.
So let's think back to binary search,
which is one of those algorithms for
searching that Christine presented.
Remember that when we do binary search,
at each step of the algorithm
we reduce the number of elements
that we need to look at by half.
And so, all in all we look at
about log n number of steps if
n is the size of the list of
elements that we started.
Okay, so what we remember now is that
in order for binary search to work,
the data in our list of elements has to
be sorted by what we are searching at.
So for example, if we're looking for.
The country code,
the airport code of Essen.
Then what we do with this particular
list is we looked about halfway through
our list of elements, and
oh, we found it, excellent.
Essen is right in the middle.
All right, so that's kind of silly.
Let's look for another element.
Maybe let's look for Beijing.
Let's look for
the airport code of Beijing.
And so, again, we start by looking in
the middle of our list of elements.
And then we compare Beijing with Essen and
we see that Beijing is
alphabetically earlier than Essen.
And so we only need to look at the first
half of the list because we have
the list sorted in alphabetical order.
So the order is really
helping us out here.
Now, think about this order.
Sorting, means that we list our element
in some order that we decide ahead
of time and is compatible with the search
algorithm that we're trying to do,
if the sorting is done as
a first step towards searching.
So in particular, for this example,
what we're trying to do is find a city
name, and so we're sorting our data.
Based on the first letter and
then the second letter of the city, so
we're sorting the city names
in alphabetical order.
Now, when you think about airports,
the city is not the only piece of
data associated with the airport.
We also have a country that the airport is
located in, and so it's conceivable that
instead of sorting by city, we would want
to sort our airports by, say, country.
And so we'd want to organize the airports
alphabetically according to country.
There's nothing stopping
us from doing that, but
we have to think about
why we wanna do that.
And so if we're looking for
an airport in a given country,
then it would make sense to sort all
the airports based on the country name.
And so that's why the sorting has to
be compatible with the searching.
Binary search,
when Christine presented it, she showed
you how it was absolutely necessary for
the list to be organized in order,
in order for binary search to at all work.
But before she talked about binary search,
she already talked about linear search,
which was the sort of
simpler algorithm for
looking through a collection of pieces of
data, to try to find one particular item.
And with linear search,
we didn't have to make any assumptions
about how the data was organized.
Remember that in linear search, we start
at the beginning and we flip through,
one at at time keep on going,
keep on going.
Looking for our particularly desired
piece of information or piece of data.
And that's fine.
But actually, what happen is if we happen
to know that our information is sorted,
then we get a performance payoff.
So let's think about the array of
airports in cities and countries and
let's think about trying to find the
airport code for Istanbul, for example.
What we might do in linear search is start
with the first element of our array,
Agra in India, and see,
okay, that's not Istanbul.
We have to keep on going.
Then we go to Beijing, so that's not
Istanbul, we have to keep on going.
Chicago, Essen, Lagos,
well If we were just doing linear search,
we'd have to keep on going.
Montreal, Quito, Sydney.
And then only once we got to
the end of the array, we would say,
okay, Istanbul wasn't there,
it's missing from our array.
We can't do anything, we return null.
But if we know that our array is sorted,
we actually could have stopped
a little earlier when I paused.
Right as soon as we got to
Lagos we noticed that Lagos
starts with L which is alphabetically
after I in the alphabet and
so if Istanbul was in our array it
would have to happen before Lagos.
And so we don't have to look at
the rest of the elements in the array
to know that Istanbul is missing
from this collection of data.
And so what we get here is that
if we do some up front work,
if we sort our array, if we sort our list.
Then in certain cases our
algorithm can run much faster and
we can have some logic built in to our
algorithm that says If we're sure that our
element that we're looking for is missing,
we don't have to keep on going,
we can stop right here and say.
We've reached somewhere past the
alphabetical location of where our element
would be, we don't need to keep going.
Okay.
So, so far we've seen that sorting,
which means arranging in order can help us
in both binary search and linear search.
And there's actually another algorithm
that is helped by having our data sorted.
And so let's think about the problem
of having a huge amount of information.
And we want to look for
duplicates, that you can imagine
all sorts of use cases for this.
But for that let's abstract away all
the applications and just think about.
How we would approach this question.
And so if we're given a whole bunch of
unorganized data this might be kind of
hard and we might have to leap
through the list a few times.
And figure out if there's any two
pairs in the list that are the same.
But what if we were willing
to pay some upfront cost and
sort the information first, well then.
We just need to do one pass over
the information after it's sorted, and
look at consecutive pairs of elements,
and see if they're equal,
because the duplicates would show up
right after another in the sorted list.
And so in the data that we started with,
we see that it's pretty quick to find
that 84 appears twice,
once we've sorted the list.
Alright, so I'd like to leave
you with a few questions,
what we've done in this video, is given
a taste for the algorithmic questions
we think about when we're developing
new strategies for solving problems.
So when we have an algorithm
like binary search or
like linear search,
we like to ask ourselves.
For particular cases,
how fast will this algorithm run?
How slow will it run?
How many steps do we need to take and
how lucky can we be?
So can the data or its organization,
the input from the outside world, have an
impact on the run time of the algorithm?
What's it going to be
like in the worst case?
like in the best case?
And also,
when we're developing algorithms,
sometimes we're willing to spend
a lot of energy at the beginning,
if we're going to be able to reap
the benefits from that upfront cost.
By having the later algorithms,
that maybe we do a lot of times,
be much more efficient,
because we did some overhead initial work.
So in the next few videos we're gonna
be talking about algorithms for
sorting, and hopefully now you
understand why they're so important,
because having sorted data could really
help all sorts of follow on algorithms.