[MUSIC]
So, in this video, we're going to look at
a specific algorithm for sorting data.
And throughout the examples, we're just
going to use an array of integers, but
the same ideas and principles translate
whenever we have information that's
all of the same type and we can compare
pairs of information of that type.
So by the end of this video, you'll
be able to explain the selection sort
algorithm and write code for it yourself.
So let's get started and let's think
of a toy example and it's always useful
when developing algorithms to think
of a specific concrete example
that we can work through the steps of the
algorithm with respect to this example and
then afterwards think
about generalizing it.
So let's think about
this array of integers.
And there's only six
elements in this array so
we can probably do it in our head but
let's think about it systematically how
we would go about sorting these elements.
And what we might do is, first of all,
say at the end I want the smallest element
to be in the first position of the array,
the second smallest to be in the second
position of the array, the third smallest
to be in the third position of the array,
and so on and so forth.
And so let's look for
the smallest element.
So we're looking through our entire array,
and we're looking for
the smallest element.
And lo and behold, we found it.
It's 7, it's already in the first
position, so we really don't need to do
anything else to it,
it's already where it's supposed to be.
And so we don't need to
ever think about it again.
It's in place, it's done.
And so
now what we want to do is move forward and
say, well what about the rest
of the elements in the array?
What's smallest among those?
Because whatever's smallest in
the rest of the array is going to be
the second smallest out of everything.
And so we should bring it into
the second position in the array.
Okay and so, we have now five elements
to consider, one less then before and
we're looking for the smallest element and
oh my goodness we're lucky again,
16 is the smallest it's already at the
beginning, we don't need to do anything,
leave it in place.
Okay, so
our problem is reduced further yet.
Now we need to find the third smallest
element overall, but that's just
the smallest element in the remaining
unsorted elements that we haven't thought
about yet, and so we've got four elements
to consider and we want the smallest one.
Now we see that it's 43,
it's not the first one like we
had in the previous two examples.
And so what we need to do is to
put it in it's correct location.
And it's correct location as it would
be in the sorted version of the array.
And so we need to swap it with 66 in order
to move 43 to it's correct location.
Okay, and so we go ahead and do that.
And now 43 is in it's correct location for
the sorted array, we don't think about it
anymore and we move on to look
at the three remaining elements.
Look for their smallest,
oh, 51 and now we move 51
to it's correct location where it's
going to be once the array is sorted.
And so we have to swap it with 66,
go ahead and do that and now 51 is done
and it's in it's correct location,
we don't need to think about it ever again
and we look at the remaining two elements.
Look for the smallest among those,
that's 66.
Swap it, and
now we're actually done, because for
the last item, while the only reason it's
in the last position is because it wasn't
the first smallest, it wasn't the second
smallest, it wasn't the third smallest.
It's already in it's correct position.
We can't compare it to anything else.
And so when we've got to our last position
in the array, we're actually done.
We don't need to do anything.
Okay and so what that means is that we've
got a algorithm, a series of steps that we
can take algorithmically to perform
this task, so we've got Selection Sort.
Being described here as,
first by the smallest element,
then put in location zero in the array.
Then find the next smallest,
put it in location one, etc.