[MUSIC]
In the previous video, we developed
an algorithm for sorting a bunch of pieces
of data and organizing them in some
order from smallest to biggest.
What we'd like to do in this video
is translate that algorithm, or
high-level description of the strategy,
into Java.
So, what we're going to do is think
step by step about how to go from
natural language descriptions
of the strategy to actual code.
And so let's start by thinking
about what that strategy even was.
And so we talked about Selection Sort.
So Selection Sort has as its
general approach, first of all,
we think about the smallest element
overall in the entire array.
And we look for that smallest element and
we try to put it first.
Because that's where it's going
to need to be at the end.
And then we move on to
the rest of the array and
try to find the smallest element among
those elements and then put it in
the second position overall because
that's its correct location at the end.
And we keep going, and we keep going, etc.
So, let's think about how we
can translate this approach,
the constructs that we
know from programming.
And so, let's start by thinking
about the big picture.
And what we're doing in Selection Sort
is we're looping through all of
the positions in the array and for
each one of those positions, we try to
find the true value in the sorted array.
So, for each position i from the very
beginning of the array all the way
until the end, we are trying to find
the right element to put in that position.
But actually,
not all the way until the end.
Remember from the previous video,
we talked about a small optimization
that once we've sorted the first all but
last elements of the array, then the last
element is going to be in the correct
position because there's really
nowhere else for it to go.
Okay, so we've got that little tweak and
the big picture here, what's important,
is that we've got a for-loop that looks
over each position in the array and
tries to find the right element there.
And, it's also useful to keep in mind,
that as we're going through this
algorithm, we have an invariant property,
a property that never changes.
And that's the, once we've worked on
position zero, position one, position two,
then the elements in those
positions are sorted, and
they're never gonna change, at all.
No matter how many more steps we
have to go or how big the array is.
Those positions are done and
the correct elements in the sorted
array are already there.
And so what we have is this array
where slowly, slowly, slowly, we're
organizing the first bit of it and then
we're focusing on the very next position,
say position i, and looking for
what element to put there.
So, let's think about
the body of the for-loop and
what we need to do in that
body of the for-loop.
And so
a way to think about that is to look for
the smallest element in the not yet
organized piece of the array.
And whatever is the smallest element among
the elements of the array that we
haven't put in their correct position,
that's the one that's going
to need to be in position i.
So we need to find the smallest element
in all of the elements that remain,
and then swap it with the element
that's in position i so
that that element is in
its correct location.
Okay, so let's formalize a little bit what
it means to be in the still unorganized or
unsorted part of the array.
Well, those are all of the elements in
position i through the end of the array,
length- 1.
All right, so
as you can tell we're getting a little
bit closer to coding up the solution.
And what I like you to do now is pause
the video, and try to write the code.
Welcome back.
Let's work through it together, and
see if the code that we developed is
similar to what you did on your own.
So, you probably declared a method that
is going to be called something like
selectionSort, and takes as input the
array of values that we wanted to sort.
Now, in this method,
the way that I've designed it,
were not going to return any values.
So the return is listed as void.
Because what we're going to do is sort
the elements of the array in place.
So we're going to move them around
in the array that we're given.
And now, remember that we have the outer
for-loop and that outer for-loop is
looking at all positions i from the very
beginning until the second last element.
Okay, now for each of those positions
we have to find the correct element to
put in that position.
And so now we have to implement
that piece of the algorithm.
And so what we are going to do is try to
find the smallest element that has not yet
been put in its correct location.
And so we want to keep track of
the index of that smallest element.
The location of where that
smallest element is in the list.
So, at the beginning, we think well,
maybe the smallest element is already
in its correct location in i.
So our first guess is that the smallest
element is in the first place that we look
at, namely position i.
And then we want to step through all
possible positions in that unsorted part
of the array and compare the elements
in those positions with the value of
the element at our current best guess for
where the smallest element is located.
So, we're comparing the element at
position indexMin with the element
at position j.
And if it so happens that the element
at position, j, is smaller
than the element at the position which is
supposed to record the smallest element,
well, we need to update
what we think is going on.
Now, in this case,
we think that the smallest element
is actually in position j.
And now we have to keep on going, and
keep on checking all of the elements to
make sure that indexMin really records
the position of the smallest element
in that remaining piece of the array.
So once we've gone through
this inner for-loop,
what we have is indexMin
recording the position
of the smallest element in
the remaining part of the array.
And then the last piece of our algorithm
is to put that smallest element
in its correct location,
namely, in position i.
And so we might have a helper method
swap that we define somewhere else, and
that's what method looks
at the array vals, and
it swaps the element at position
indexMin with the element at position i.
And so what that would do,
is take the element that supposed to be
in position i, and really put it there.
Okay.
And so, what we've done here is we've
gone from the high level description
of selection sort and we've now gone
ahead and implemented it using Java.
All right, so,
before we leave this algorithm and
say hoo, we've done it, pat on our back,
we can stop thinking about it now.
It's useful to probe further and
always ask ourselves some questions.
How do we know that this algorithm and
this implementation always works,
no matter what array we give it?
And if we believe that it does work,
how well does it work?
And of course, as good engineers and
scientists, we always want
to do better and can we?
So, in the next video we'll talk
about some of these questions.