[MUSIC]
In the previous video,
we implemented selection sorting Java, and
then we stopped and thought about some
questions to do with this algorithm and
how well it performs.
So, so far in this course we haven't
really asked ourselves whether algorithms
are correct and how well they run,
and so let's take a few minutes now to
think about how we might even
formulate answers to these questions.
So let's think about correctness first.
We had a problem that of sorting an array,
meaning organizing
the information in the array.
And then we had a candidate strategy,
selection sort, that we think did
pretty well, and we think that it really
does organize the elements in the array.
But if this was a really mission-critical
problem that we are trying to solve here,
it's not enough for us to just sort of
say hm, yeah, I guess it's gonna work.
Hopefully there won't be any bugs.
All right, we want to be certain and
convinced that our algorithm is really
going to do what it's supposed to do,
no matter what edge case we throw at it or
how big an array we give it.
And so let's think back to the high-level
picture we have of selection sort, and
think about how that
high-level picture can give us
confidence that the algorithm works.
So remember what we're doing in selection
sort is, at each step through the for
loop, we're looking at a new
position in the array and
we're swapping into that position in the
array the element that's going to be there
when the array is really truly sorted.
And so what we have is some initial
piece of the array that is sorted,
and it keeps growing each time.
And so as this sorted part of the array,
the dark gray part of the array, grows
with each iteration of the foreloop, more
and more of our array is in good shape.
It's organized and it's sorted.
And so,
by the time we finish the foreloop and
have gone thought the entire length of the
array, then our entire array is sorted.
And so, this argument that we just went
through can be completely formalized and
can be used to prove
the correctness of selection sort.
Okay, so we're convinced that it works,
but how well does it work?
And what does that even mean?
And so the question of performance
is a really tricky one but
a super critical one.
And it makes the difference
between a very sluggish
computer that no one really ever wants to
use because it takes seconds between when
you click a mouse and when it actually
responds, to a super snappy computer that
everyone is really happy running
apps on and maybe even multitasking.
Because performance we can measure with
time, we can measure with resource use,
and the experience of how an algorithm
runs makes a big difference to
how far we can push that algorithm and how
big a dataset we can expect it to work on.
So it turns out that selection sort,
even though it's correct, doesn't do so
well when we think about its performance.
It turns out to be a very
slow sorting algorithm.
Now we won't talk about
the details of what it means for
one algorithm to be slower than another,
and how we can compare algorithms,
when their performance might depend
on their input in this course.
But we will talk a lot more
about it in the next course.
And so, stay tuned,
it's a beautiful theory of computation and
complexity that we'll get
to in a little while.
Now, what I wanted to mention though,
is that aside from performance issues and
somewhat motivated by performance issues,
we're always on the hunt for
other algorithms for
solving even the same problem.
So we had this sorting problem,
and we had one solution for
it, namely selection sort.
But, even if we did not know that it
was kind of a slow one and maybe not so
great, we'd still be interested in finding
other algorithms that solves sorting.
And that motivation for
finding other algorithms comes from
recognizing that in the real world
different contexts might require
different properties from our algorithms.
Sometimes, we might have
a nearly sorted list,
a list that is usually pretty organized
but occasionally we add on to it.
Maybe as new computers join a network or
as new people join a team.
And so, we might want an algorithm that
responds really well to almost sorted data
and is really fast in that situation.
On the other hand, we might have
a context where our data is going
to be coming from all over the place and
is not organized at all,
but maybe is not going
to change too often.
And so maybe we have a different
algorithm that doesn't respond so
well to dynamically changing data, but
does really well even if the incoming
information is completely unorganized.
So, even if one algorithm is
often slower than the other,
it might still be useful for
other reasons if we know something
about the problem that we're solving and
the real world contact that we live in.
In the next video series,
what we're going to be doing
is thinking about other algorithms for
sorting and foreshadowing
some of the other techniques that we'll
be thinking about in the future courses.