[NOISE] Hi and
welcome back to our module on sorting.
It's time for
another one of these concept challenges.
You've already gotten a good feel for
these and
you know that you're gonna try
to solve the problem yourself,
you're gonna discuss this if you
have other learners around you,
you're gonna watch our UC San Diego
learners talk about the problem, and
then you're gonna see my
explanation of the answer.
So you've already seen
the Selection Sort algorithm.
You know that Selection Sort goes
through every element in the array, and
essentially looks through
the unsorted portion of the array,
finds the smallest value, and adds that
to the, the next smallest value, and
adds that into the array.
So, if I have two arrays,
is sorting faster on one,
or the other, or neither?
Go ahead and think about this and
we'll come back.
>> Hi, I'm Luis.
>> I'm Melissa.
>> I'm Gustavo.
>> Well I think that it would take the
same amount of time because there is one
four loop that iterates
over the entire thing.
>> For me I thought it would be answer
A because why would you have to sort
something that is already sorted?
Wouldn't it take the least
number of steps?
>> Yeah, I thought the same thing.
It's already sorted, but
the computer doesn't know that, so
it has to go to the end.
>> Hi.I hope that you see
San Diego Learner Video is helpful.
What we'll do now is just walk
through both of these arrays and
apply a selection sort to each of them.
So in the first array,
we're gonna do a pass.
We're gonna look at all the elements, and
we're gonna see what
the smallest element is.
And this is going to require us to
look at essentially six elements.
It's gonna require us to look at all six,
and we're gonna find that
seven's the smallest one,
and we'll put 7 in the very first slot,
which is where it is already.
In the next iteration in the array,
we're gonna look at the second
element in the array.
And we're gonna see,
what's the smallest element.
We're now gonna scan,
we're gonna look at all five of these, and
we're gonna find that 16 is it smallest,
and keep it there.
When we move to the next element in
the array, we're gonna scan the remaining.
So I'm gonna have to look at
all four elements here to find
that 43 is in fact the smallest and
then I'll swap them.
So 43 now moves into
the place that 66 was at.
And we'll move to the next element
in the array, and I'm gonna look
at this element along with the remaining
elements, to find the smallest element.
And it's gonna take me 3 steps
to find 51 is the smallest, and
then I'm gonna swap 51 and 66.
In the next iteration of the array
I'm now gonna be looking at 97,
I'm gonna have to look at 97 to 51 and
66, to find out that 66 is the smallest.
That takes 2 steps.
And now I'm gonna swap 66 97.
And then the last of the array,
I'm going to look at 97 to see if it
is the smallest element of the array.
It is, and we're done.
That did seem like it took number of
steps because I was having to swap so
many elements, but what's going
to happen with assorted array?
Is it going to behave that differently?
Well, with the assorted array,
it's going to start at seven, and
it's going to see is seven
the smallest element.
And it's going to look at
all six elements again.
It's then going to move onto 16,
it's going to find the smallest element.
It's going to have to look
at five elements to do that.
It's then gonna look at 43 and it's gonna
say is 43 the smallest, and it's gonna
have to look at all the remaining elements
to find that 43 is, in fact, the smallest.
It's gonna move to 51, do the same thing.
It's gonna take three steps,
it's gonna move to 66, take two steps.
It's gonna move to 97 and take one step.
So we haven't done as much swapping, but
we've essentially taken as many steps.
What this really leads us now to thinking
about is, how do we define faster?
So we can see that both of these arrays
essentially took the same number of steps.
Is that how we define faster?
Well, If you're looking at a high level,
the same number of steps means they
essentially take the same amount of time.
Now some of you may be thinking,
well wait a second, I think if you look at
the really nitty gritty details, you can
see that swapping only sometimes happens,
or maybe this if statement only executes
sometimes, and it doesn't execute other
times, and now you're starting to argue
about individual machine instructions.
But what view do we want to have?
Well, for the most part we tend to have
a really high level view when we look at
algorithms to say whether or
not one is faster than the other.
In this case, we actually say that
theses are gonna run the same speed
regardless of the contents of the array.
But, we're gonna spend a whole bunch more
time in the next module talking about
defining performance, defining how
to compare different algorithms, and
we're looking forward to
doing that with you then.