[MUSIC]
>> So in the previous video we
talked about selection sort which is
one algorithm for sorting data.
By the end of this video, you'll have
seen another algorithm for sorting data.
And we're going to play a little game.
Instead of talking with
the algorithm at a high level,
what we're going to do
is present some code.
That I promise you will sort the data,
but what I'd like to do is work with you
to figure out how to describe
that code in high-level terms.
And this are really useful skill that
helps with reverse engineering code and
also working in big teams,
when other people are implementing
different pieces of the code.
And so then, once we'll have traced
the code and figured out what it does.
We'll be able to describe alternate
algorithms for sorting and
compare their relative merits.
So let's start with a code, and
let's see what we have here.
So we're gonna call this method
mysterySort until we solve
the mystery together.
And at this point there aren't
a lot of comments to help guide us,
we're just seeing some Java statements and
so
let's see what we've got here and we'll
step through with a particular example.
So we see that we've got
a variable being declared and
we've got a for loop that does something
and has an inner while loop, okay.
Doesn't help us so much so far,
but let's work through an example.
And again, it's really useful to
work through some concrete examples
when we're working through these questions
to help guide our understanding.
And then later, we wana generalize.
We wanna think about the full generality.
But first,
let's make sure that we understand
what's happening at a small scale.
Okay, so
we're working with the array of integers
that we talked about last video as well.
So we've got six elements and
we're going to trace through and
step through the execution of our
mystery method to see what happens.
Okay, so at the beginning in our for loop,
we are initializing the value pos to one.
And what's going to happen the first
time we run through this for
loop is that currInd.
Which you might guess means current index,
is going to be initialized
to the same values position.
And so what we see on the left of the code
here, is that we've got a memory model.
So think way back to the earlier module,
one of the first modules that we did in
this course where we talked about
using memory models to help us reason
through the change in values of
variables as we run through code.
And so we've got boxes for each variables
and at the beginning each of those
contains the values of the initial
values of the variables namely, one.
Okay, now what happens is,
we look into the condition for
the while loop and we see, do we have
to execute the body of the while loop?
While we're checking whether the current
index is greater than zero, so yes,
it's 1.
And we wanna check whether the array
element at position currIndex
is less than the array element
at position currIndex-1.
So, currIndex is 1,
currIndex minus 1 is 0.
So we're comparing the numbers 7 and
16, and
we're checking whether 16 is less than 7?
It's not, and so we don't need to
execute the body of the while loop.
We go right back up to the top of the for
loop, after incrementing the pos
variable or position variable.
Okay, so now position is two and
the currIndex is initialized at the top
of the body of the for loop to be two.
And again, we have to check the condition
for the while loop and we look,
is the current index positive?
Yes, okay and now we wanna compare
the value of the array element at position
2 and compare that to the value of
the array element at position 1.
And basically look at
what's happening here,
we're asking whether they're in the
correct relative position to one another.
We're asking whether 66 is less than 16?
Or 16 is less than 66?
And in the array as it stands right now,
16 and
66 are the correct relative positions,
so we don't need to do anything.
All right, so
far we haven't done much except for
updating our helper variables, pos and
currInd and we do that once more.
Okay, we step up to the next execution
of the body of the for loop and so
now the pos variable has value of 3 and
the current index has the same value
of that at that the beginning.
And now we check whether
the array element at 43,
i'm sorry at position 3
which is 43 is less than
the array element at position 2,
which is 66 and it is.
So 43 is less than 66, which means that
these two array elements are out of order.
They need to be swapped in order
to be in the correct location
relative to one another.
And so that's what's happening
in the body of the while loop,
we're swapping these two positions.
And we also need to update
the current index variable.
Okay, so we've swapped the two positions,
now we have 43 in position 2.
We have 66 in position 3, and
the current index is two.
And we go back to the top of the while
loop and we check whether 16 and
43 are in the correct relative positions?
They are, so
we don't need to do a thing in this
execution of the body of the for loop.
We increment, pos.
We update currInd, and we go again and
now we're checking whether 66 and
97 are in the correct relative position?
They are, awesome, keep going,
update pos, update currIndex.
And we check whether 97 and 51,
the elements at position 4 and
5 are in the correct relative position and
they're not.
97 is greater than 51, and so what we
need to do is we need to swap them.
We update the current index,
and now we check again.
And what we're checking is whether 66 and
51 are in the correct relative positions?
They're not, so we need to swap them and
update current index.
Okay current index is now three, 51 and
66 are in the correct relative positions.
And now we check whether 43 and
51 are in the correct relative positions?
And they are, so sweet, we're done.
Okay, so what that means is, at each
point of the execution of the for loop.
At each time we've gone through the for
loop, what we know is that we've
guaranteed that an increasing part of
the array is going to be in sorted order.
So, if you think about what happens and
what the array looks like at the end of
the body of the for
loop when pos equals one.
What we have here is that 7 and
16 are in their correct final locations.
Okay, at the end of position 2, we have 7,
16, and 66 at the head of our array.
Now these are not going to be the correct
final locations of each of these elements.
At the end when we finish
sorting the array,
66 is not gonna be in that third position.
But, what we do know, is that the first
three elements of the array at this point.
Are in the correct relative order,
with respect to one another.
And so what we're doing is we're
growing an array that is sorted,
even though there might need to
be some elements that get put in,
into that array later on as we go
through the rest of the algorithm.
Okay, so at the end of position,
at the end of the for
loop when we've got position equals 3.
What we have is, that we have a list of
four elements of incorrect sorted order,
then we have two elements that
we haven't worried about yet.
And they may need to go somewhere and
nudge some of these sorted elements
around, but these four elements will never
switch position relative to one another.
Okay.
So, what we have here is.
A beginning of a description in higher
level terms of what this code is doing.
And this transition between looking
at code and being able to trace it's
execution one step at a time, to being
able to describe it in higher level terms
is a really really hard cognitive leap but
that is really important.
And so it takes practice, keep at it.
Work on it and
you can see you'll get much better at it.
And the one of the key strategies for
doing it is tot take it
little pieces at a time.
Okay, and so what we're thinking about
is we're thinking about this for loop.
Where we're growing a piece of the array
that is in relative sorted order.
So it's sorted, and even though
the elements in this part of the array
may not be in the correct final location.
Which is different from what we saw
in the previous video by the way,
they are still always going to be in
the same relative order to one another.
And then we're increasing the amount of
the array that is in this relative sorted
order each time.
Okay, and so what's happening here is,
in order to increase
the piece of the array that's sorted each
time within the body of the for loop.
We're finding the correct location
of the next element that we haven't
thought about up until now relative
to the first i-1 elements.
And so then we want to nudge it into the
sorted part of the array, nudge, nudge,
nudge, nudge, nudge,
until it gets into its correct
relative location, leave it there.
And then all of a sudden we have a nice,
bigger part of the array that
is sorted and we can go look at the next
element that we haven't looked at yet.
So this is actually a well
known sorting algorithm.
It's a mystery no longer.
It's called Insertion Sort and
that's because we keep inserting new
elements into a previously sorted array,
into the correct position
relative to the other elements and
then this sorted part grows and grows.
All right, notice that this
algorithm is quite different from
the previous algorithm
that we talked about,
the selection sort algorithm that we
talked about in the previous video.
And that's because in the insertion
sort algorithm, we have the elements
that were taken care of,
they get taken care of in a different way.
We don't immediately put them
where they're going to be.
And they stay in that
position forever after, and
we know their location in the complete
array from that point on.
Rather, we're looking at relative
locations and relative ordering and so
we have two different algorithms.
But they share some features and so
with each algorithm, as we go through it.
We ask similar questions about
correctness, and performance, and
similarly we would want to compare that
selection sort algorithm to the insertion
sort algorithms and
other algorithms as well as they come.
So, with insertion sort, the mystery sort
that we were working through just now,
how do we know that it's correct?
Well, the argument that we were making
before about the part of the array that is
in relative sorted order,
growing and growing and growing until we
get to all of the elements in the array.
Well, if we were able
to make that precise,
that would be a convincing argument
that this algorithm is correct.
Because no matter what we start with,
at the end we get
all of the elements in the array in
sorted order and that's what we want.
So then theres the question
of can we do better?
And when it comes to algorithms,
we always want to do better but
what is that even mean?
And so the question of goodness of
an algorithm has a few levels to it and
has a lot of complexity to it.
So the baseline, lowest bar of
goodness that we want is that
algorithm does what it's supposed to,
that it's correct.
Okay, both selection sort and
insertion sort have met that bar.
But then, we might want more.
So for example, we want to be able
to tackle huge reams of data and so
we might want our algorithms
to be really fast.
And so
we want to be able to process billions and
trillions of pieces of information,
very efficiently.
And so we need to think about, how do
we measure the speed of an algorithm?
How do we talk about its performance
in terms of time in general?
When we don't a priori know
what our data looks like.
We wanted to be good for
all sorts of pieces of data.
And so, that will lead us to things
like worst case analysis and asymptotic
analysis that you'll see lots more about
in the next course of this specialization.
I want to also mention that there
are other measures of goodness
of an algorithm.
For example, we might not want
to waste a lot of memory while
performing the execution of an algorithm.
And so, we might want you to
be very resource sensitive and
not use up a lot of space.
And so, there's a notion of space
complexity that we would want to
think about as well.
And then we also might want to think about
other properties that the algorithm
could preserve or not preserve.
So for example, if we want to
sort a lot of data on dimensions.
So you can think back about
the airport data, we want to sort.
First by name of country,
and then by name of city.
Then we would want our
algorithm to behave in a way
that's compatible with doing
multiple task sorting.
And so we might want to restrict
which algorithms we consider,
based on only those that have
properties amenable to our use case.
So goodness and can we do better?
Are always relative questions, relative
to how we plan to use the algorithms.
Algorithms are actual living,
breathing objects you can think about.
And they don't exist in a vacuum,
we want to use them and the measure of
their goodness is only in terms of how we
can use them and what they can tell us.