[MUSIC]
In the previous two videos, we've seen two
different algorithms for sorting data.
Now, that's just the beginning,
the tip of the iceberg.
There are many, many,
many algorithms for sorting.
We're not gonna cover all of them.
What you do want to keep in mind is that
it's possible to optimize these algorithms
tremendously depending on the application.
And that takes a lot of work, but
if you actually just want to use sorting,
you don't need to write
the sorting algorithm yourself.
So by the end of this video you'll be
able to use the predefined Java method to
sort and you'll be able to explain
the properties of this built in method.
Because whenever we use a tool we wanna be
able to know both it's functionality and
it's limitations.
So it's useful to be aware of what
the built in method is actually doing.
As a reminder, we've talked both about
selection sort and insertion sort.
We talked about why each of these give
correct algorithms for sorting data.
And we also talked bout some potential
limitations in terms of the time that it
would take for the sorting algorithms
to actually work through a lot of data.
And we've talked about how to
write the code for these for
these sorting algorithms.
But we don't want to write
that code each time, and
so here's this code snippet of how we
might be able to sort some data as
part of a larger method without
actually writing the sorting ourselves.
We do need to use some built
in utilities from Java.
And so that's why the import
method is up top there.
And then once we build a list of, for
example, integers, then all we need to do
is call the sort method, collections.sort,
on that list of integers.
And then low and behold if you run this,
you'll see that our numbers are sorted.
And so it's this one line method
that is kind of a cheat because we
haven't actually implemented sort method.
But if what we're focused on
in the particular method that
we're writing is not the sort, but that's
just sort of a helper piece of our code.
Then it's useful to go to the library and
pick out that built-in method and
use that instead of having
to implement it each time.
The reason it's useful,
is that we get the benefit of
a lot of other people's hard work.
Turns out that in this built in method
what's being implemented, is an algorithm
called merge sort, that's then been
tweaked and optimized for various reasons.
In particular it's been
made to be super fast, and
we'll talk again in the next course about
what we mean by a fast algorithm and
how we can compare algorithm
speeds to one another.
But merge sort is known to be provably
faster than selection sort and
insertion sort in most
cases that we care about.
And in particular it's really good for
nearly sorted data.
If you think back to selection sort and
insertion sort, trace through how
those algorithms would behave if
our data was already almost sorted.
And what you'll see is that one of
them does better than the other in
responding dynamically to the kind
of data that's being presented.
And so it's really useful if we know that
we're going to maintain, for example,
our list of airports.
And every so often a new airport
is going to come up, and
we wanna add it to the list, and
then re-sort the list to make sure
that it's in the correct location.
We want our algorithm to be able to be
responsive to that, and be fast when our
data is almost sorted, and we just maybe
have a couple of things out of place.
The optimized merge sort that is also
built into Java has an additional property
in that it's stable so that means that if
we run sort a bunch of times on the same
data and we have a couple of pieces of
data that are duplicates in some sense,
they won't switch orders.
As we run sort again and again and again.
And that could be useful if we want to,
for example,
sort the data on different dimensions.
So, what you'll see is in the project
you'll be using some sorting and
searching techniques.
But what we encourage you to do
is to use the built-in sort and
not have to rewrite sort on your own so
that you can make use of these
great properties that
the optimizations have given us.