[MUSIC]
In the previous video, we started talking
about how to use the built-in sort that's
available to us in Java.
What I'd like to do now is to think about
how to generalize that technique for
more complicated objects.
So by the end of this video,
you will be able to define and
use the Comparable interface in Java.
So that we can have access to
that built-in sort method.
So if you remember last time,
what we talked about is how to
use collections.sort and
then feed in a list of integers, and
somehow magically get the list
returned to us as a sorted list.
Now, what we did in, or what we observed
happens when we used this method
is that we're using
the Built in Merge Sort.
And the beauty of that was that we didn't
have to implement merge sort ourselves.
The issue, though, is that the list
that we gave it was an integer list, so
all the values are numbers.
But sometimes the objects
that we want to sort,
the data that we want to
organize isn't just numbers.
Maybe it's more complicated objects, and
so what we'd like to do now is think about
using this built in functionality but
for collections of non integers.
And so for example,
we might want to sort airports.
So remember back to
the beginning of the module and
the motivating example that
we've been talking about.
We have an array of airports and
each of those, each of the array elements
are references to airport objects.
And what we'd like to do is sort this
array based on the city of the airport.
Okay?
So if we try to just go ahead and,
in our airport class,
define a method within the main method
that just says, let's sort our airports.
So we have an airports list and
we're gonna go ahead and
sort it, then we can hope for
the best and try to compile this.
But unfortunately,
we're gonna get a big old error message.
And the reason for that error message is
that airports are kind of hard to sort.
We don't know how to compare two airports.
So this is where the comparable
interface comes in.
And the comparable interface says,
I will be able to give you access
to merge sort and all of these other built
in functionalities like sorting in Java,
if you only tell me how to compare
two object instances of your class.
And so, for example, if we think about
the object that has the city Montreal, and
Canada, with a particular airport code,
and the airport object that we have that's
initialized to the airport in Lagos,
then we might want to compare these two.
And say, M comes after L in the alphabet,
and so when we're
thinking about the city names than the
object that corresponds to the airport in
Montreal should come after the object
that corresponds to the airport in Lagos.
On the other hand, we might want to
organize our data based on country names,
rather than city names.
And so then,
we might focus in on a different field.
And look at the instance variable for
country.
And in that case we see that Canada,
starting with a C, comes earlier in the
alphabet than Nigeria, starting with an N.
And so we'd want our objects to be
organized a little bit differently.
All right, so how do we do that,
and how do we tell Java this order?
Well, if our class implements
the comparable interface.
And we say that by adding that
keyword to the class definition.
Then our objects in that class will be
able to be compared to one another.
Now notice that special word
that's after comparable.
We've got the angle brackets and Airport.
And that's saying that we're specifying
what kind of objects we're going to
know how to compare, and
this is using generics.
Okay, so if we've told Java,
we promised that we're going to implement
what's needed for a comparable class.
What that's saying is that we have to
fulfill the promise of the interface.
And the interface comparable says,
you must implement a compareTo method.
And the compareTo method has to be
called by an object in that class.
And it's going to tell us how
to compare that calling object
to an input other object.
Okay.
So let's think about how we might do that.
And think about what
functionality we want.
So we're going to return an integer,
and that integer should
demonstrate the relationship between
the calling object and the other object.
So if the calling object is supposed
to be smaller than the other object,
then the integer that
we return is negative.
If the smaller object, if the calling
object is supposed to be sort of the same
size as the other object,
then we should return zero.
And if the calling object is
bigger than the other object,
then we're going to
return a positive number.
And so what you might think about is
the comparison method is something like
doing subtraction, subtracting
the calling object minus other object.
That's sort of the reference
that we have for
why these integers
are returned the way they are.
Okay, so what we'd like to
do is to return some number.
When an airport calls
compared to another airport.
And what we're comparing
to is using the city name.
So we're going to have to have access
to the city name instance variables
in each of these objects and
we'd like to order those city names.
But city names are just strings,
and strings are objects, and
strings can be compared because we can
sort strings by alphabetical order.
And so what we're going to do is
really just be kind of lazy, and
say someone else compare
these two strings.
And we just want to return
the result of that comparison.
So what we're returning here when
we comparing two airport objects,
is what happens when we compare
the city name of our current object,
the calling object, as compared to
the city name of the other object.
Okay, so let's try it out.
Once we've implemented this compareTo
method, what happens when we
go ahead and
try to sort a list of airport objects?
So we go back to the main method
of our airports class and
we call Collections.sort
on the list of airports.
And now, beautifully, we get as our output
the list of airports in sorted
order based on the city name.
So Agra in India comes first, and
then Beijing in China, etc., etc.
Cool.
One more thing,
when we first thought about this problem,
we said we can compare airports
in some different ways.
Maybe we can sort based on
the alphabetical order of the city name.
But what about the country name.
So what do we need to do in order
to change our compareTo method
in order to reflect the order
of the country names?
Well we just need to change the body
of that method to instead of using
the getCountry getter method for the,
sorry, instead of using the getCity
getter method for the city name of
the airport, we're using getCountry.
And that's really all there is to it.
We just need to change that one line
of code, and when we run the same
Collections.sort method in the main
method of the airport class,
all of sudden our list is ordered
based on the country names.
We have Australia first, and
then Canada, and then China etc.
And so at this point, you're ready to
dive back into the project and use
the comparable interface and the compareTo
method to compare markers in your project.