Hi again and
welcome back to our module on sorting.
At this point, you've seen two
different sorting techniques, so
we're gonna see how well do you
really understand both of them.
You're very familiar with the concept
challenges at this point.
You know the approach is you're gonna
pause, think about the questions,
answer it yourself, discuss it with
people if you have them around you.
Watch a video of UCSD, UC San Diego
learners, learning about the material, and
then confirm your explanation
with our explanation.
So without further ado,
if you look at these two arrays,
in the top array we have the initial
setup, and in the array below
that we've got the state of the array
after three loop iterations.
Which sorting algorithm could've
been applied to reach this state.
>> Hi, I'm Melissa.
>> Hi, I'm Ken.
>> Hi, I'm Michael.
>> So for this one, I thought it
definitely can't be selection sort because
the one would be at the beginning, right?
>> I was actually kinda confused on this
question because I actually picked D.
I thought it was both of them since like
the first couple of elements are already
sorted and we're sorting the elements,
shouldn't that be correct for both?
>> I'm actually pretty sure it's insertion
sort because what happens is through
the first iterations or the first loop, it
checks the four and the seven, no switch.
Goes to the next two elements, seven and
two, switches the seven and two.
>> Okay.
>> And then actually goes back and
checks the two and the four, the four and
the two, and makes that switch.
And that would be three loop iterations,
and
that would be exactly
what the bottom array is.
And what she said,
it can't be selection sort,
because the one would be at
the beginning for selection sort.
>> Oh, right.
>> Insertion sort never
made it to the one.
>> To reach this state.
Hi, I hope this video with
the UC San Diego learners was helpful.
We're going to just walkthrough both
insertion sort and selection sort, and
see the state of the array
after three loop iterations.
With insertion sort, the key idea here
is that you always keep the left side of
the array sorted, but you're only looking
at essentially, the left elements.
So the first pass, all you're gonna
do is look at element four and say,
is four sorted?
It sure is.
Next iterational loop
is gonna look at seven,
and it's gonna say where should
seven be in relation to four.
Well, it belongs in the same place.
So the third iterational loop is where
it gets interesting because it's gonna
look at two.
I was gonna say, where does two
belong relative to four and seven?
And it's gonna move two down all
the way to the first place, and
then four and then seven.
So after three iterations of the loop,
this would be the state of insertion sort.
And this is what
the question was asking for.
So the right answer
here is insertion sort.
But let's talk through what
selection sort would have done.
Selection Sort is always gonna be looking
to the remaining part of the array to find
the smallest value and
put that where we're currently looking.
So a selection sort, you're gonna be
looking to the entire array at the start
and you're gonna look to see that
one is the smallest element and
then you place one right at the start.
And you're gonna look through
the remaining part of the array, and
you're gonna find that two is
the next smallest element,
you're gonna place that next.
And then you're gonna look through
the main part of the array again.
You're gonna find that four
is the next smallest element.
You're gonna swap that in.
And this will be the state of the array
after three durations
of selection sorting.