[MUSIC]
So the programming assignment for
the module you get to do something that,
I think, is really fun.
And that's called Markov Text Generation.
This video is really about giving
you the background that you need.
Just a little bit on Markov processes and
how Markov processes can
be used to generate text.
So let's think about all sorts of examples
that we have in our interaction with
technology where somehow the technology is
magically able to predict what we want.
And so thinking about even typing
a search string into Google,
I can start with the word song and
all of a sudden the suggestion comes
up underneath that says song lyrics.
How did google know I wanted lyrics?
Well there's a lot of really cool
technology that goes on under the hood.
We won't be able to get into the details
of what exactly happens at Google but
what I'd like to show you is
one model of predicting what's
going to come next based on training
data that we may have accumulated.
And then, this is not what's
used in practice at Google, but
it will give you a taste of how
you might start and then tune and
make more sophisticated after the fact.
So what we'd like to
think about is how we can
predict what's going to come next
based on the information that we have.
And so what we're going to do is
abstract the information that we have
as the current state of
the system that we might be in.
And so the basic principle of a Markov
process is that we should be able to
predict or have a probability distribution
on the next possible outcomes,
just based on knowledge
of our current situation.
And so we try to encode everything
that's going to be relevant
to guessing what's going to happen
next in this notion of state.
And then what we'll do is assign
probabilities to what's going to happen
next, which state will have to transition
to based on our current state.
All right, so let's think about
an example of what that might mean.
Let's think about a song that I really
like by the Beatles called Hello, Goodbye.
And if you know this song, you'll notice
that there's a lot of repeated phrases and
it goes back and forth.
There's some duality there.
And so, we might try to generate
additional verses of the song,
if you really like it.
And the Beatles aren't recording any more,
you might want more of it.
And so you might want to think about
what patterns show up in this song.
And so you might notice that after
The Beatles say you then they say, say.
And you might generate something.
And so
I did a little bit on the back end and
I'll show you the machinery in a minute.
But I generated a couple more
sentences of the lyrics.
Now, notice that these sentences
don't exactly match the song, but
they have a bit of the same flavor.
So, you say hello.
I don't know why you say hello, hello.
I saw goodbye, oh no.
You say no.
And, so you notice that there's
some similar patterns to it, but
it's not quite the same,
it's not copying the text
from what we started with,
from the Beatles' song lyrics to begin.
And so let me show you how I would've
created those couple of new sentences.
What we want to do is try to capture what
pairs of words typically go together, and
what next word I can expect based
on the current word I have.
So in this model for this particular song,
my state is going to be
the current word in the lyric.
And so what I'm going to do is predict
what the next word is going to be,
based on the current word.
So for example,
I can go through the entire song and
see that every time the word you,
with a capital Y, shows up in the lyrics.
A capital Y is important because it's
at the beginning of the sentence.
Then every single time that happens,
the word say follows.
And so in my model,
I wanna mimic that behavior, that pattern.
And so I'm going to represent that
with having a node for You and
then always transitioning or having an
arrow to the next word or the next state,
which is the node for the word say.
So how that pans out in the predicted
text is that every time my model
predicts that there is going to be a You,
immediately afterwards you'll see a say.
And that shows up in both times that I
have a You at the beginning of a sentence.
All right, but other words aren't
always followed by the same one.
So for example, if I have hello at the end
of a sentence, looking through it what
the Beatles wrote, about a half the time
the next sentence started with I.
And a sixth of the time the next
sentence started with why.
About a third of the time,
the next sentence started with you.
And so what I would like to do is, for
the model that I create that's
based on this song, to mimic that.
So, you'll see that the frequencies in
the short snippet that be have here,
also mimic those relative frequencies.
And if we generated more text, then you'd
see those frequencies coming up as well.
All right, so
what's the point of all of this?
What I'd really like you to
get away from this video is
that when we have a whole bunch of data,
what we'd like to do is use that data
to inform the model that we build.
And so we're gonna build a model,
in this case, each node, or
each state in our model is a word.
And what we'd like to do is fill in the
probabilities of transitioning from one
word to the next, and those probabilities
are going to be based on the frequencies
that we see those pairs of words
in our data set, our training set.
Once we have our model built,
then what we can do is generate and
use our model to predict the next text.
And so we could start with
some node in our model, and
then just keep on randomly selecting
what the next word is going to be based
on the probabilities that we've determined
for what those next words might be.
And so in the next video, what we'll
be doing is talking a little bit about
the implementation details
of doing this in Java so
you'll be all ready for your project.