[MUSIC]
So, in the previous video, we talked
about this concept of using Markov
processes to generate random text
after we train on some data set.
And so, now we're going to dive into
the implementation of this idea.
So by the end of this video, you'll
be able to describe the class design
of the Java classes that we're going
to be using, both in the video and
in your project,
to create a Markov text generator.
And then you'll also be able to implement
some of the code that's needed for
the project.
So let's think back to what we said.
So at the beginning, we're going to build
a model of the patterns that are implicit
in the data that we want to
emulate by training on that data.
And the model that we're building
will have these estates that
represent the current
situation that we're in.
And then transitions between those
states to say how to go forward and
how to generate more and more text.
And then once we've built our model,
we're ready to go into that second stage
of the process and
actually generate some text.
So let's focus the class design first.
So remember that when we talk about class
design we have the notion of interfaces.
And with the interfaces we can
specify what's the desired behavior of
our classes without going into
the details of the implementation.
So when we have a MarkovTextGenerator
what we want it to be able to do is
train on some input data or string.
And then we also wanted to
be able to generate text,
perhaps a certain amount of text,
and so we want to be able to give it
an integer which says the number
of words we want to generate.
Now just to make our
objects more useable and
more flexible, we're also going to
add the functionality of retraining.
So we want to be able to
train on some data and
then maybe generate some text based
on that model, then throw it away and
then retrain on new data
generate more text etc.
So that’s going to be the interface and
these are the methods that we’re
specifying in this interface.
So, if we want to go ahead and implement
that interface we need to define a class
that’s going to implement
each one of these methods.
And let’s focus on
the training piece first.
So, when we train on data,
what we're training on is an input string.
And we're going to go back to the example
from last time where we have that
Beatles song, Hello, Goodbye.
And so we want to think about our
model capturing the quirks and
patterns in that body of text.
So that when we generate new text,
we're going to emulate those quirks and
patterns as well.
So for each new word, what we need
to do is keep track of the current
word that we're looking at and then
what words might follow after that word.
Because our model is going to predict what
next word to generate based on the current
state which we are going to
think of as the current word.
And so what were looking for are likely
consecutive pairs of words, and so
as we process the input string that
we are looking at that's our training
set what we are trying to track is
which words come after other words so
that we can mimic that later.
So, in order to put that into our class
design, our concrete class that implements
the interface MarkovTextGenerator
is going to have a list.
And we're going to use a generic to say,
well, what kind of lists,
what objects are stored in this list.
Well, each object that stored
in this list is a word node.
It's going to be something
that captures what
the information that's contained
in a word ought to be.
And so when we look at a specific word,
what we care about is
what are the possible next
moves after we see that word.
And so we're going to define another
class called WordNode that keeps track of
the value of the word that we're
thinking about, the current word.
And so that's our private String word.
And then it is going to keep a list of the
possible next words that come after it.
Now from a WordNode we
might want some methods.
We might want to get the value
of the current word.
We might need to add a possible next
word as we're training on the data.
If we come across this word again, and
we wanna add a new word to
the collection of possible next moves.
And then when we actually generate text
afterwards, we're going to need it to get
a random next word based on the current
location we are in our state model.
And we'll come back to how we use
that method in a little bit, but
basically what we're doing when we're
training on data is we're going through
the array or
list of words that we have, and
for each one of those words that
we're looking at in our training set.
We have to decide wether we want to create
a new WordNode object that is going to
basically be a state in our model.
So let's get a bit of
a sense of how we do that.
And so
when we start at the very beginning,
we've never seen the word you before,
because this is the very beginning and so
you have to create a new WordNode
object with the value for the word you.
And then we look at what word comes
immediately after you at this point in
the input data set, and
we say that say comes next.
And so the next words list for this
particular instance of the object, for
this particular object
at least contain say.
It's got to have that as
a possible next word to you.
Now we come to the next word in our
training set and it's a word that we
haven't seen before, so we have to create
a new instance of the word node class.
That instance is going to have
the instance variable word
set to the value say and it's possible
next words is going to contain yes.
And so on and so
forth as we go through this list.
And now the first interesting
thing happens when we get to
the second time that we see the word say.
So in the song it goes,
you say yes, I say no.
And so
the second time we see the word say,
we don't want to create a new object that
has the same value for the word in it.
Because what we're trying to do
with this model is keep track of
the distinct possible words that
we might have in our data set, and
for each one of those,
what are all possible next words.
And so what we'd like to do is update the
object that we already created whose value
for the variable word was say, and we want
to add a new possible next word to it.
Now say is followed by the word no.
All right and so that's what we did
with the object whose value for
the variable word was say.
All right.
So we keep on going and
we keep on going, but
remember that our model actually had
this notion of probabilities, right?
When we were thinking
about the Markov model,
what we had was each word defined as
state and then we had probabilities.
On the transitions for how likely was it
each of the possible next words
was actually going to be given?
So, if we have the word hello
at the end of a sentence, so
hello with a period, half the time, we
a re going to have the word I afterwards,
but a sixth of the time,
we are going to have the word why, or
a third of the time we are going
to have the word you afterwards.
And it's not clear that we've captured
that in our algorithm, so far,
of training through the data and just
adding words to the list of next words.
But let's think about what we've done.
And in particular,
let's see what happens to the object
who's word points to the word hello.
So, the first time we encounter
hello in our song, and
you can go through the lyrics and
see, it's followed by I.
And so the list nextWords gets the value,
or gets I put into it.
And then the next time I comes again.
And notice that we just insert a second
copy of the string I into this list.
Okay?
Next time we insert why, and
next time we insert I again, and
then you, and
then the next time will be a you as well.
And so as we're training on the data set,
what we're doing is we're
concerned about whether the current word
that we're looking at is new or not.
And every time we've got a new word,
then we add a new object.
But then when we look up what the next
word is, we don't care if we've seen it
before, we always just stick
it into the list of nextWords.
And that's gonna be really important,
because then when we go ahead and
generate text, what we're going to do, is
when we generate the next random word for
a particular word, we're just
going to pick randomly, uniformly,
between all of the words
in our next word's list.
And that's gonna do exactly what we
need in terms of the probabilities
because the probability of picking
I from a list of six elements,
three of which are I is
exactly three out of six.
If we pick each one of those elements with
equal probability, and so what we've done
is we've stacked the list of next words so
that the distribution of probabilities for
each distinct word matches
exactly what we need.
And so that simple algorithm
that we talked about where,
when we process each word we just stick
the next word into the list of next words,
not caring if we've seen it before or
not, does exactly the right thing for
generating the next words with
the correct probabilities.
So now let's talk about how we would
Implement this algorithm at a high level,
so we want to think about
how we generate words
using the model that we've already built.
So we have at our disposal
a list of word nodes.
And now what we'd like to do is use that
list of word nodes to generate some text.
And so until we have enough words,
because remember we've got
that integer argument that tells us how
many words we're supposed to produce,
what we're going to do is look for
the current word that we're currently at
through the list of word
notes that we have.
We're going to look for which word
note has that word as its value,
and in that node, we're going to
generate a random number between 0 and
the number of words in
that list of nextWords.
And we can generate random numbers in
Java because we have this great package
called random.
And so
we just pick a random number between 0 and
the size of the list, minus 1.
And just pick the next word whose
index is that number, and so each of
the possible next words in that list will
have equal probability of being picked.
And because we've stacked the list,
then we'll get the right
distribution that we want.
And so
we'll just print the word at that index.
We update what the currentWord is and
we look for the currentWord node, and
we just keep on going and keep on going.
And now you're ready to
begin your project and
implement this high
level algorithm in Java.
So enjoy the class design,
enjoy generating some really cool text.
And play around with what starter
text you want to train on,
what training data sets you'll have.
And you'll notice that this
can be a little bit absorbing.
Hours of fun can be had.