[MUSIC]
Okay, the last lesson in this module
is talking about variable scope.
Now you may be already familiar with
the notion of variable scope, but
we're gonna introduce it again because
it's such an important concept.
And we're gonna do more than just
introduce the notion of variable scope,
we're gonna also incorporate it
into those memory models for
reasoning about Java code.
So by the end of this module, you'll be
able to describe the notion of scope and
Java's rules for scope as well as draw
those memory models to incorporate scope
and reason about code
using those memory models.
So get out your pencil.
Get out your piece of paper.
Make sure you're not driving and
you'll draw these memory
models right along with us.
So, we're starting off with
a little warm up question.
I want you to look at this code.
And, this code should look
pretty familiar to you by now.
And I want you to identify the six
variables that appear in this code.
So, pause the video for
a second and see if you can find
six variables in this code.
All right.
Welcome back.
Hopefully you found six variables,
if you didn't don't worry about it.
Here's the six variables
that I found in this code.
Now, you may have also identified
that keyword, this, as a variable.
It's not quite a variable,
it behaves a little bit like a variable.
We'll talk more bout that later as we
add in scope into our memory models.
But here are those six variables.
There's latitude and longitude,
which are the member variables
in our SimpleLocation class.
There's latIn and lonIn,
which are the parameters to our method,
to our constructor.
And then over in our main method, there's
lima, which is our simple location object.
And then that tricky one, which is
the parameter to the main method args.
So all of these variables are not
necessarily created equal.
So even though latitude is
a variable in this code, if I try to
refer to latitude over here in the main
method, what do you think's gonna happen?
So take a minute, take a guess,
what happens if I just try to
directly access the variable
latitude in the main method?
So if you tried this, you will have
found that it caused an error.
If you try to access latitude in
this location, in this main method,
Java is gonna tell you that this
variable latitude is not defined here.
So this brings us to the idea of scope.
The scope of a variable is
the area in the code where
it's defined to have a particular value.
And in this case, in the main method, that
variable latitude is not defined at all.
It hasn't been declared here.
It was declared over in
the SimpleLocation class.
It was one of the member variables.
So I can't get at it in main.
So let's talk about a few
different types of variables and
types of scoping rules for
those variables.
So the first kind of variable we're going
to talk about is called a local variable.
A local variable is a variable
that's declared inside some method.
For example, lima is a local variable.
And if that variable is declared inside
the method, outside of any block like
an if statement or a while loop,
then that variable can be used, and
has a particular value that you set it to,
all the way through that method.
So in this case I can use the variable
lima anywhere inside the main method, but
not outside the main method.
Second kind of variable I wanna
talk about are parameters.
Parameters are those arguments
that we pass into methods, and
they behave basically just
like local variables.
You can use them anywhere
inside the method,
you can change their value if you want to.
And essentially,
they're just like local variables.
The third kind of variable
are called member variables.
Now you're familiar with
member variables already.
They're those variables
that belong to a class.
Rather than being declared
locally in any method,
they're declared outside
any method in the class.
And this means that these variables, their
scope is actually the entire class itself.
So you can refer to latitude and
longitude from any method inside
this simple location class.
So they have kind of a broader scope or
a wider array of places where they can
be used than those local variables.
So that in a nutshell describes scope and
a few different kinds of variables,
but really what we want to do is be able
to reason with this notion of scope and
in order to do that we're going
to go back to our memory model.
So here's where you're gonna need that pen
or that pencil and that piece of paper.
We're gonna trace through this code.
It's only two lines of code.
And we're gonna layer in this notion
of scope into our memory model.
So we're gonna start you off
with a simple statement here,
which is just a variable declaration,
and an assignment statement.
So you know what to do.
You draw the box,
you put the value in the box.
There you go.
There's our variable.
It's called lat, and
it stores the value -12.0.
But now we're going to, as I mentioned,
layer in a notion of scope.
So this variable doesn't
exist just anywhere,
it exists inside the scope
of the main method.
So the way I'm gonna denote that in my
model is I'm gonna draw a box around that
variable and label it with the name
of the scope that I'm talking about.
So I've got a fancy box with some shadows,
but
in your drawing on your piece of paper,
just put a simple box around it.
Label it with the name of the method,
which is main.
My next line down,
I declare another local variable,
lima, inside of the main method as well.
So that also goes into the box
representing the scope for me.
Now things get a little bit interesting,
because lima is an object type variable.
It's going to store a reference
to a SimpleLocation object.
So that SimpleLocation object, as we've
looked at before, gets created over here,
in the heap,
which is a separate part of memory.
So the SimpleLocation object gets created,
and its two member variables, latitude and
longitude, get placed inside the object
that gets created on the heap.
So that latitude and longitude,
they're not inside main scope.
They're over there in
the scope of the object.
So that's how I'm going to
denote them in our memory model.
But when the constructor gets called
we get some more variables that get
instantiated.
We get those parameters latIn and
lonIn and
they have their own scope which is local
to the constructor for SimpleLocation.
So I need to draw that scope in together
with the variables latIn and lonIn.
So I've got another scope box for
the constructor with the parameters
that I've passed in.
Those parameters of course get their value
from the arguments that I passed when
I called the constructor.
Now I'm gonna add one more thing
to the scope of the constructor.
And that is this keyword, this.
So, we talked about this before.
This refers to the calling object.
And in any method that's inside the class,
we have access to this keyword, this.
And what this stores is a reference
to the object that we just created.
So, in this case,
we see that object over there on the heap.
We have our keyword this whose value is
a reference to that newly created object.
And I'll put this inside the constructor
scope because the constructor has access
to this.
So now we can go ahead and
trace through the rest of the constructor.
We see that that first line of
the constructor takes the value of latIn,
which is inside the constructor scope, and
copies that value over into this.latitude.
So, we follow the arrow and
copy that into the member variable
latitude inside the object.
Same things happens with
the longitude variable.
We just copy the value from lonIn over
into the objects version of the longitude
variable.
Now, the constructor is over.
So what happens to its scope?
Well, when a method ends,
its scope disappears.
So all those local variables,
the parameters, any variable that has
been declared locally, they disappear.
They go away.
You can never use them again.
They're just gone.
And now as we know, the constructor is
over, so we return back to the main
method and set lima to have a reference
to that newly created object.
So that's basically it for adding
scope to your memory model diagrams.
There's just one more subtlety I want
to touch on before we finish off
this introduction to scope,
and that's the keyword this.
So we've been using it,
and it's very useful, but
it's not strictly required in Java.
So I don't have to preface my
member variables with a this dot.
I don't have to preface calls to
methods inside my class with this dot.
I can omit this.
And Java will work just fine.
It will figure out what I'm
talking about just fine, and
let's take a closer look
at how it does that.
So, if I leave off the keyword this, what
Java is going to do is first gonna say,
oh, I see a variable name called latitude.
I think that's probably a local variable,
so I'm gonna look for it inside the scope
of the method that I'm currently in,
which, in this case, is the constructor.
But in this case, it's not going to find
the variable latitude in the constructor.
So what it's going to do instead is
look over in the object, basically,
that was the calling object for
this particular method.
So it looks over here in
the SimpleLocation object,
now it finds the variable latitude, and
that's the variable that gets changed
with this assignment statement.
So that's all there is to scope.
And we've got some practice problems for
you which we hope you'll enjoy.