Hi, and
welcome back to our module on Scope.
It's time for
another one of these concept challenges.
Again, the flow for this is, you're gonna
pause, think about the problem yourself.
You're gonna discuss this if you
have other learners around you.
You're gonna watch the UC San Diego
learners tackle the problem.
And then you're gonna
hear our explanation.
So the question here is gonna
involve essentially two classes.
You've been working a great
deal with simple location,
and we're gonna keep using this class.
And that's the one on the left.
We've got a tester class on the right,
and that tester class has a main method.
It's within this main method where you're
gonna see a number of things get declared.
And something get printed.
The big question is, what gets printed?
>> Hi, I'm Tinky.
>> Hi, I'm Peter.
>> And I am Joe.
>> So what actually happens when
we go back to our main method and
we look at lat gets negative 12.0.
Is that going to change
lima's latitude value,
since that's what we
took in as the variable?
>> Well I think since we were just
working with a primitive data type.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Then it was just like
getting a copy of it, right?
It wasn't doing the whole
arrow thing like before.
We're not pointing to an old object,
we're just getting a copy of it's data.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Mm-hm, all right.
In regarding the scope, I think the double
here is adjusting the main scope, so
it wont have any access
to the object itself.
Right?
So you're changing the number here,
you just change the number in this scope.
>> Oh, like locally?
>> Yeah, just like locally.
>> All right so.
So even we come back to the main method
and we look at lat gets negative 12.0,
that's not gonna change
the latitude in our lima.
>> Right, I see.
>> You just have the same name,
but two different access, I think.
>> All right, okay, so in the end when
we print out lima.lat, it's gonna
remain whatever we created it in
the first place, which was negative 15.5.
>> Mm-hm.
All right, cool.
>> As you saw when
the students were discussing,
the key to solving this problem
is tracing through the code.
So what we're gonna do is exactly that.
Now with our code we're always gonna start
with main, as we have in the past, and
we're gonna start with the very first line
in code, which is that double lat = -15.5.
Just so
we know with all the memory diagrams,
I'm gonna start by creating scope and
main.
And I'm gonna declare space for
a variable named lat.
The first thing I'm gonna do
then is fill that with- 15.5.
And that does the first line of code.
Next step we're gonna create
a new variable called lima.
Right over here.
And that's just a reference.
Then we call new SimpleLocation,
pass it a lat and a -77.0.
That operation is now gonna
call the constructor.
So let's move to the scope
of the constructor.
Box this off as the scope of main, and
box off the scope of my
constructor in simple location.
ctor stands for constructor.
And within that scope,
I've passed now two parameters.
So it has two variables, both LatIn
and lonIn.
Each of those parameters just
are now prefilled with the values
as defined at the time of the call.
So lat was -15.5 this is copy
pass by value in Java so -15.5.
And lonIn is gonna be -77.0.
The other piece here is we
said new simple location.
The act of saying new actually
allocates space on the heap.
So what I'm gonna do down here,
is create that space on the heap, for
a simple location object.
And that object is gonna have the private
instance variables, lat and lon.
At this point we already see that we
have a number of cases where we see
the variable lat.
And that's gonna be at
the heart of this problem.
So let's continue walking
through the code.
So we're right now in
the middle of SimpleLocation.
We've already passed in
these two perimeters, and
what we're gonna do now is
actually do this line of code.
So this.lat refers to
the object on the heap.
This is my SimpleLocation object.
And it's gonna be assigned
the value of LatIn.
Which is minus 15.5.
So I'm gonna copy that value over.
The next line of code is gonna
behave exactly the same way, right?
All it's gonna do is
copy minus 77 into lon.
Now we finish this constructor.
And the end of any method, as we know,
these variables essentially get destroyed.
So I'm just gonna do a quick line through
it to say our constructor variables
are gone, and we're now back in main.
So within main, the very next line of code
we're gonna execute is right down here.
It's gonna say lat =- 12,
what lat are we referring to?
Well, I'm gonna look at my local scope,
I have a variable named lat.
And I'm gonna change it to be -12.
Now I've already made one mistake here.
And that mistake is,
when this constructor finished,
it would have returned a pointer to this.
And I failed to connect this
to the object on the heap.
All right, now that's connected properly,
we now would have done
the change to this to be -12.
And now, we're gonna try a print,
lima.lat.
So I'm gonna follow my pointer,
my reference out to lima,
and I'm gonna check what
value does lat have?
Well, the value is- 15.5.
What's gonna be printed,
then, is exactly that, -15.5.
What we see from this
walking through this code,
is that as long as you trace through
the code, you draw your memory diagrams,
you're gonna be able to
solve this type of problem