[SOUND] So welcome back.
Before we do the big reveal and say what
actually happened, let's sift through and
see if we can predict it.
Okay, so
stepping through the code means we have
to run together through the main method.
And we're gonna pretend to be
the computers running this code.
Okay, so the first thing that we have to
do is we're declaring the variable coords.
And so using our memory models,
that means that we need to write
the word coords next to a box
in the scope of the main method.
And what we want in that box
is a reference to a new array
that is initialized to the values
5.0 in index 0, and 0.0 in index 1.
Okay, so
the coords variable is in Main's scope and
the array object that we
created is in The Heap.
And so, what's stored in the box for
coords is a reference to the array.
Okay, what's important here,
what's important to keep in mind is that
an array is not a primitive type,
it's an object type.
Okay so, so far, here's our memory model
and we've gone through one line of code.
Now we get to the line of code that
we will spend the most time on, and
this is when we now declare
the variable accra.
And this variable is going
to be of type ArrayLocation,
which means that what we want to do is,
still in our Main's scope,
draw a box with accra.
And what we're going to fill in
there is a reference to an object.
But in order to refer to an object,
an object needs to be constructed.
And that's what that keyword new is doing.
It's saying hey, I want a new object.
And the kind of object that I want
is the ArrayLocations object.
And so I have to go to
the ArrayLocation class and
see that in The Heap, I'm going to
have an ArrayLocation instance.
And the instance variables associated
with that ArrayLocation instance, while
they're listed right there in the class
definition, and I need a coords variable.
And now I'm going to go ahead and
follow the constructor to
initialize the variables
in the instance that I have
of the object that I have
of type ArrayLocation.
So in the constructor's scope, I have
another variable that's called coords.
And that's my local variable for
the constructor method that is
the parameter to that constructor method.
So, the constructor ArrayLocation has,
as a parameter,
a variable that's called coords.
And what we do in this constructor.
Oh, sorry.
Going back.
Before we go ahead and
see what's in the meat of the constructor,
we have to see what the value
of that parameter is.
So let's think about what's
passed into the ArrayLocation
constructor when we were
in the main method.
When we were in the main method, what
we passed into a relocation is coords.
Aah!
Too many coords.
We can take care of it.
We know what to do by
looking at the memory models.
The coords that's a parameter
to the constructor
is the variable in Main's scope.
And so the red arrow is what needs
to be copied into the value of
the variable in the constructor's scope.
And so now the constructor's
scope coords variable also
points to the variable,
to the array that we had in The Heap.
All right, so when we call
the ArrayLocation constructor,
what we're doing is we're creating
a new scope for the constructor.
We've got a variable in there that
is the parameter to that method.
And that variable is initialized
to the value that was passed in,
which was a reference to
the array in The Heap.
Okay, so now we need to remember one more
thing when we have a constructor, and
that is that we want a variable as well
in the constructor's scope called this.
And what this does is point
to the location in The Heap
where we've allocated space for
the object that we're creating.
And remember that when we finish with
a constructor, what we'll be returning
to Main is that reference to the object
that we've just made and initialized.
Okay, so here's our picture so far.
And now let's figure out what's happening
when we actually execute the code in
the ArrayLocation constructor and
try to initialize the variables
in the object that we've created.
So the one line of code in that
constructor is an assignment,
this.coords = coords.
So what we're trying to do is,
we're trying to assign the value on
the righthand side to the thing
on the lefthand side.
And so,
on the righthand side we just have coords.
But we're in the constructor's scope,
so that variable is the circled variable
coords that has that red reference that's
pointing to the array in The Heap.
And what we're doing is we're copying
that reference to this.coords.
So remember when we have a dot,
that means that we can find
the variable by following the arrows.
So we look at where this points to, and
this points to the object of
type ArrayLocation in The Heap.
And what we're doing is we're setting
the value of the variable coords
in that object scope.
So this.coords, that variable in The Heap
that belongs to the object
is going to now point to
the array in The Heap that was pointed to
also by coords in the constructor's scope.
So we have all of these arrows,
references pointing to the same array.
But notice that we're still missing one.
We've got one box empty.
And so, we're going to want
to fill in that box, but
we're going to be able to do that.
And let's think about how that happens.
So, let's think about what's gonna happen,
now that we've executed
the one line of code in the constructor
and finished with the constructor.
So we're done the constructor and
what happens now is that the reference
that was contained in the this
variable in the constructor gets
copied into the variable that
gets assigned the new object.
Okay, so that yellow arrow is now
allowing the variable accra to
point the object that
we created in The Heap.
But also we have to do a couple of things
when we finish executing the constructor.
We notice also that once
the method finishes and
returns its value, its scope goes away.
And all variables associated
with it just go away.
And so, we can erase it from our memory,
erase it from our memory model.
We don't need to think about it anymore.
Okay, so we finished our constructor.
Our memory model is now a little bit
cleaner and we have in our Main's
scope a couple of variables and they
point to a couple of things in The Heap.
And so, now let's think about what happens
as we continue executing the main method.
So we go ahead and
we try to set the value at the first
position in the coords array,
so at index 0.
And we're setting it to 32.9.
And so, what we're doing is we're saying,
let's look at coords in Main's scope.
And we're setting the value at
the first position there to 32.9.
Cool, we can do that.
Similarly, we look at that same
reference to the same array and
we change its second position at index 1.
Cool, we did that.
But now, let's think about what
happens when we print accra.coords.
Its value at its index is 0.
And so, when we think about that number,
well we need to find it
by following the arrows.
So we go to the variable accra,
and it's got a reference.
And so, when we say accra.coords,
we want to follow the reference from
accra all the way over to its object,
and look at the variable in
that object's scope coords.
And that coords is also pointing to
the same array that we had in The Heap.
And so, notice what we get output is 32.9.
Okay, pause and think.
There's something weird happening.
Right, we wanted to store in the accra
object the coordinates of accra.
But then, we were able to do
something outside that object,
without any setter methods, without
going into the variables of that object.
And without doing that,
we were able to change the value of
the instance variables in that object.
And that is not a good thing.
So this is what happens
when we're too loose
about using object type variables as
opposed to primitive type variables.
They can change on us without us
intending to have them change.
And so the moral of this example is a,
memory models help us in actually tracing
through code and
figuring out what happens.
And b, when we have objects, and
basically object types which include
arrays, something that's not primitive,
then we really have to worry about what
is allowed to refer to that object.
And how can its values change,
in perhaps unintended ways.
Okay, so hopefully, you feel like you
can do this yourself as well with any
example that's thrown at you.
This is a tricky one, so if you need
to go back and look at it again, do.
But now you're ready to go,
continuing on with this module and beyond.