[MUSIC].
So welcome back to this second of a
sequence of videos in which we're going to
be building a graphical application.
And remember our goal is to display
this beautiful beach picture and
add a second sun.
And that sun is going to
be a visual clock for us.
So, if we deconstruct the application and
what we need to do.
Basically, we need to create
some window or canvass and
then place items unto that canvass.
And so, where going to have a background
image and then we're going to put some
shapes unto the image and so
we'd like a way for our canvass.
To be able to display images and shapes,
and for us to be able to control
the location and color and
various other properties as well.
Let's think about how we would do that and
we'll start by thinking about controlling
the position of elements
in our application, so
a really convenient way of specifying
position is using coordinates.
You probably thought about them a lot
in various math backgrounds and
other situations.
Maps, for example, and what we can
do is we can separate our canvas,
the window that we're working with,
into a grid and
we've got points on this grid
being determined by their location
across in the x direction and
up and down in the y direction and
so the x direction determines how
far across the picture we are and
the y coordinate determines how
far down the picture we are.
And so it's useful to keep in mind how
each of these variables changes as we
walk across the picture.
And so the 0 of the x coordinate where the
x is smallest is on the left hand side.
And as we go towards the right,
the x value increases.
And that's just as you would expect
from other contact, the coordinates.
But y is a little different.
Y is a little tricky.
It start as 0 at the very top,
not the bottom,
at the very top is where y is equal to 0.
Then as we move down
the picture is how it grows.
All right so let's practice.
Let's take an example and
suppose we had a canvas and
it was 200 pixels wide and
200 pixels long.
And let's think about what
the coordinates would be
of the center of the yellow
sun in this picture.
Okay, so let's think about it and when
you're ball parking at these coordinates,
what you might want to do is
think about relative position.
So is the sun half way across the picture?
No, it's not really, is it?
A quarter of the way across the picture?
Yeah, it kind of looks like
it is a quarter of the way.
So, the center x coordinate
would be probably around 50, and
ditto for the y coordinate.
It's probably a quarter
of the way down as well.
And these are just rough numbers, so
it's not exactly those, but pretty good.
Okay, so we know how to place, how to at
least determine positions on the canvas.
But now what we would like to do is
translate this into actual Java code and
not just talk about abstract
drawing a grid on a canvas but
actually coding it out.
We are going to use processes and
processes is this amazing
versatile library of classes and
methods and
data types that we can use in
order develop our applications.
The thing is though you would not want to
memorize everything that's in processing.
What you want to do is have some sort of
index, or a way of looking things up.
I really want to do something with the
size, I'm going to look in my processing
index to see if there's a method to
do with the size of the canvas and
the Javadoc documentation of
processing gives us exactly that.
So we look up in processing and we see
that there's a class called PApplet.
What this class does is it does all
of the hard work under the hood.
Of bringing up a canvas,
a little window, and then giving us
functionality for drawing in that window.
So when we wanna go ahead and
define our application,
the one with La Jolla Shores
in the background and the sun,
we don't need to worry about what it means
to draw a canvas on my computer screen.
I can leave that to the PApplet datatype,
which is a kind of a GUI datatype,
and then just customize
what's being displayed in that window
that's being brought up by my PApplet.
So if we look at this code snippet,
what we see here is that our class,
the class that we're defining,
MyPApplet extends PApplet.
So extends is a really important keyword
and Leo is going to tell you all about
that in next module about inheritance.
But you don't need to
worry about that just yet.
We're going to use this notion and
then learn about it after you've got
some experience about with how powerful
it is for now think about extends PApplet
as a way of telling Java that we would
like to use the core functionality
that's available in PApplet but
then customize it a little bit.
The people who wrote processing
developed the data type PApplet.
They developed it with graphical
applications in mind so
it gives us a kind of GUI.
And what we're going to do now
with MyPApplet is customize it and
change it up a little bit.
But in order to use it, we have to tell
Java the thing that I'm extending,
well it comes from the processing library.
And so in the beginning of our
code there we have to tell Java,
please look at the code that's
available in processing.core,
and we're going to access
some of those data types.
So that's what that
line up there is doing.
But now, when we we want to build our
PApplet, what we have to do, our job,
is to specify 2 methods.
What we are going to need to tell Java is
first of all, how to configure the canvas.
That's going to be in the set up method.
Then, once we've configured the canvas
what to actually draw in there, and
that is going to be in the draw method.
If you think about the flow of
execution of our application
what's going to happen is that Java
will execute the setup method once.
As we run our application,
the first thing that happens that
we define is the setup method.
And then that's executed once and
then that code is never touched again.
And then every time the canvas
is refreshed or redrawn, for
example, if it gets
resized in the screen and
the draw method will get executed
again and again and again.
So that piece of code gets executed often.
We loop through it a lot.
So let's think about what actually happens
when we start developing this code.
And to do that, let's do baby steps.
And this is a useful thing
when you're testing your code,
as well, or debugging,
is to run it very often.
And you'll see especially when you're
debugging graphical applications.
You'll want to stop developing code and
hit that run button in Eclipse.
Extremely frequently because it's going
to be really the best way of making sure
that what you think you're implementing is
actually what's showing up on a screen and
you'll be able to catch
bugs much more quickly.
So you want to hit that run button very,
very often.
Okay, so if we do that even before we
put any methods in our class at all
Let's think about what will happen.
And here I did in eclipse offline and
I'm giving you a little screenshot of it.
And what you'll see is that we didn't
get an error, the code compiled, and
it did something even though
we didn't define any methods.
And that's because we're
using the power of PApplet.
So PApplet as a datatype
already tells Java, hey,
I want to draw some default canvas and
then I'm just gonna wait.
I'm gonna do nothing,
unless the person whose extending
this class, tells me what to do.
Okay, so by default,
the applet just displays a blank canvas.
But we wanna do more than that.
We wanna draw our picture.
And so
we're going to now work on bringing in
some content to both the setup method and
the draw method.
Now, what content?
Well, that content is
going to be determined
by the methods available to
us in the processing library.
And so it's really useful as
you're developing to have
a browser open with the documentation.
Open available to you and keep going
back and forth between Eclipse and
your browser, as you are developing.
Don't memorize these methods.
Libraries change over time.
Which one is most modern,
that will always change.
All the libraries that are most useful
have really good documented code, so
you'll be able to understand which
methods are available to you.
Okay, so
let's think about the setup method, and
the pieces that we want to do
at the very beginning are to.
Set some default size to our canvas and
then get access to the background beach
picture that's going to be
the background of our application.
Okay, so
we look up in the index we're processing
the documentation and oh woo-hoo!
We have a size method.
And that documentation
even gives us an example.
It's sweet we're great.
And we realize that if we type
in size open graphic 200,
200 then what that setup method is going
to do when it executes this line of code,
is display our canvas at the default size,
200 wide and 200 long, or high.
All right, cool, we've done that.
And now what we'd like to do is have
access to the background image.
And, again,
look up in the documentation and
see that there's a really
nice way of loading an image.
And we could even load
an image from a URL.
So an image might exist as a JPEG file,
for
example, on your local machine or
it might be on a server somewhere.
And with processing, we have a way
to going to a specified web address,
a URL, and grabbing an image there and
bringing that into our application.
And so in the documentation we
have an example of how to do that.
We stick it in our code and
now we've defined out setup method.
Whats going to happen when we run?
So pause.
What do you think?
I hope that you ran this example
in eclipse and saw what happens.
And what happens might be
a little counter intuitive.
We still get a blank canvas.
The reason that happens is because we've
only loaded the image into memory,
we haven't displayed it yet.
And so it's really useful when
you're using methods from a library,
to read through the description.
And if we had read through them we would
have seen that what happens when we
execute load image is that we have
that image loaded into memory and
it's stored in a PImage.
Object and then we'll have access to it
later, but nothing in that documentation
talks about displaying that object on the
canvas, and we'll have to dot that later.
And so in the next video, we're going
to really implement the draw method
of our PApplet, and once we do that,
we'll have our full working application.