[SOUND] All right.
Welcome back to our sequence of videos
where we're building an application that's
going to indicate the hour of the day
based on the color of the sun that
we've added to the picture.
And up until now we've figured
out how to use a PApplet class
from the processing library, and we've
set up our canvas using the setup method.
And so now what we'd like to do is
fill in the draw method which is
going to let us display the content.
Okay, so what we'd like to do
is display the background image
that we brought into memory.
And so
we can do that by using the image method.
Okay, so let's do just that.
We say image and
then (backgroundImg, 0,0).
And what does that do?
Well it seems to us like it's gonna have
something to do with background image but
the 0,0 at the end of that
are the coordinates that we want for
the position of the top
left corner of the image.
So in this method what we're doing is
we're saying we would like to draw
a particular image, and we'd like that
image to be located in our canvas so
that its top left corner is at 0,0, and
0,0 is the top left corner of the canvas.
And so that means that we're going to want
to have our canvas be at the very top and
very left.
Okay.
So lets see what happens if we do that.
[SOUND] Is that what you expected?
Remember that image that we
want is all of the beach.
And we're getting a bunch of blue but
it's familiar blue.
That blue is a sky blue,
and the reason for
that is that we're actually getting
just a tiny piece of the sky.
The image is way, way, way too big.
Our canvas is just 200
pixels by 200 pixels and
our image was, well it's a high-def
image we took with a modern camera.
So it's much more than that, if you think
about resolutions of images these days.
And so what we need to do in order to
display the whole image is to resize it.
So what we're going to need to do is
to figure out how to take a really big
image and cram it into the canvas
that we're working with.
And so we look up our handy documentation.
There's a theme here, right?
Keep looking at the documentation.
And we see that we have a resize
method that we can call, and we can
specify the width and the height that we
would like our image to be compressed to.
Now, our image already came
at a specified size, but
what we're doing in the resized image,
is we're saying, move, change it.
We want a new size, okay?
So let's try and say, maybe we want to
have our image just go 50 pixels across,
so it's only gonna go a quarter of the way
across our canvas, which was 200 by 200,
and it's gonna go half the way down,
so it's gonna be 100 pixels long.
And so we resize our image in memory,
and then we go ahead and display it.
Okay so it went a quarter of the way
across and half way down, so
that did it, but notice how
warped the picture looks because
the ratio of width to
height is totally off.
It's totally not what the original image
looked like and so we see the trees
look like they're reaching like
skyscrapers or something in this image,
and it's not really giving us the kind
of image that we'd like to do.
And so what we'd like to do is be
a little bit, maybe more careful,
maybe we wanna use up the whole canvas,
and so
we could say let's use all 200 pixels
across and all 200 pixels down.
And so now we see the full image,
and we see it a little bit bigger.
But it's still not the right proportions.
The trees are still way too big,
it doesn't look like
the original image that we had.
And so maybe we do something
a little bit tricky, okay.
So what we've done here
is tricky in two ways.
Let's start with the 0
that we've got there.
And the 0 that we've got is the first
parameter of the resize method,
says I don't want to specify width,
I want to be lazy.
And the reason I want to be lazy is that
I want the proportions of my picture to
match the original, and so I only want
to specify one of the coordinates.
Just the y, just the height coordinate.
I want my picture to be
the full height of the canvas.
And then, Java,
you calculate the right width.
You calculate the right width so
that the aspect ratio, the ratio between
the width and the height, is maintained
to be the same as the original image.
Okay, so
if we put a 0 in one of the parameters,
that means that we don't want to
calculate both of the parameters.
Java is gonna do it for us, so that
the original proportions are maintained.
The second tricky thing that we've done,
is instead of writing an actual number
in the second parameter,
we've written the word height.
And the advantage of doing that is
that height is an instance variable
in the PApplet class.
Which tells us the height of the canvas.
It tells us how many pixels
high the current canvas is, and
if you think about taking our canvas and
dragging it so
it's bigger, or smaller,
the height of the canvas is gonna change.
And this height variable will
change right along with it.
So what this does when we say that
the background image will have the size,
so that its height is
the height of the canvas,
it means that our image will
change right along with
the canvas as the user plays around
with the size of the canvas.
So we've made our picture dynamic.
We've put our background
image that we wanted
in the right proportions
in the background.
But we're still missing the sun.
So in the next video, we'll wrap
things up by putting the sun in.