[MUSIC]
We are almost done so
remember what we've done up until now.
We are working towards building an
application that has a background image of
the beach, and then has a visual clock
that is represented by a second sun.
And at this point we've defined
the setup method of our class
MyPApplet that customizes the PApplet
class provided by processing.
And then we've started
working on the draw method.
And our draw method so
far has brought in and
displayed the background image but
we're still missing the sun.
So let's think back to where
we want the sun to be.
And think about where that location is in
that grid of coordinates that we have for
specifying positions on our canvass.
And so we want the sun to be somewhere
in the top left of our picture.
And before talked about how that's roughly
about 50, x equals 50, y equals 50.
Which is about a quarter of the way across
and maybe a quarter of the way down.
And maybe we wanna tweak it so
it's a little bit higher up.
And so
we want maybe a fifth of the way down.
And so what we wanna think about
is how to specify the location
of the center of the sun in this x and
y space.
And we're going to do it dynamically so
that the sun stays in that top left corner
and visible, even as the user of our
application might resize the window.
And so we're not going to use fixed
numbers like 50 pixels across or
50 pixels down,
we're going to use relative coordinates
relative to those variables,
width or height of the canvas.
All right, so let's think about
where we might want to put it, and
about a quarter of the way across and
a fifth of the way down seems like
about right position for the sun.
So now we need to go ahead and
place sun there.
And we use a library method
ellipse to draw an ellipse
in the locations x and
y so the coordinates of
the center of the ellipse are the first
two parameters of the method.
But then we have two
other parameters as well.
And, so the second two parameters
are the actual width of the ellipse and
the height of the ellipse.
So if those two parameters happen to be
equal, then we're going to get a circle.
And if those type of
parameters are unequal,
then we'll get an ellipse
that's maybe flatter or longer.
Okay, and so a thought question,
something to keep in mind.
With this particular method, will what
we're drawing always be a true circle,
or can you think of a situation
where what we've specified over here
will actually look like a flattened
ellipse or a tall ellipse?
All right so
that's something to keep in mind.
But let's keep going with our example,
with our application.
And if we run the code as it is right now,
we see we get our circle
in the top left corner.
But it's what?
Okay and so, here is where we get to
the dynamic part that we want to change as
this application runs.
And what we'd like to change
is the color of the sun.
So now we're getting to the nitty gritty
of how we want the color to change,
now that we've displayed the shapes.
Okay, so let's think about how
we're going to specify the sun.
And this is a super common way of
coding colors in programming languages.
It's used in web development, it's used
in Java, it's used all over the place.
What we're going to do is
we're going to specify a color
by specifying three values
that describe a color.
The amount of red in it, the amount of
green in it, and the amount of blue in it.
So we think of a color as being
decomposed into three channels rgb.
Okay and so
we want that sunny yellow color and so
we need to talk about how
much red will be in there,
how much green will be in there,
how much blue will be in there.
And the smallest amount of
a color that we can specify is 0,
we can say we don't want any for example,
blue or we don't want any green and
the maximum amount is going to be 255.
And that 255 is, there's a reason for it.
It seems like a random number.
There's a reason for it, you can look
it up, but it's there for a reason.
And it's the maximum value for
a color channel in the RGB coding.
Okay, so for
the particular color that we care about,
it turns out that we're going to get that
warm sunny shade of yellow if we have
the red set to it's maximum value 255, the
blue set to it's minimum value 0, because
blue's kind of a cold color, we don't want
it in this particular shade, and the green
is helping that red go off to yellow so
the green is pretty high as well.
Now, you don't need to
know how to design colors.
It's kind of fun.
You can play around with
these three values and
see what colors you can create,
but you can use Google and
just put in the search string,
HTML color selector or RGB codes.
Color selectors and you'll get lots of
these palettes where you can click on
the particular shade that
you're interested in and
out will come the rgb code for it.
So it's a handy tool and
you should feel free to use that.
Okay, so if we set the fill or
the pen color, you could think of,
of the drawing to be 255, 209, 0,
i.e., the color specified by the RGB code,
where R level is 255,
G level is 209, and B level is 0,
And then draw the ellipse then
the ellipse is filled with that color.
And so then we get our beautiful sun just
like we wanted in the top left corner
of Lahoya Shores Beach okay.
Well that's great for
the static version but
now we want that sun to
change color over time.
So at 7:00 when it's beautiful sunset
we want maybe a pinker sun and
then as dusk comes we want it gray.
And the way that we can get our
application to change is by
remembering that crucial fact that
when we have the methods set up and
draw in a class that extends p applet,
the draw method loops and
updates the drawing over and
over and over again.
And so what we're going to do is
in our draw method we're going to
set the color of the sun based on the hour
of the current time stamp of the clock.
So I'm going to leave that as a tease for
you.
I want you to try and implement it.
And in one of the support videos that we
have coming up Christina is going to work
through how to draw a similar method,
and then we'll be right back at you from
tweaking the example that she shows you
to getting this application to work.
And you can do it.
But I want you to keep in mind
that central paradigm of setup
being run once and then draw anything
dynamic, that changes, it's gonna be in
that draw method because it gets
executed over and over and over again.
So that's one big central
message from this example.
The second really important message
that I want you to get from these videos
is documentation is our friend.
So when we are writing code,
think of yourself as joining
this wonderful brotherhood and
sisterhood of programmers all around
the world developing code together.
Developing libraries together and
we want to use each others experience,
expertise, and draw from the work
that we've all done together and
the way we can do that is by describing
what methods we have and what they do.
And so the API for
libraries are what tell us
what methods are available in a library,
so that's like our index to the library.
But also, what we can use those methods
to do and what functionality that have.
So for the processing library,
for the library that we've been using
up until now to create applets and
to draw shapes on them the documentation
is on your screen right now.
And in the next lesson of this module,
we'll be taking it one step further and
thinking about how processing
can be used as the backbone for
some more sophisticated
visual applications
that also involve real-time
data coming from the Internet.