[MUSIC]
So I remember first
starting to write code.
And at the beginning, I was told that
documentation's really important and
that we should comment everything.
And not just the step by step,
each line put a comment, but also,
when we first define a method, that there
should be a little description in Javadoc
that other people might be able to use.
And this other people notion was just
sort of vaguely said by, oh by the way,
someone might wanna use your method.
I always thought it was kind of
silly because if we do the other
recommendations and name variables
appropriately and the name of the method
should maybe be something that's natural,
then who would need the documentation?
And then I started using
other people's code,
because I started writing more complicated
programs, and using libraries.
And all of a sudden, I was reading
other people's documentation.
And when they didn't put very much in
there, other than the name of the method
or the name of the variables,
it would be really frustrating.
I'd have to do a whole lot of testing and
trial and error to try and
figure out what these methods are doing.
And so I learned the hard way that
documentation's really important.