[APPLAUSE]
>> All right, now we get to have some fun.
In that last video that Mia presented,
she showed you how to work with GUIs
in Java and
specifically using the processing library.
And in this video we're gonna
actually write some code together
to create a fun little GUI.
So, I hope you're at your computer.
You should open up Eclipse.
You should navigate to the package, to the
project, where you've got all the code set
up for this class that we set up in Module
1, and you'll be ready to get started.
Okay, so
we're gonna get started by creating
a new package to place our code in.
So let's go over here
to our source folder,
and I'll right-click and
I'll create a new package.
So here's my new package.
I'm gonna call my package GUI module.
Okay, so I've got a new package
to put my new class in it.
It's always a good idea to organize
your classes in packages so
they don't just become a mess
that's all unorganized.
So inside this new class
there's our new package.
I am going to create a new class.
So I go over here,
right-click again and say New > Class.
And I'll call my class MyDisplay and
create it.
So here's my new class.
So let me get rid of this window
here cuz I don't need it anymore.
So I've got my new class all set up.
And if you remember back from Mia's video,
the way I'm gonna turn this class in to
a class that represents a GUI is I'm
going to make it extend with this
magical keywords extends, that we're
gonna talk about next module, I promise.
And it's going to extend
the PApplet class.
All right, so that PApplet class, it's,
Eclipse is giving me an error on that.
It's saying, I don't know what the PApplet
class is, and it turns out it's actually
smart enough to fix this error for
us by importing the correct class for me.
So f I go right down here and I go yes,
I want to import that PApplet class,
it will do that for me.
So it adds that import line for
me and I'm ready to go.
So now if you remember back from the video
as well you know that there are two magic
methods that we have to implement
in order to get our GUI to display.
So let's implement those now.
So they are public void setup.
That's the code that gets run right at
the beginning of when that GUI starts up.
And then there's this other
method public void draw, and
that's the method that's gonna get
called every time the GUI is redrawn,
which actually turns out
happens quite a bit.
So I've got our two methods set up and
ready to go, and
now in fact this GUI will run.
So let's try it out.
Let's look at what happens
when I press play.
Great.
So when I press play,
I see a small window here.
That's my GUI.
It's kind of a boring GUI, so
let's do something interesting with it.
Let's start first by playing
with the size of that window.
So, you may remember from the video,
we have this method called size, and
I can pass in parameters,
the width that I want my window to be and
the height that I want my window to be.
So I'll make a 400 by 600 size window and
then run that again and see what happens.
There we go.
My window is both wider and
taller than it was last time.
So there's my new window.
Now, it's always a good idea to
just write a tiny piece of code and
then play around by pressing Run, and
we're gonna use this method a lot as we
write this GUI code, especially GUI code.
It's almost impossible to tell what you're
writing if you don't actually see it, so
we'll be writing a couple lines, running
it, and it'll be kinda more fun that way.
So now that we've got our window set up,
actually I want to make my window square,
so I'm gonna make
a window that 400 by 400.
Let's start playing around with color.
So I want to first change
the background color of this window.
And in order to do that, I need to
remember that there's a method that I can
call that will change
the background color.
Now, we might not remember what that
method is called, but that's okay.
And that's where our documentation
is going to come in handy.
So I'll use that page in a second.
But for now, I want to show
you the documentation page for
the processing library.
So here is the documentation page for the
processing library, and if you just search
for processing documentation you
should be able to find this page, or
the URL is right here.
And I can look right here
at this color column and
see I've got a number of methods that
will change the color of my drawing,
and one of them right here
is called background.
So if I click on the background method,
I see that there are a number of different
versions of this background method.
Remember that overloading we talked about
in module, in that last module on objects.
And you can see that there's a method,
there's a version of it that takes one
parameter, three parameters,
takes an image parameter.
I'm gonna focus here on the one
that takes three parameters and
explain that in a little bit more detail.
So that three parameter background method,
what it's doing is it's
taking three values which
are respectively the red, green, and
blue amounts that I want in my color.
So we're defining a color in terms
of its red, green, and blue.
And that's a standard way of
representing color on a computer.
So if I say I want no red, no green,
and no blue, I pass in all zeros.
And take a minute to guess about what
color you think this is gonna be.
All right, let's try to run it, and
see what happens, see if you were right.
Nope, it has errors.
I forgot a semicolon.
No problem, I'll fix that.
Now I'll run it, and now you can
see that this background is black,
because I have no red light,
no green light, no blue light.
So no light at all gives me black.
If I want white,
I can change these colors to,
these channels to all their maximum value,
which is 255.
And you can see that I'm going
to get a white background.
So there's my white background.
And I can play around with the color here.
I can change it to red
by making the blue and
the green channels both 0 and run again,
so there's my red background,
and I can keep playing around to get other
combinations of red, green, and blue.
But if you get tired of playing around,
there are plenty of sites on
the internet that you can go to.
Here's one that I like that
will allow you to pick an RGB,
sorry pick a color visually and
then it tells you what its RGB value is.
So, if I like this nice kinda teal color,
I can see that its red, green,
blue value are in those boxes below.
I think I copy those values
out into my processing window.
Okay, so I want my background
to be just a kind of plain grey.
So I'll put it at 200, 200, 200.
And incidentally, whenever I have a red,
green, blue value that are all the same,
I'll get some shade of grey.
The lower the numbers, the closer
to black, the higher the numbers,
the closer to white.
Okay, I've got my window setup.
I've got my canvas setup,
it's just gonna be a grey square.
And I am ready to draw a picture.
But we're gonna,
in order to keep these videos from getting
too long, I'm gonna break the video here.
Feel free to go off and play, start
creating your own image on this GUI, or
you can come back to the next video and
we'll draw a happy face.