[APPLAUSE]
>> All right, so now we're gonna
look at the example that Mia presented in
her video on your introduction to GUIs.
And that example was to display an image,
and
then put a sun on top of that
image by putting an ellipse there.
And change the color of that ellipse
depending on the time of day.
She talked about using hours
to calculate the time of day.
But I'm a little too impatient to wait for
hours to go by to see
the change in the sun.
So I've modified that example slightly.
So that the sun color is going to change
based on the secant of the minute.
So you can see here, as I open up this
application, I see my beach scene.
That already has a sun in it, but
my sun that I placed on top of it
is now changing color every second.
So it's getting darker,
and darker, and darker.
And in a minute you'll see it get lighter,
and lighter, and
lighter as it goes back
to its yellow color.
So let's take a look at the code
that makes that happen.
Here it is.
Of course, it's a GUI, so my class
needs to extend the PApplet class,
which is my base class for
implementing all of my GUIs.
And I'm going to implement these
two fundamental methods here,
the setup method, and the draw method.
I've got all the code written.
I'm just gonna walk you through it.
So the setup method is for
all the codes that I want to run once,
only when this method
first starts running.
So that involves setting
the size of the window,
setting the background color,
setting the stroke color to be black.
And then loading up my image and
placing it into the background.
In my draw method, here's where I'm
going to create and color the ellipse.
And the draw method is what's going to
get called over and over and over again.
So it's going to change the color
of that ellipse every second and
show me that change as you can see
there on the right of the screen.
So it's actually not too complicated
to understand how this is happening.
At the heart of this code,
all we are doing is calculating
a custom color on this line.
And then we're filling the ellipse on
that color that we're about to create.
And then we're going
to create the ellipse.
So I'm gonna talk about
created an ellipse first and
talk about how we create
that custom color.
So we're creating the ellipse to be based
on the width and the height of the window.
So we're taking the ratio of the width and
the height of the window over four and
over five,
to basically position the ellipse and
to size it according to
the height of the window.
So if the window was bigger,
that ellipse would be bigger.
And you have access to this width and
height member variables.
Since you're working inside a class
that extends the p applet class.
Those get set automatically for
you when you call the size method.
So that's just a way we can make things
a little bit more flexible in terms of how
big our window is, rather than setting
the size of the ellipse directly.
But really the interesting thing
here is how the color gets set.
So, the color gets set through this
helper method called sunColorSec.
And so let's take a look
at what sunColorSec does.
Well, the first thing it does, is it takes
an argument in, and it takes the argument,
which is a call to this built
in method called second.
And what this built in method called
second does, is it returns the number of
seconds that have elapsed since the last
minute according to your systems clock.
So that's built in for you.
You can use it.
There's a similar method called minute and
another method called hour,
that do just what you would expect.
So based on the number of seconds that
have elapsed since the last minute,
we can calculate a color,
a version of yellow, either very dark or
very light depending on
those number of seconds.
So what we're gonna do is we're gonna sort
of base everything on how close to the,
sort of bottom of the minute we are.
So how close to 30 seconds are we in
terms of the number of seconds that have
elapsed.
So the very first thing I'm
going to do in this method.
Well first I'm going to create my integer
array, that holds three integers and
that's going to the red, green, and
blue values that I'll be returning.
And then I'm gonna calculate the
difference between the seconds that have
elapsed and 30.
But I don't care if they are positive or
negative.
I just want to know the distance.
So I'm going to call
the math.abs function,
which is going to calculate
the absolute value of that number.
And I'll store that in
a variable called diffrom30.
Then I want to calculate a ratio in terms
of how far around the minute are we.
So I'm going to divide difffrom30 by 30.
So if I'm exactly at 30
then my difffrom30 is 0,
and I'll have 0 divided by 30 and
my ratio will be 0.
If I'm all the way up at 30,
then my difffrom 30 is going to be 30.
Sorry if I'm all the way up,
far away from 30,
so either at 0 or at 60,
then difffrom 30 is going to be 30.
And I'll have 30 divided by 30 which is 1.
So this is going to be
a number between 0 and 1,
depending on how far away I am from 30.
Then I'll use that ratio to scale
the red and the green values of
yellow to create a color that's
either very dark or very light.
So if my ratio is very close to 1,
then I'm gonna be multiplying 255
by something that's close to 1.
And I'm gonna get a very big number for
my red and my green.
My blue is always going to be 0 because
a pure yellow color would be 255 255 0.
So a bright yellow is going to happen
when that ratio is very close to one.
And then a dark yellow or
a black is going to happen when
that ratio is close to zero.
So when my ratio is very close to 0,
it's going to multiply by 255,
giving me a very small number.
And I'll end up with a color that's very
close to black, or even black itself, 000.
Now you'll notice that I'm
also casting the result of
this multiplication to an int,
because my array can only store integers.
So I have to do this cast
to do the type conversion.
Once I've got all those three values set,
I return my RGB array and
I use it to populate my fill method for
color red, green, and blue.
Since this draw method
is called continuously,
it will change the ellipse as it goes.