[MUSIC]
Hi everybody.
In this video we're going to do a walk
through of the program assignment for
Module 3, Part 1, and that's
implementing and testing a linked list.
First off, with all these assignments,
what we're gonna do is essentially start
by making sure we have the starter code.
Now if you pull up your code for
the project you're going to find
that there's a textgen package and
within that textgen package there's
MyLinkedList and MyLinkedListTester.
Those are the two files we're going to be
focusing on in this video walk-through.
So the first thing to do is essentially
just run MyLinkedListTester to make sure
everything's set up properly.
So if I run MyLinkedListTester,
what it's gonna tell me is that
essentially my tests have failed.
And the reason for that is I've
already put in some tests, but
we haven't actually ran
any of the implementation.
So this is what you should expect to see.
After you've got this
MyLinkedListTester running,
next step is to essentially open up and
examine the starter code.
And the way to do that is to essentially
to open up the mylinklist file itself,
look to see the methods that you're
essentially gonna implement.
And then to go through
MyLinkedListTester and
to see that we've actually created a setup
method for you which sets up the test, and
we've already created a testGet method,
which does all the tests that you really
should need to do for for the get method.
And then lastly, we have some
initial tests already in there for
you for test removed and then space for
the other methods that you're
going to need to write.
If you look back to my link list,
you're going to find that we've already
written a linklist node class for
you that has a previous element,
a next element, and data.
And I just wanna point out that you might
wanna add another constructor to this, but
we're giving you a constructor to
essentially start working with this class.
On this class has, these have package
access so you can access previous and
next from within your
My Linked list class.
When you go to submit, you're gonna
essentially submit two things.
You're gonna submit the code
which implements linked list,
which was the my linked list class,
as well as your code which is gonna
test the linked list implementation,
which is mylinikedlisttester.java.
And you're gonna submit separately,
but what I want to point out is I
don't want you to code this essentially
by writing the whole implementation.
And then thinking about
the tests you want to write.
I want you to do this essentially the same
way you do an industry which is write some
tests as you write your implementation and
just keep going back an forth so
that each step of your implementation
is tested before you go forward.
So to do this what we'll do is- we
already gave you the testGet method.
And what we'll do then is write enough of
the LinkedList class so that you're able
to run that tester and see if your
MyLinkedList notation's working for that.
So, after reviewing the testGet method
to see what's actually being performed,
go into MyLinkedList.java.
Author the constructor.
I do wanna point out that
it's up to you whether or
not you wanna use the same sentinel nodes.
We had a sentinel node and
a sentinel tail in all the videos.
Or if you just wanna go
without the sentinel nodes.
That's completely okay.
Either way will work for this assignment.
Anyway, so you're gonna create your
constructor, you're gonna create then
the get method which should return
the elements at that index.
If you're asking for an invalid index,
it should throw an index
out of bounds assumption.
You then wanna add an add method or
create an add method, and
this method is gonna add
an element to the end of the list.
It's always gonna add it
to the end of the list.
Once you've ran those methods,
you can go back into your tester,
run the tester, run the J Unit test.
And if things work properly, your test for
the get method should work properly now.
Notice that we've added a method,
the add method,
without actually adding any tests for it.
So the last step here is
to test your add method
to make sure that it's
working properly as well.
Once you've done this cycle of
creating some code and testing it and
going back and forth.
What you'll wanna do is do the same
process for the remaining methods in my
linked list, and those remaining methods
include size, which is how big the list
is, a method that adds an element
at a certain index within the list.
Or essentially inserts
an element at that index.
You'll want a remove method, which allows
you to remove an element from the list.
And notice, in all these cases,
if someone does something inappropriate,
like tries to add an element and
index that doesn't exist,
you should be throwing it
out of bounds exception.
If someone tries to remove an element,
an index that doesn't exist,
you should be throwing an index out
of bounds exception, and so on.
You should also author the set method,
which will change an element's
added index to a different value.
Now if someone tries to set or
add an element that has a null element.
You should also be throwing a null pointer
exception because people shouldn't
be putting a null element into the list.
I've already mentioned that you may want
to add an additional constructor for
linkless nodes, and the reason you want to
do this is when you first start authoring
your add method, that first add method,
what you'll notice is that if you're
seeing the same code in repeated places,
you might just want to put that code
in one place within
the linked list node class.
You also potentially want a two
string method to be able to print
out both the list as well as
the nodes within the list.
So how are you gonna submit this?
Well again,
you're gonna submit two things.
And you should feel free to submit,
either in isolation, but
really if you follow the process
that we're recommending here,
you should have completed your whole
MyLinkedList implementation at
the exact same time that you've completed
your whole MyLinkedList Testing.
To do this, what you'll do is
you go into the interface and
you'll go up to the submit button.
You'll go into My Submissions and
you'll create a new submission and
you'll notice that I've actually
done a whole bunch of tests here
in the process of creating your graders.
Anyway what you'll do is you'll do
an upload files and submit, and
you'll put in your linklist.java file.
You'll put in your mylink.tester file.
You'll submit these, and
after a brief time period,
you'll get back the graded results.
And I encourage you to, essentially,
if you don't get a full score, to look at
the grader output to figure, and it should
tell you essentially what went wrong.
You should also feel comfortable, though,
looking at the tester,
the greater code itself.
This is for the implementation,
and it'll essentially tell you
what tasks were performed.
So you should feel free to go into
the my linked list creator class and
look at what methods are being tested.
All right.
Good luck on the assignment.
If you have questions,
feel free to post in the forums and also
feel free to go back and review the videos
on how to write a MyLinkList test and
how to write good tests for MyLinkList.