[MUSIC]
Hi, my name is Robert.
And I remember this one time when I
was in a data structures class and
we had a programming assignment to
write our compression algorithms,
it was Huffman compression.
And we were all getting into it.
And I think because we'd done so
well on our previous assignments,
we wrote all of our code in a big rush
all together, no unit testing at all.
And when it all came together, we put in
the test cases, and it was all wrong.
We tried moving around
the different test cases, and
we couldn't see any pattern
about why everything was wrong.
We had reached that point
without any testing and we had
no confidence whatsoever that anything
we had written was actually correct.
So we had to completely tear down
our assignment from the bottom up,
and write tests, and actually get
confidence in each of our levels.
And now, since I've been coding for a
little bit longer, it seems kind of insane
not to write testing, but I definitely
didn't know that in the beginning,
and that caused me to struggle a lot.