[MUSIC]
All right, in our first module you were
introduced to the project that you're
going to be doing throughout this course.
And we hope that you think
it's as exciting as we do,
visualizing this geospatial data.
In this module though, we're going to
be stepping a little bit away, and
we're going to be talking
about some of the concepts
that underly the code that
you're going to be writing.
So, by the end of this module,
you're going to be able to motivate the
use of classes and objects in programming.
So, why do we want to use classes and
objects when we write our programs?
You'll be able to write classes in Java,
and then create instances,
or objects of those classes.
And you'll be able to describe
the parts of a class,
like member variables,
methods, and constructors.
So in order to motivate the use of
classes and objects in programming,
I want to go back to my favorite
definition of computer science.
And of course, software engineering and
software development,
which is what we're
focusing on this course and
this specialization,
is a major part of computer science.
So my favorite definition
of computer science is,
that computer science is the science of
using and processing large amounts of
information to automate useful tasks and
learn about the world around us.
Of course, all using a computer,
because none of this would be possible
if we didn't have the computational
power that the computer affords us.
I'm gonna zero in on this
line in the definition,
this idea of using large
amounts of information.
These programs that you're going to be
writing and programs that people write, if
you think about programs out in the world,
deal with huge amounts of information, so
much information it's almost
impossible to get your mind around it.
So one of the fundamental
questions in writing programs is,
how do we organize this information?
How do we organize it in a way such
that our programs are easy to write,
easy to maintain, and easy to debug?
Well the philosophy behind object oriented
program, object oriented programming, is
to build our programs in a way that match
the problem that we're trying to solve.
So if we go back to our project and
the problem we're trying to solve, it's
to visualize geospatial data on a map.
And if we think about what's
involved in solving that problem,
we can think of lots of
real-world objects and
entities that are part of this
problem that we're solving.
So we can think of things
like the map itself.
That's an object that
we're all familiar with.
Shapes.
Shapes are objects that have properties.
We could talk about the shapes of
the countries, for example, in this map.
Locations in the map,
colors of the objects in the map,
even the window in which
the map is displayed.
Plenty more objects as well, but
these are all ideas that have
real world counterparts.
And the idea behind writing
an object-oriented program to solve this
problem, is that we're going to structure
our code around these real-world concepts.
So in order to build our code in this way
that matches the real world, we're gonna
design these things called classes, and
what classes are, are just custom data
types that we get to define to match
the problem that we're trying to solve.
Now of course you're
familiar with classes,
cuz you've been working with Java for
some time now.
But we're gonna talk about really
the details of creating and using classes.
So a class is a new kind of data that
we the programmer get to define.
And it's kind of like a factory.
It can produce pieces of data with
a template that we get to define.
So I'm gonna use this factory icon
when I talk about class definitions.
On the other hand, an object is the thing
that comes out of this factory.
It's a piece of this data with this
custom type that we've defined.
And some associated functionality
that goes along with that data.
And I'll represent the objects with this
little symbol here to represent the things
that are coming out of the factory as
we create objects using our classes.
So you can think of this like
a real-world factory, right?
Like a car factory.
A car factory knows how to produce,
say, one kind of car.
And it can produce many
of that kind of car.
And once the cars are out in
the real world, well, at first,
they all kind of look the same, but
then each individual car can be
customized and it can be changed
in its own way without affecting all the
other cars that came out of the factory.
The same thing's going to happen for
our classes and
our objects in our Java programs.
So we're gonna go through
an example of creating a class.
And the class we're gonna
create has to do with this map
example that we've been working with.
So here's a map of the world.
I'm gonna zoom in on one
particular place in the world,
which is where this orange box is,
which is approximately where I'm standing
right now on the campus of UC San Diego.
So here's the University of California,
San Diego campus, and
I'm about right here on this map.
So what I want to do is,
I want to build a class that can represent
my location in the world, or can
represent anyone's location in the world.
So the question I have to ask myself is,
what do I need to know in
order to represent a location?
Well for this example, I'm going to
represent the concept of a location using
two pieces of data, the latitude and
the longitude of this location.
And in my case, for
this location right here,
you can see these approximately my
latitude and longitude coordinates.
So let's define a class that
represents this notion of a location.
Here's my class definition.
So I'm telling Java that I want
a new class called SimpleLocation.
And you can see that on the top
line in this declaration.
I say, public class SimpleLocation.
SimpleLocation is the name of the class.
The keyword class tells Java
that I'm creating a new class.
And public, which we'll talk about
more in some of the next videos.
Just means that my class
is public to the world.
Anyone can use it.
Inside, after that first curly brace,
is the definition of my class.
Now before we look closely at
the definition, I wanna point out that
all of this code has to exist in
a file called SimpleLocation.java.
That's just a rule that Java enforces.
That when you're creating a class, you
have to put it in a file that has the same
name as the class, and that's if
the class is public, which our class is.
So all this code is in a file
called SimpleLocation.java.
So let's look a little closely at
the definition for this class.
Up here you can see the data that I
have associated with my simple location.
I had a latitude and a longitude.
And I'll represent both of these
using double type variables.
These are what are called
member variables.
These are variables that exist throughout
the class that represent some essential
pieces of data that I need to represent
my simple location in this case.
And notice that they're declared
outside of any methods, but
inside the declaration of the class.
So, they come after that
open curly brace for
the class, but
not inside any particular method.
My class also has some
methods associated with it.
So it has, for example, that method
that you see down there at the bottom.
The distance method, and
what the distance method does is,
it takes some other simple location out in
the world as a parameter, and it returns
the distance between on simple location
and the simple location that's passed in.
So that's something that my class can do.
So these are the methods.
These are the things that my class can do.
And I want to zero in now on this
special method called the constructor.
So this is the constructor, and
this is a special method that gets
called when my objects get created.
So when I ask Java to give me a new
object of type SimpleLocation,
it's going to call this method here,
which is called the constructor.
And the reason you know
it's the constructor,
is that it doesn't have a return type,
so it simply says public and
then next word in the declaration of this
method is just the name of the class.
So public, SimpleLocation,
that's my constructor.
This constructor happens
to take two arguments.
And it takes the values of those
arguments that are passed in and
stores them away in those member
variables, latitude and longitude.
Now you might see this key word, this.
This dot latitude.
This dot longitude.
You might be wondering what is is.
We're gonna talk about that
in just a couple of minutes.
So all of this together is my
class declaration, SimpleLocation.
Class has two member variables and
couple of methods.
And again,
it's in the file SimpleLocation.java.
So now, how do I use this class?
Let's take a look at some
code that actually creates
objects of type simple locations and
does something with them.
So now I'm gonna go over into
a totally different file.
I'm gonna go into a file
called LocationTester.java.
Inside a totally different class, because
everything in Java has to be in a class,
and I'm gonna look at a main
method inside that class.
This main method is fairly simple.
It just has three lines of code.
And the first two lines
of code are creating
new objects of this type SimpleLocation,
the class that I just wrote.
So, you can see here that I declare
two new variables, ucsd and lima.
And I'm creating two new
SimpleLocation objects
to represent the location of where
I'm standing here at UC San Diego.
And then the location of Lima, Peru.
When I call new, and
then say SimpleLocation, and
then have the parentheses
in passing those arguments.
What that's doing is, that's going over
into the SimpleLocation class definition
and calling the constructor.
So those arguments you saw being passed
in, those are gonna go in as arguments.
To this constructor,
which is going to store those values away
inside the object that just got created.
So I call the constructor twice,
I get two new objects.
Then I can use those objects in
some code like I do down here.
So, what I'm doing here is,
I'm taking my ucsd SimpleLocation object.
And I'm calling the distance method on it,
passing it in the SimpleLocation object
that represents the location of Lima.
So let's take a look at how that works.
When I call that method,
it's going to invoke this method distance
that's inside the class SimpleLocation.
All right.
So
let's look in a little bit more
detail what's going on here, so
we can understand the difference
between UCSD and Lima.
So when I call ucsd.distance and
pass in the parameter lima, like I
mentioned before, it invokes that method
called distance inside the SimpleLocation
class, which you can see right here.
Now I'm showing you just a little bit of
what the body of that method might look
like, so
that I can illustrate a couple of points.
We're comparing the distance
between two SimpleLocation objects.
One of those objects, lima, is past in
as an argument to the function, and
that's gonna be stored in the parameter,
other.
So I can see that other is used
inside the body of the method
when I get its latitude and its longitude.
But what happened to ucsd?
How are we getting the latitude and
longitude of ucsd?
That's where the keyword, this, comes in.
This refers to the calling object, which
is the object that called the method,
or on which the method was called.
So in this line of code, ucsd dot
distance and then pass in lima UCSD
is called the calling object because it's
the object that occurs before that dot.
So when I'm inside this method,
this will refer to the location of UCSD.
So that way I can get the latitude and
longitude of where I'm standing
here at UCSD, and compare it to
the latitude and longitude of Lima, Peru.
and return the distance.
Putting it all together,
when I run this code by compiling it and
running it, I see that distance between
where I'm standing now, and Lima, Peru,
is approximately 6,568 kilometers.
So those are some objects basics.
In the next couple videos, we'll introduce
you to some more subtle details and
interesting things you can do when
creating classes and objects.