[MUSIC]
All right, so when I was first learning
about objects, I was taking this class and
the professor was at the front of
the room talking to us about objects.
And he kept saying objects this and
objects that, and
I just kept getting more and
more confused.
I'm sitting there thinking,
objects, they're like things.
But, what the heck is an object?
And finally, I got up the nerve to
raise my hand and ask the professor,
what is an object?
And he kind of looked at me with this look
on his face like, oh dear, where have I
gone wrong with this poor student that
she doesn't know what an object is?
But he was very patient with me,
explained what an object is, and after he
explained it, I realized that I actually
knew more about objects than I thought.
I just hadn't necessarily associated
the word object with the concept that I
already knew a fair amount about.
So that was kind of an example
of vocabulary tripping me up.
And as I learned a little bit more, and
got more sophisticated with designing and
implementing objects,
it all made more sense.
I look back now, and I wonder how
I could have possibly struggled
with something that seems so
simple to me now.
But that's how it is when
you're first starting out.