Okay, now that you know the basics
of creating classes and
objects in Java, let's talk about
overloading methods which is another thing
that you're going to do and work with a
lot as you work with classes and objects.
So by the end of this video you'll be
able to give examples of what overloading
methods is in Java.
You'll be able to explain how to overload
methods, and how not to overload methods
in Java, and you'll be able to explain
why it's useful and why we wanna do it.
Let's go back to our simple location
class that we worked with last video.
So we saw this class, here it is,
it has a couple of member variables.
It has a constructor, and
it has a method called, distance.
Of course, you know by now that it must
be in a file called, SimpleLocation.java.
Now let's say right now we have one
constrictor, it allows the user to
create objects of type simple location
by passing in a latitude and longitude.
But let's say that the user doesn't want
to always have to pass in a latitude and
longitude and, they want to be
able to create SimpleLocation
objects without passing in any parameters.
Right now,
the user of our class can't do that
because there's no constructor
defined that takes no parameters.
But we can fix that.
We can create a new constructor
that takes no parameters, and
create still a new simple location object.
Now, you might wonder, well where
should this simple location object be
if the user doesn't
give us any parameters.
And since I'm here at UC San Diego,
I'm gonna create my class that will always
create simple location objects here at my
location at UC San Diego unless the user
tells me to create it somewhere else.
So what I've done is I've added a new
constructor that takes no arguments which,
by the way,
is called the default constructor.
It's just the constructor that you can
invoke without passing in any data at all.
And it will give my parameters, a sorry,
it will give my number variables,
latitude and longitude,
these default values, which is the
location of where I'm standing right now.
I still have my other constructor,
which takes the two arguments,
latitude and longitude, lat and lon, and
those two constructors can exist
happily together in the same class.
This is exactly what I'm talking about
when I talk about overloading methods.
So I've now created a class where
my constructor has been overloaded.
There are two different copies of the
constructor that take different numbers
and types of arguments.
They both do the same thing more or less
in that they both create a new object, but
how they assign values to latitude and
longitude differ slightly.
So I can not only overload constructors, I
can also overload the methods in my class.
So before I had one method
called distance, and
it took in as a parameter
another SimpleLocation object.
And, that was fine, but maybe I don't want
to force the user of my class to have to
create a whole SimpleLocation object just
to find the distance to another location.
So, I can overload the distance method
by creating another version of it
that takes in two parameters other lat and
other lon.
So instead of having to create a whole new
SimpleLocation object just to pass it into
the distance function, the user of my
class can now call my distance method
by passing in two parameters,
representing the latitude and
longitude of the place that they're
trying to find the distance to.
So two examples of overloading.
Why do we care about overloading?
Why is this useful?
Let's take a look at how you're gonna
use it extensively in your project.
So this is a little snippet of code that
we looked at back in module one that uses
this UnfoldingMaps library to create
a new map and display it to the user.
And what it does is it creates
a window of size 800 by 600 and
then puts a new map inside that window.
And when I run it I see
something like this.
I've also created, I've added a line
of code that zooms in on San Diego so
you see San Diego rather
than the whole world.
So that's what I see when I run this code.
But what if I decide that I don't
really like the fact that the map
takes up the whole window, I'd like
to shrink the map down slightly so
there's a nice border
around the edge of the map.
I can do that.
And I can do that by invoking a different
version of the UnfoldingMaps constructor.
So this is an overloaded version
of the UnfoldingMap constructor
that takes four additional parameters.
So my original call to UnfoldingMap
just took two parameters.
Now I'm calling the,
the UnfoldingMap constructor
that takes six parameters total.
And these four additional parameters
I've added specify the x and
y position of where the map should appear
in the window, as well as the width and
height of the map.
So when I run this code, what I see
is a window that has a nice border
around the map that it displays, because
the map is smaller than the window size.
So this is pretty useful, but
you might wonder, well how do I even know?
How do I know what constructors
are available to me?
That's where the Java
documentation comes in.
So you can go to the UnfoldingMap Java doc
just like we showed you in module one and
you'll see all the constructors
detailed there.
So here's the first constructor we
called that took two parameters and
you can see what it does and
what those parameters are.
And here's that second constructor that we
called that took those six parameters and
you can see that the second
parameter's the x position of the map,
the third parameter's the y position
of the map, and so on and so forth.
And if you do go to
the unfolding map documentation,
which I encourage you to do right now,
you'll see that there are actually like
eight or nine different overloaded
constructors for UnfoldingMap.
So you can create unfolding map objects
by passing it a wide variety of
information and each of those constructors
will do something slightly different.
So before we end this video,
I want to caution you
against something that seems really useful
but is actually not possible in Java.
So you might think that it's a good
idea to overload the distance method
instead of by changing the parameter list,
by changing the return type.
So let's say you want a distance method
that returns a double type, but you also
want a distance method that's slightly
less precise and returns an integer type.
So you say, oh,
I'll just overload the distance method and
make the other one return an integer.
Unfortunately that is not allowed,
you can't do that, java will complain.
You have to have some difference in the
parameter list when you overload a method.
You're not allowed to have
a method with the same name,
and the same parameter list,
and a different return type.
And the reason for that is a little bit
beyond the scope of this course, but
it has to do with how the compiler works.
At compile time, Java C,
the compiler, has to decide
which version of the overloaded method
you're actually trying to call.
And it does that by using
the parameter list.
It can't do that by using
the return type alone.
So Java doesn't let you do
this type of overloading.
So that's all for overloading and
in the next video,
we'll talk about a few more
details of objects and classes.