[MUSIC]
Okay, in this next video we'll layer on
some more details of building classes
in Java.
We're gonna talk about the keywords public
and private and protecting your data and
methods inside your classes.
So by the end of this video you'll be able
to describe what those keywords mean and
their effect on who can access the data
and methods inside your classes.
And you'll be able to also talk
about how to use getters and
setters to allow customized access
to the data inside of your classes.
So as usual,
we're gonna go back to the SimpleLocation
class that we've been developing.
So these class, as you know, has two
member variables, latitude and longitude.
And we originally declared
them both to be public.
So let's take a closer
look at what that means.
What that means is that anyone can
access these member variables from
any class at all.
So when I create a new object
of type SimpleLocation,
I can get at the member
variable latitude or
the member variable longitude to read
its value or to change its value.
So if I go over here into
the LocationTester class,
I see that I've created two
new SimpleLocation objects.
I can change the value of latitude
inside the object stored in lima.
That's totally okay, because that member
variable is declared to be public.
So I can access it from anywhere.
Similarly for methods, I've declared
my method distance to be public.
Which means that I can
access that method anywhere.
So over here, back in my LocationTester
class I'm calling the distance method,
which is also totally allowed because
again, that method is public.
On the other hand, if I were to
declare my member variables private,
what that would mean is that those
variables would only be accessible
from within the SimpleLocation
class itself.
So only inside this class definition.
Nowhere else.
No one else has access to either read or
write those variables.
Same thing goes for methods.
If I make a method private,
I can only call that method within
the class I'm defining, and nowhere else.
So, if we look at what that means,
if we look at this constructor,
these two lines of code are just fine.
I'm using this.latitude to access
the member variable latitude and
this.longitude to access
the member variable longitude.
Perfectly okay because I'm
inside the class SimpleLocation.
However, if I go back to that
class LocationTester, and
look at this line here that's trying
to change the value of latitude in
the SimpleLocation stored in the variable
lima, that's no longer allowed.
Because now I've said that that
latitude variable is private.
It can only be accessed from
within the SimpleLocation class.
And we're no longer in
the SimpleLocation class.
We're now over here in the main method,
inside LocationTester.
So that would cause an error.
So, it's actually,
despite this error that just got caused,
it's actually a good idea to make
your member variables private.
Because you as the class designer
want to really have ultimate control
over who gets to see and
change the data that's stored in each
object of the class that you're creating.
So as a rule of thumb,
always make your member variables private.
Now methods can either be public or
private, depending on whether they're for
world use, like the distance method.
Or whether they're maybe just helper
methods that are designed to be used only
within that class itself.
We'll talk more about that as we start
talking about more sophisticated
class design.
But, for now, let's focus on this rule
of thumb that we should make our member
variables private.
So, if our member variables are private,
nobody else can access them.
They can't see their values,
they can't change them.
So, that seems like a bit of a problem.
We probably sometimes want to
give a little bit more access
to the member variables
in our class than that.
So the way we get around that problem is
through the use of what are called getters
and setters.
So this is an example right here of a
getter, and the purpose of a getter is to
take the value of a member
variable that's private and
expose it outside of that class.
So you can see this getter here gets
the value of the member variable latitude,
which is private, and
returns it to the outside world.
So the variable itself
is still private but
now I can gain access to that
variable by calling this getter.
So if we go back over here to the code,
we can see that if I try to
access the variable directly say,
print it out I get an error, but
when I call that getter method,
that's perfectly fine.
So I can actually get access to
the value of that latitude variable
through the getter.
And now notice that in this code so far,
going back here, I haven't provided my
user of my class with any way to actually
set or change the value of latitude.
And that may be what I intend as the class
designer, that once that latitude variable
gets set in the constructor, I may
never want anybody to change it again.
And in that case,
I would just simply provide a getter and
not provide any way for the user to
change the value of the variable.
But, let's say I actually do
want to allow somebody to
change the value of the variable.
In that case I would provide
what's called a setter.
So, here's my setter.
What it does is it takes in a value, lat,
and it changes the value of the private
member variable to the value
that was passed in by the user.
So a setter sets the value
of our member variable,
usually a private member variable.
So now I've got a getter and
a setter for my latitude variable.
And you might be thinking,
I would be thinking if I were you,
why didn't we just make that
member variable public?
If we're exposing
the ability to change it and
read it, we might as well
just make it public, right?
So here's why, having the getter and
the setter allows us more
control as class designers.
So let's say we want to allow the user
to change the value of the latitude.
But we're little bit unsure that the user
of our class will know what they're doing
when it comes to legal latitude values.
So we can put some precautions in place
that allow the user to change the value of
that latitude, but only to values
that are legal latitude values.
So the way we would do this is we would
modify our setter to rather than just
blindly accepting whatever argument was
passed in, we would have some checks,
some logic inside of that method
that said okay, if it's out
of range of -180 to 180 then
that's not a legal value.
So we're gonna print out an error,
inform the user of our class that,
hey, you tried to set your latitude
variable to an illegal value.
That's probably some bug in your code, so
you should probably go check that out.
And not change the value that's
stored in the latitude variable.
Otherwise, we can happily accept the value
because it's within the legal range and
change the value of that variable.
All right, so that's it for
the details of classes and objects.
You now know all the basics of
creating classes and objects.
Next you'll take a short practice quiz and
then move on to the next module.