[MUSIC]
All right, so
it's time to get started on your project.
In this project, there are two parts.
The first, you're gonna write some
code to sort the earthquake data.
And the second part, where we think you're
gonna have a lot of fun, is to add your
own extension to this whole project that
you've created throughout this course.
So before we talk about what
you're actually going to do for
the programming assignment, let me say a
few words about how you're going to submit
this programming assignment.
It's a little bit different
from previous modules.
So if you go over here to
Week View on Coursera,
these are the things you're learning this
week, and down here at the bottom is,
of course, the Check Your Knowledge
lesson, which is the last lesson.
Just like it is in every assignment, and
right now you're watching
the Programming Assignment Walkthrough.
Of course coming next,
the Programming Assignment Instructions,
which I'm going over in this video, but
let me talk to you about how you're
going to submit the assignment.
So as usual, what you'll do is, you'll do
a quiz, just like in previous modules,
to check your understanding
of the concepts.
And to make sure you've actually done
the programming assignment correctly.
But in this module,
you're gonna have an extra piece.
Rather than just taking a quiz,
we're actually going to ask you to submit
a peer-review assignment talking about
part of your programming assignment for
this module.
So, what's a little weird is you're going
to see two peer-review assignments,
and they're right next to each other.
So you can see one right here and
the other right there.
One of them has a due date, meaning that's
the one that's actually due for a grade.
The other one that you see right
before it, this one is just basically
a non-graded,
an optional peer review assignment, and
it's actually identical to the graded
version of the peer-review assignment.
Now, you may be wondering, why do we have
an optional version of the assignment
that's identical to the sort of
required version of the assignment?
And the reason for this is that we
want you to be able to get preliminary
feedback from your peers
in a quick turnaround.
So that you can get some feedback to
incorporate into the submission that
you ultimately submit for a grade.
So this version, this ungraded
peer assignment, is optional.
But you can use it to submit
your peer-review assignment and
get some quick feedback from your peers,
make some improvements on your
peer-review assignment, and then
submit it for a grade by the due date.
So now that we've looked at how you're
going to submit your programming
assignment in this module,
let's go back and
take a look at what you're
actually going to do.
So, the first steps are the usual steps.
We want you to find
an open starter code and
take a look at it, then we're asking you
to compare our implementation to yours,
and this is really more
of a reflective question.
How does what we did in the module five
implementation compare to your module
five implementation?
Be ready to reflect on that in the quiz.
The next part, you're going to be
implementing the code to sort.
So the first step says to implement the
comparable interface in Earthquake Marker.
So we go over here to
the Earthquake Marker file, and you can
see that there's a to-do in here that
says, implement the comparable interface.
And so
you need to figure out what that means,
how do we change the class header so that
it implements the comparable interface?
And then, of course, there's a second part
to implement to the comparable interface
which is to implement all
the methods in the interface.
In this case it's just this one method,
compareTo.
And you'll see a TODO down here as well.
And remember the compareTo compares
the calling object Earthquake Marker,
to the parameter EarthquakeMarker.
And returns either a negative value,
zero, or
a positive value depending on the
relationship between those two objects.
And it's gonna be up to you to figure
out how to do the comparison and
return the correct value so that you get
your earthquakes sorted in reverse order.
All right, and then the second half of
that piece is to implement this method in
EarthquakeCityMap, so we go back
over here to EarthquakeCityMap, and
you'll be implementing a method.
You can click here to this little TODO.
We're gonna implement this
method sortAndPrint, and
that takes a parameter, the number
of earthquakes we want to print, and
it's going to print out the earthquakes
in reverse order of their magnitude.
So it's gonna be strongest magnitude
first and then weaker and weaker.
So you're gonna implement
that method here, and
then you'll wanna call it
from the setup method.
So you'll be adding your call
somewhere in here in the setup method.
Then you can see here that the second part
of the project, the main second part,
is to add your own extension.
So this is where we want you to get
creative, have a lot of fun, and in case
you don't have any ideas, we hope you have
some ideas, but if you don't, that's okay.
We have some ideas to
seed your creativity.
So there are two kind of major
directions you could take this in.
You could extend the functionality
of your earthquake application, so
continue to work with the earthquake data.
And you're all set up for that.
And we've got a number of
different suggestions here
that you might choose to implement.
And then the other direction
you could take is you could
incorporate new data sources.
So we have a couple of new kinds
of data already prepared for you.
So one is airport and
airline root data that you can find over
here if you go here into the data
directory back in Eclipse you
can see that we've got this airports.dat,
and then we have a routes.dat file.
And we're also providing you with some
code that will give you a demo of this, so
we've got this AirportMap and
AirportMarker so
you can get a sense of how
to use those data files.
So you can work with that data source or
you can work with data
from the World Bank.
We've got the life expectancy data that
Mia showed you way back in module,
the first module on GUIs.
And we've got some sample code
that implements, basically,
the example that she implemented
from that module, and
you'll find that over here in
the lifeexpectancy.java file.
So, decide which direction you wanna take,
decide what you wanna do, play around,
have a lot of fun, and then after this,
what you're gonna do is you're
going to be submitting this.
In addition to taking the quiz,
you'll be submitting this as
a graded peer review assignment.
So you can see,
you'll get to see what all your fellow
MOOC mates have done with this project.
So have fun and we really look
forward to seeing your extensions.