[MUSIC]
Congratulations on completing our course.
You've created a large project and
I hope you enjoyed it.
>> Think back to everything
you've learned in this course.
You've learned about object
oriented programming.
You've worked with class hierarchies,
inheritance, and polymorphism.
And you've created an interactive
graphical user interface.
We hope you're really
proud of your project.
>> And we hope you'll join us for
the second course as well.
We'll be thinking about the performance
of the programs that we build.
And we'll be incorporating data structures
as the programs get even more complicated
and interesting.
So we hope to see you there.