[MUSIC]
This video is a walk-through of
the Programming Assignment for Module 3,
Part 2,
which is the Markov Text Generator.
And again, this assignment should be
a fair amount of fun because essentially
when you're done with this you're gonna be
able to generate random texts which look
a lot like original source text.
And I've had a lot of fun
playing with this myself.
To do this what you're gonna do is,
just like all the previous assignments,
make sure that you have the starting code.
So here is the startup code
that we've provided to you.
The two files that we're gonna focus
on are the MarkovTextGenerator.java and
then MarkovTextGeneratorLoL.java file,
or LoL file.
So what you'll notice initially is that
the MarkovTextGenerator is actually
an interface, and the interface just
requires that you implement three methods.
The train method, which is
essentially given some source text,
train my MarkovTextGenerator
based on the source text.
The second is the generateText method,
which is what you're gonna call if you
wanna generate say 50 words, and get back
some random text that looks like this.
The last method is, you should be able to
retrain your generator from scratch, and
base in some new source text.
So, all you're gonna have to is implement
those three methods within your
MarkovTextGeneratorLoL class for
this to work properly.
So if you look at your
MarkovTextGeneratorLoL class,
you'll find that what it has is a three
instance variables that I want to point
out real quickly.
The first is,
it's gonna have a list of list nodes.
I'll show you what a list node
looks like here in just a moment.
And this is why it's
called a list of list,
because each of the ListNodes is actually
gonna have a list within itself.
You wanna have essentially
a starting word which says
at what word should we start with
when we wanna generate some new text.
And then lastly you're gonna have
random generator that's past you.
We already wrote
the MarkovTextGeneratorLoL constructor for
you, which takes in a random generator,
hooks that up right here,
and also sets up your word list
via a linked list of list nodes
as well as to set your starter
string to be the empty string.
Now you may ask but why am I taking in
a random generator as per the constructor?
And the reason for
that is to help with testing.
If you take in a random generator
that is seeded with a value, say 10,
it will always produce the same
random numbers after that.
And that's quite useful for testing.
And you'll find this useful
when you test your own code.
As you'd expect because this
is implementing the Markov
text generator interface.
It's got a train method
a generate text method.
And it's also got a retrain method.
You'll notice that we've also
given you a two-string method
to essentially help print out this
list when you're debugging it.
We've also given you a main method which
does some primary tests and you should
feel free to use this however you feel
fit in terms of testing your own code.
Lastly, we've given you a list node itself
and a list node, I'll show you a graphic
for this in a moment, contains a word
which is the word in the original source
text, along with all of the possible words
that follow that and that, of course,
is going to have to be a list
because you can have more than one
word Have falling each
original word in the text.
And we already set up an instructor for
this, we already created a getter method,
we also created a method that lets you
to add additional words to this list.
And we've also given you
a two-string method,
and again a two string method is for
testing.
What we haven't given you
is a getRandomNextWord.
And this is where you're gonna have
to produce a single random next word.
So your MarkovTextGenerator class
is gonna call your linked list node
object's getRandomNextWord method and
it should give you back a random word,
that follows this.
And again, I'll show you some
graphics of this in just a moment.
But this is essentially the code
that you have to start with.
So again, I encourage you to
look first at the starter code,
go through the code itself.
Look at the train method,
the journey text method.
The retrain methods and see what you
need to implement for this assignment.
After you have done that I encourage you
to read this write correctly we've given
you the algorithms that you will need
to implement as part of this write up.
If you want an extra added challenge
go head and skip these parts and
try to do this on your own but
I do encourage you to look at the
algorithms if you want that extra help.
So the algorithms you're gonna be
implementing are actually fairly well
defined.
First, the train method.
So to train,
you're gonna take an imput text and
you're gonna generate a data
structure that's gonna help you
perform the MarkovTextGenerator
based on that imput text.
And you can see that, I have the algorithm
essentially outlined right here.
What I wanna show you is essentially
the output of the data structure.
So if you were to train on the phrase,
hi there,
hi Leo, what you'd end up with is
three nodes in your list of lists.
The first node would have the word hi.
That's the start word, and there's two
possible words that follow from hi.
As you can tell from the original text,
there was hi there, so there is included.
There's also hi Leo, so Leo is included.
So, if you have the word, hi,
you potentially generate
either the words there or Leo.
The word there is only followed
by the word hi in this text.
So, if you produce the word there,
the only word that can follow it,
again, is hi.
And the last node to focus
on is the node for Leo.
So there are no words to follow
Leo in this initial text.
Let's make your generate
text method easier,
what you're gonna do is have it followed
by the very first work in the text.
So, when you hit the word Leo,
you're gonna make sure that it's
followed by the very first word.
Now if Leo had appeared multiple
times in this text already,
again you'd still wanna pan
the word hi to make sure
that it could have been eventually
start over without the very first word.
So your goal for the train method is
essentially produce this data structure.
And what we've given you again is a method
that allows you to print out the output.
So, if you train on hi there, hi Leo,
what you want then is when you
print it is to get this output.
The second step, and I encourage you to
heavily test your train method before
you move on to the generate text method.
Well, once you've tested your code
carefully for train, move on to
generate text and what you'll do is again
follow the algorithm that we've given you.
And let me go back up to
our visual representation.
And the idea for generating text is
essentially start with the start word,
which is hi, and
then pick one of the possible words.
And you're gonna use a random number
to essentially pick which one that
you wanna use.
So you'll pick hi initially because it's
the first word, it's the starter word.
And then you'll randomly select one.
Let's say we pick the word bear.
So, we're gonna go there.
There can only produce the word, hi.
So you're gonna print hi and there,
you're back at the high note.
So, hi can produce either there or Leo,
and let's say we randomly now select Leo.
So, got a Leo, Leo can only produce hi.
We're back to hi, and
we just continue this process for
as many words as the user has asked for.
Again, if you want more details,
the algorithm is provided right here.
Last step is to do retrain.
So retrain is going to look a lot like the
train method its just that you're going to
have to clear out the data structures
that you've already created and
just start over again.
So retrain is basically just
train except that you discard
the train that you already had.
So some hint's,
you're almost only gonna really use that
two string method both within the list and
within each node when you're trying
to test and debug what's going on.
The second is I encourage you
to train on small inputs and
then draw your expected list of lists
by hand before you run the code itself.
And then run the code and
see if it actually generates that
list of lists that you inspected.
This kinda very careful debugging
process is gonna be incredibly valuable
in terms of solving this
project efficiently.
When you pick a random next word, there
are a couple of things that can go wrong.
The first is you wanna make sure that
you can produce all possible words.
So, if your current word
could produce hi there or
this, make sure that you can produce all
of those, by running essentially a large
enough generate text that
you see all of them occur.
Really common bugs are to
omit ever outputting hi or
this, just in terms of which
one you pick randomly.
The other thing to focus on when you're
generating random words is to recognize
that you should be able to
repeat words in your list.
For example, if your word is
followed by the word hi, and
then it's followed again by the word
hi later in this source text.
And it's followed again by the word
hi 'later in the source text and
then it's followed by the word
hello in the source text.
Your list should actually contain hi,
hi, hi, and hello.
And the reason for this is because you
wanna make sure that hi gets generated
more commonly, than the word hello does.
And the way you're going to test this
again, is to generate a large enough
segment of text that you can make
sure that the word in question here
generates hi following it more often
than it generates hello following it.
And if you generate next word
methods working properly,
it will do this just fine.
When you're all done writing you
MarkovTextGenerator class and
testing it, you're gonna upload this
to our servers for automated testing.
And just like the previous one,
you'll go to my submission, you'll
notice that I've already been doing some
testing in terms of testing the graders.
You'll go to create submissioa And
you will
upload your MarkovTextGeneratorLoL.java
file and you'll submit it.
And then if you get a full score grade,
if you miss some test cases
that's not a big deal at all.
The grader output should tell you
the things that you missed, but
if you're still unclear on it feel free
to go back into the original source code
pull up, MarkovTextGeneratorGrader,
and you'll see the test that we run.
And you'll get a better feel for
what we're testing and
then you'll be able to fix your code.
It's almost certain you'll have a couple
of bugs in your code the first time
around, and that's totally fine.
Once you fix your code, keep
submitting until you get a full score.
And again, I encourage you,
as you're working on this project,
to always feel free to go back to
the videos on MarkovTextGenerator.
If you have any questions,
post in the forums.
Good luck.