[MUSIC]
As in the previous walk throughs,
it's a good idea to make sure you watch
the overview video before
you walk through this one.
The review video, again,
gives you the high-level picture of what
is being asked of you for this project.
So let's just dive right
into the write up.
In this programming exam, we're gonna be
adding new features just like we did for
module three.
It's a good idea to make sure you
read through the learning outcomes,
as well as the introduction.
Again, just like in the last module,
make sure you have these two
references open when you're working.
So what are you gonna do for
this assignment?
First is you're gonna make sure you
find and open up the starter code.
So here's our starter code for
module four right over here.
And you're gonna notice we
have five classes in here.
So that's kind of your first step.
Open up these files and
you may wanna check to see what
the relationship is between them.
So for example, EarthquakeCityMap.
It sends p applet,
just like it did before.
But you'll notice that city marker
is gonna extend simple point marker
and so on.
It's a good idea to walk through those, so
you can figure out the class hierarchy.
In the next step, you're gonna
want a trace to the store code,
predict what happens when you run it and
then run it.
Now, notice that we've made some changes
to the code from the previous assignment.
So you're gonna wanna make sure that
you identify what those changes are.
The next major step is
implement the IsLand method in
the EarthquakeCityMap class.
So let's go to EarthquakeCityMap,
you scroll down for awhile.
You're gonna find there is
a earthquake surround even more,
your gonna find the IsLand method.
The reason we're gonna use this is for
this next step in the assignment,
where you're trying to
figure out whether or
not an earthquake occurred in land or
under the oceans.
And if it did occur in the land, you're
going to know what country it occurred in.
And the good news is
we've given you a method,
a little bit further
down called IsInCountry.
So this is gonna allow you to essentially
check is my earthquake occurring in this
country in the process of checking that,
it's actually gonna set that property
of the country that it's part of.
So if it is actually inside that country,
it'll set that earthquake to be
attached essentially to that country.
You'll wanna use that in a future step.
So you wanna use this method IsInCountry
within your IsLand method.
The next step is to implement
your printQuakes method.
The idea for the printQuakes method is
to print out all the earthquakes that
occurred in each country, as long as
there's at least one earthquake in that
country and then also print out how
many earthquakes occurred in the ocean.
You're gonna wanna use that
country property that's
attached to earthquakes
to help solve this.
The next step after you have coded
these is just like any piece of code,
you're going to test it to make
sure it's working properly.
So the way to test this is we have
given you two tester input files called
testonediadem and testtwodiadem and you
can essentially just use those test cases
to make sure you get the right output.
I'm giving you the test1.out.text and
text2.out.text is essentially
the right answers to verify against.
If your printQuake method and
your IsLand method are working properly,
this should work just fine.
Your next step is to draw
a UML class hierarchy.
As I was showing you just before,
you can always look in say,
EarthquakeMarker to figure out.
Go back to your code, look in
EarthquakeMarker and see where it extends.
So this extends a simple point marker.
And we know a simple point marker,
if you look in the documentation
extends for marker.
So this is the way you're essentially
going to piece this all together with
the class you'll know
hierarchy looks like.
The next step is to complete
the method definition for
the draw method within
your CityMarker class.
We're gonna wanna add all
of the cities to the map.
So this is essentially
our goal at this point.
And to do this, you're gonna
go into your CityMarker class.
You're gonna find the draw method and
you're gonna find that there's
a big TODO which says,
this is where you're gonna want to draw
a triangle to represent the CityMarker.
To draw a triangle and then you have to
think about where is the center location,
which is denoted by this x and this y?
And how will I draw a triangle
essentially around that?
Your next step in the project is gonna
be completing the method definitions for
drawEarthquake in
the LandQuakeMarker class and
the OceanQuakeMarker class.
Notice that if you go
into EarthQuakeMarker,
there is a drawEarthquake method,
that's an abstract method.
So this is a method that you're gonna have
to override within the derived classes.
So both LandQuakeMarker and
OceanQuakeMarker have
to have these methods.
They already have them, but
they're essentially stubs.
They don't do anything yet.
So if you want to drawEarthquakes, you're
gonna add the code to draw a circle,
if you're in the LandQuakeMarker class.
For the OceanQuakeMarker class,
you wanna add the code to draw a square.
Your next step is going to be
completing the color determine
method within the EarthquakeMarker class.
Let's look real quickly though, at where
that's called and then what it's gonna do.
So if we pull-up our code for
EarthquakeMarker,
we have a method called draw.
So this is what the EarthquakeMarker
is gonna look like and
it essentially does a few steps.
It's going to call this
colorDetermine method,
which we know we have to write for
this step.
And then it calls it drawEarthquake
method, which we wrote for
the previous step.
So let's look in
the colorDetermine method.
Within the colorDetermine method,
we don't have any code yet.
So what we wanna do here is figure out
whether or not it should be red, blue or
yellow and these are the colors we suggest
based on the depth of the earthquake.
If you're curious to figure
out how to figure out depth,
notice there's a bunch of helper methods
within EarthquakeMarker class that
are gonna be useful to you from getting
the magnitude, to getting the depths.
Now we're gonna talk real quickly
about why we laid this out this way?
So you have your draw method
in the EarthquakeMarker class,
which is the parent class of both
LandQuakeMarker and OceanQuakeMarker.
Because you're gonna mark and determine
the color to be red, green or blue
regardless of whether or not, it's a Land
or an OceanQuakeMarker, it actually makes
sense to put this color determination call
in the parent class and define it there.
If you try to put it in the subclasses,
LandQuakeMarker or OceanQuakeMarker,
you just write the same code twice and
that doesn't make any sense.
Back to our steps.
We are almost done at this point.
If you want,
you can add this extra feature,
which is a check to see if
the earthquake has occurred recently.
And if it has, then you will
want to draw these kind of Xs.
And the place you will wanna do that
is actually, we scrolled right past it.
If you wanna check to see right here,
right after drawEarthquake, whether or
not it's occurred in the last day.
If it has occurred within the past day,
you'll wanna put an X.
I hope these steps help you get started.
As always with these projects, you'll
wanna work through this step by step.
So go right back up to step one and
start working through.
You wanna read this fairly carefully,
because we've tried to give you
the necessary details to solve that
part of the problem in text right here.
If you do run into problems though,
feel free to review the videos,
check the forums.
And again, try to have fun.