[MUSIC]
In the project for this module,
we'll be going further with our graphing
of earthquakes onto the world map.
The past assignment was really neat.
You displayed earthquakes on a map, and
had their appearance determined by
the magnitude of the earthquake.
But knowing the magnitude of
the earthquake alone, isn't really enough
information to understand
the potential impact of that event.
So we'll be going further with
this idea in this module by making
the earthquakes appear differently based
on the location of the earthquake,
the depth of the earthquake, and
optionally the age of the earthquake.
But we'll continue to visualize the
magnitude of the earthquake as the size
of the marker.
So there's a number of steps
to this assignment, but
let's try to break it down
to four high level goals.
The first goal is to add markers for
major cities.
If you don't see your city here,
please feel free to add it.
The second is to figure out if
the earthquakes occurred in the land, and
if so, occurred in which country.
Then, you want to draw the earthquakes
differently if they occurred in the land
or in the sea.
And you'll again change the size of
the earthquake, based on its magnitude.
Now, where earthquakes occur matters.
As the threat they pose is affected by
whether or not they're under water and
could cause a tsunami.
Or if they're on land and could cause
physical damage to surrounding areas.
The third goal is to change
the color of the marker
based on how deep the earthquake occurred.
Again, the depth of the earthquake changes
its potential impact to surrounding areas.
Lastly, as an optional goal,
you can add an X to the earthquakes,
which occurred in the past day.
To accomplish these goals we are using
features of both inheritance and
polymorphism in Java.
So be sure to check out the videos on
these topics if you are unfamiliar or
uncomfortable with those ideas.
This is one of my favorite
parts of the project.
I hope you'll enjoy it too.