[MUSIC]
Hey everybody.
In this video,
we're gonna learn about the programming
assignment associated with week three.
Now there's two pieces to
this programming assignment,
the first is creating your
own linked LinkedList.
And the second part of it,
is creating Markov Text Generator.
I just wanna show what you're
gonna do with each of these.
So, the first part, creating a LinkedList
is an interesting assignment.
And the reason it's interesting is because
this kind of already exists in Java.
So if you look at the list
interface in the Java Docs,
you'll notice that it has a number of
features which are useful to programmers.
In fact, you've almost certainly
used the list interface already.
Now, there is a LinkList implementation
of the list interface and
this is provided by Java.
So there's a bit of a question.
Why then should you code
a LinkList yourself?
Well the reason why is that LinkedList
are a core data structure and
they're also a linked data structure.
And we're gonna be doing a whole
bunch with the linked data structures
as we go forward through this course and
even into the next course.
LinkedList is a great place to
start when trying to write your own
linked data structure.
So what you're gonna do is you're
gonna create your own LinkedList and
it's gonna have many of the features that
the Java implementational LinkedList has.
The second reason why we're gonna write a
LinkedList yourself is because we're gonna
learn about testing in this week.
Mainly, how do you do unit tests and
why are they so important.
What we're gonna do is apply this
knowledge of how to do testing to
essentially test your LinkList interface.
And you'll also run your test against,
essentially,
a whole sweep of LinkLists,
which are either correctly or
incorrectly written as part of
the grading for the assignment.
The second part of the assignment
is actually really fun.
So, what I have here in our interface, and
I hope you've got this all running at this
point, is I've just typed in some text.
And all I wrote in was this is a test.
This is a video.
This video is cool.
Now, what Markov Text Generation
does is it creates text
that's artificial but
it looks similar to the original text.
So, let's just do this.
I'll show you what it looks like.
I'm gonna generate Markov Text.
I'm gonna use, creates say 50 words worth.
And what it produces is text that
looks really similar to that original.
But it's not quite the same.
I wanna highlight a couple
of these phrases in here,
that shows you that this isn't doing
exactly what you may think it does.
So, if you look at the original text,
there's nowhere in the original
text that says this is cool.
To create this is cool,
he looked at the original text and
it found that the words that
followed this, include is or video.
And I happened to randomly select is.
And then I looked at words
that potentially follow is and
it found that words that follow
is are either a or cool.
And it randomly selected cool.
And that's how it ended up producing,
this is cool.
Now, this Markov text looks like real
text, but will also have mistakes.
For example, this video is a video
doesn't make any sense, but
it makes sense in terms of
Markov Text Generation.
From the original text, it says,
this is, I'm sorry, this video is,
and then I found a sign that
matched after is, which as video.
Now if this is a bit confusing, don't
worry about it we'll talk in depth in our
lessons about how Markov Text Generation
works and the basis behind this.
I hope you have a lot of fun with
both this part of the assignment and
with the first part of the assignment and
good luck.