All right, now you've gotten warmed up
with a project and now we want to think
about performance, and this is a common
theme throughout the entire course.
We'll be writing code but then we'll
also be talking about analyzing it,
thinking about if it's good enough,
and what that even means.
So, by the end of this first video, you'll
have a better sense of what it means to
talk about the performance of
an algorithm and why it's important.
And then we'll also describe some
factor that impact the performance of
an algorithm.
So, first of all,
before we delve into an example,
let's remind ourselves that an algorithm
is a strategy for solving a problem.
So when we talked about
the performance of an algorithm,
we're talking about how
good that strategy is for
coming at the solution of the problem
that we're thinking about.
So, let's think about an example
that comes from the project.
And in the project we're analyzing
a whole bunch of text, and
we're trying to understand
how readable it is.
That's the first part of the project.
And Christine suggested that
we used the Flesch score and
she talked about that in
some of the earlier videos.
And so we have a way of computing
some numerical representation
of the readability of a text,
based on the number of words,
the number of sentences, and
the number of syllables.
Okay, so that's great.
We read in a whole bunch of text,
we compute this Flesch score and
then we have a description
of how readable the text is.
But the question is,
how long does it take?
So, from when we've read in the text to
when we have the Flesch score available
for our user.
And if we want to answer that question,
we might just time it.
So, we might start a stopwatch and
press go when our algorithm to compute
the Flesch score starts, and then stop the
stopwatch when we've gotten the answer.
The issue, though,
is that this time that we get
might not be a great representation
of how good our algorithm is.
So we're asking how good is
the algorithm for computing flesh score?
And so, before we get to answering that
question, let's think about what might be
the problem with just looking
at the stopwatch time.
So if we think about how
much time it takes for
our code to run on a particular input,
what might impact that time?
Well, so, for example,
the computer that we're running on,
will have a huge part to play
in how quickly the code runs.
So, if we run on really old hardware,
then we expect
our code to take longer than if we run
it on a really snazzy new machine.
Or if the computer's really bogged down
with a whole lot of other programs,
then we expect it to be a little
bit slower than one that
is devoting all of its resources to
just the one program that we're running.
Other factors that might come into play,
include the compiler that we use to
compile our code into machine language.
But also decisions that we make
about what libraries to use and what
optimizations were made in those libraries
for the particular commands that we want.
So, just running our code on
a particular input and timing it
doesn't really give us a big picture
of our overall strategy for the code.
So you can think about the problem solving
paradigm, as we're given a problem,
compute the Flesch score of given text.
And we've got a strategy for computing
that Flesch score that maybe says,
read in all the text and
compute how many words there are.
Read in all the text and
compute the number of sentences.
compute the number of syllables.
And then once we've got those numbers,
then we do something with it and
compute the Flesch score.
And so, that high-level description
is like our algorithm, and
then we've coded it up in Java, or
you've done it in the project, and
we have a particular implementation.
And what we'd like to do is talk about
the performance of the algorithm and
sometimes that's tied into
the implementation as well.
And so, just the time for running
the specific code on a specific machine
on a specific input doesn't
give us the whole picture.
So, should we just give up
trying to measure performance?
Well we shouldn't because
performance is so important.
Performance is the difference between
running a really cool algorithm
that let's us answer very hard
questions in very short amount of time.
And therefore, processing more and
more data that then leads
to analyze even bigger trends and
answering more important questions.
And if we don't have handle on
the size of the data that we can
process with our algorithms, then maybe we
think we have a really cool solution but
if we try to run it, then the program's
not gonna stop until the end of time.
And so, having a sense of how our
solutions interact with larger data and
more complicated data is at
the heart of solving these problems.
So we don't want to give up,
but what can we do?
Well, maybe instead of measuring the time,
we're going to count operations.
Because hopefully we have a sense of,
perhaps if we have some sort
of basic operation, then
the amount of time that it takes to make
that operation, well, we can't control it.
But, we'll know that our algorithm
takes not too many operations.
And so, it won't take that long.
Okay, so, we are deciding that we're just
going to focus on what we can control,
which is the number of operations
we asked the computer to do,
rather than how long the computer
takes to do those operations.
And, so we might go ahead and
try to count them.
In our example of the Flesch score,
we want to start at the first part
of our text, and go through it.
And for example, we're going to count
the number of syllables in the document.
And so we want to count the number
of operations that happens.
The thing is, though, the number of
operations that we have to do in
order to count the syllables,
depends on our input.
So, if we're looking at the whole
American tax code, that's
going to be a whole lot of operations
to count all the syllables in there.
As opposed to,
if we just looked at a short snippet,
like in the example that Christine did,
where it's still a complicated text, but
we're just looking at a small part of it.
And so the number of operations
that we execute will be smaller.
Now, notice that we're performing
the exact same algorithm,
whether we're looking at the whole
tax code or just a small part of it.
And so our measure of performance
should be about the algorithm
shouldn't be talking about the input.
So what we need to do,
is focus on how the performance scales,
which means how does the number of
operations grow as our input grows?
So for example,
we'll ask questions like, if the list,
which is the string of text
that we're processing,
is twice as long, how many more
operations will it take us to process it?
Okay, so, we've moved away from just
timing using the clock time, and
we've gone to looking at the number of
operations our algorithm takes, and
we're not just going to look at
the number as an absolute number.
We're thinking about how it grows and
changes as the input size changes.
Okay, but is size all that matters?
For example, if I have two collections
of text, say the American tax code and
then something else that is equally long,
that are standing right in front of me and
I try to process both of these
texts one after the other.
Will the number of operations that's
required to process the IRS tax code,
be exactly the same as the number
of operations required to process
something else?
Maybe, maybe not.
This is a worthwhile question to consider,
and so
we're going to take that into account as
well, when we think about performance.
So, our three strategies for
talking about performance include,
#1, count the operations
instead of the time.
So we abstract away from the machine
considerations and the software
considerations that aren't part of the
algorithm design problem that we faced.
#2, is focus on how
the performance scales.
Because we care about
really big inputs and so
we wanna know about what happens
eventually as the output gets bigger and
bigger and bigger,
how does our algorithm handle it?
And #3, go beyond the input size
because what we'd like to know,
is how the algorithm responds
in all sorts of situations.
And so we'd like our performance analysis
to be able to capture not just the size
of the input but
also what might happen because of
internal structure to the input.
Okay so,
in the next video what we're going to do,
is delve right in to counting
operations for specific codes snippets.