[MUSIC]
So in the last video, we talked about
how we're going to measure performance,
based on counting operations.
So we're going to count the number
of operations that are performed
every time we execute code.
So, let's practice how to do that.
By the end of this video,
you'll be able to count the operations
when you look at
a particular code snippet.
And think about what happens when
we run it for a given input.
All right, so the code that we're going
to focus on is going to solve the answer,
answer the question of looking for
a particular letter in a word.
And we'd like to think
about how long that takes.
So, for example, we're going to look at
the word or two words, but it's a single
string, San Diego, and we're going to
search for the letter, lowercase a.
Now in order to do that, Christine showed
you a method in the previous lesson where
we have the method hasLetter,
which has input both the string,
which is the word that we're looking in.
And the letter that we're looking for,
so that's a character.
So we have those two inputs, and then
what we're going to return is a Boolean
which says true if we found the letter
in the word and false if we didn't.
Okay, so
thinking about this algorithm, what
we're really doing is a linear search.
We're gonna go through the entire string,
which remember, is an array of characters,
and we're going to start at the beginning.
And one by one, character by character,
we're going to compare
the current character to
the letter that we're looking for.
So we start at the beginning
with our index being at 0 and
then we keep checking whether
the character at that index 0,
is the same as the letter that we're
looking for, which was input by the user.
So we have our example word San Diego and
we're looking for the letter a, remember.
Okay, so we start by initializing
our loop counter i, and
that counts as a single operation.
And now we check that our loop
counter is less than the bound, and so
we're comparing 0, the current value of i,
to the word length, which is 9.
And what we need to do now is say,
okay, yes, that's correct,
0 is less than 9, and so we keep on going.
But we have to increment the number
of operations that we've done,
because that test is an operation.
All right, so now we've gone into
the body of the for loop and
inside the body of the for loop we have
an if statement, a conditional branch.
And what we're checking here is
whether the letter at position 0,
which was our current value of i,
is the letter that we're looking for.
But notice that even making that check,
testing that condition, is an operation.
And so we have to increment our
operation count once more so, so
far three operations.
In this case, the current character is a
capital S that's not the same as little a.
And so we don't execute the body
of the if branch at this point,
we go up to the top of the for loop.
We increment the counter i, oh,
incrementing, that's another operation.
And now we check that our
current value of the counter,
which is 1, is less than the word length.
It is, and so
we go back inside the for loop.
But that means that we have to
increment our operation count
because we did another check.
Okay, so we're now back inside the if and
we're checking whether
the current character, little a,
matches the letter that we're looking for
which is little a, all right?
So this check evaluates to true,
but before we go ahead and
follow the logic, we remember that we
have to increment our operation count.
And now that we've decided that we have
to go inside the if branch, we go in and
we return true.
Returning is an operation, and so
our total number of operations is 7.
Okay, so hopefully that trace
through gives you an indication
that we have to count each time
that we execute a statement.
Or that we evaluate a conditional branch,
or
a check,
something that evaluates to a Boolean.
Now, is this number of operations 7,
going to be the same every time we run
the method, hasLetter,
on inputs of string and a character?
And so what we have now, we have
a couple of quizzes for you, to see
what you think about what happens when we
run this method in different contexts.
So in those quizzes hopefully
you got a sense of just how many
variables there are for
deciding how many operations get executed
when we run a method on particular inputs.
And so let's recap what you saw in those
quizzes and let's think about what happens
when we search for the letter x,
still in that same word San Diego.
So we're still looking at
the hasLetter method and
now we're thinking about just looking for
a different character.
So when we think about counting
operations, I know that I think about
groaning because I don't wanna do that
same line by line counting each one again.
That was kind of painful but
I'd like to find a shortcut.
So let's think instead of grouping
a whole bunch of instructions,
a whole bunch of operations into maybe
something higher level, that then I can
think about how that higher level
construct repeats over and over.
So let's think about what happens as we
go through a single iteration of the for
loop, what that body of the for loop is
going to contribute to my operation count.
And so, in a single iteration,
what I need to do is,
well I need to test whether my current
loop counter is less than the bound.
I need to, in that case, perform
the contents of the body of the for loop.
And then I'm going to need to
increment my loop counter.
Okay, so
each of those contributes one instruction,
in this particular case,
to the operation count all in all.
And this is, of course, assuming that
in this current iteration of the for
loop I haven't found the character
that I'm looking for,
because that would kick us out of the for
loop.
And so let's just think about what's
happening in an iteration, somewhere in
the middle of my algorithm, somewhere in
the middle of the execution of the code.
And so in that case,
each iteration takes 3 operations.
And so
if we think back to looking for 'a',
then we only really did 2
iterations of the for loop.
We went through an iteration when
our loop counter was at the 0, so
we were comparing a to capital S, and
then we had an iteration with
our loop counter at position 1.
And so then we were comparing a to a, and
then we broke out of the for loop and
were happy.
Okay, so, when we had just the 2
iterations, we got 7 operations.
And so now let's think about the how
many iterations of the loop are there,
when we're looking for the letter 'x'.
Okay, so thinking back to the algorithm,
we're going from the beginning to
the very end of the word San Diego.
And so we're going to be looking through
every single position of the string, and
that means that there's going
to be an iteration of the for
loop for
each of the positions in the string.
And there are 9 such positions
because this is a length 9 word.
Okay, now we can go ahead and
do the calculations for
the number of operations
based on the 9 iterations.
We see that there are going
to be 29 operations.
And now you might stop and
say, whoa, hold on,
I know my arithmetic,
9 times 3 is not 29, it's 27!
Think about what happens at the very
beginning, when we initialized
the variable i, and at the very end,
when we break out of the loop.
And so, there's going to be some niggly
little counts at the very beginning and
the end that aren't exactly the same,
it's just doing 3 times
the number of iterations.
You can do that calculation, I trust you,
you can do that on your own.
But big picture, we've got about
3 operations for each iteration.
And then we've got 9 iterations of the for
loop, as we're looking for
that letter 'x' through
the word San Diego.
But in all of this,
we're kinda sweeping under the rug,
this question of what
counts as an operation?
What does it mean to have an operation?
And so, when we first started out,
I suggested that every time we execute
a statement, that's an operation.
And every time we evaluate
a conditional statement and ask for
the Boolean value of that conditional
statement, then that's an operation.
But you might ask, well how did you know?
How did you know that when we returned
to something that's an operation?
What about other possibilities,
or can I group operations?
What if I have a single line that's
both a variable declaration and
an assignment,
is that one operation or two?
Who knows?
Well so that's a really good question and
it goes to the heart of what we wanna
do when we're analyzing performance.
What we'd like to do is not
worry about this question,
what we'd like to do is only worry about
the pieces of the algorithm that we
can control as algorithm designers.
And not so
much about the implementation of how
a single line of Java code gets executed.
And so a way to think about an operation,
is a basic unit
of execution that doesn't
change as the input changes.
So when we have a single line of code that
is both a declaration and an assignment,
then what we're doing in that single line
of code doesn't depend on the input.
How long it takes us to do that doesn't
really depend on the input and so
we can count that as a single operation.
So a basic operation is something that
doesn't depend on the size of the input,
it doesn't depend on what
happens with the input.
And so
what we'd like to do is not worry so
much about whether we count such
a declaration plus assignment as two
instructions or one, and
just think of it as a single operation.
And the tools that we'll be developing
in the next video will help us do even
more of that kind of abstraction,
where we're less worried about counting
every single operation and
every single line.
And rather look at the whole scale
performance of the algorithm,
specifically as the input grows and
the input size gets really, really big.