[MUSIC]
So in the last video,
we got all tied up in questions
of what an operation is.
How do we count every
single last operation
when we execute a piece
of code on a given input?
And now, what we'd like to do is
just clean away all that clutter,
clean away all that mess, and
talk about asymptotic analysis.
So by the end of this video, you'll be
able to explain why asymptotic analysis is
so useful, and
then start calculating the big O class,
which is that indicator of asymptotics
of particular code snippets.
So we've already got some of that
motivation based on the pain that we went
through in the previous video.
What we'd like to do is not have to worry
about things that we can't control.
So we'd like to let go
some of the details, and
think about the big picture of how our
algorithm or our problem solving strategy
behaves, in particular,
relative to big data and big inputs.
So we're going to think about putting away
the details of the initialization time of
the execution.
So if there are certain things that
we need to do at the beginning,
some variables we need to declare.
Or some tidying up stuff that we need
to do at the beginning of our code.
We don't want to have to worry about that.
We also want to not have to worry about
implementing specific operations.
How do those happen?
Especially if they don't have anything
to do with how our input size
determines the runtime.
We don't need to think about them at all.
And so what we'd like to do is come up
with a principled theoretical way of
analyzing our algorithm.
But something that's a little bit
more sophisticated than counting each
instruction and that has this
wider purpose of not having to
worry about the nitty picky details
of the specific operations and
things that have to do with initialization
time or small inputs for our algorithm.
Okay, so our focus is going to be
on how the performance scales,
how our algorithm runs as we give
it bigger and bigger inputs.
So, that motivating question
that we talked about earlier is,
if our input is twice as big, how many
more operations do we need in general?
Okay, and so, that's going to
be motivating us throughout.
So let's start to think about
some specific code snippets.
And these are, you'll recognize them,
taken from that hasLetter method
that we were thinking about before.
So let's think about this, just the if
branch that we have right over here.
And think about how it behaves,
with respect to word.
So our input here is that string word.
And when we're thinking about performance,
we're thinking about it
relative to the input size.
So if we have a string, then the size
of that string is the length,
the number of characters in that string.
And you'll notice that whenever we
talk about asymptotic analysis,
when we talk about inputs,
we usually use the letter n
to represent the size of
the inputs that we're given.
So as we work through these examples,
whenever you see a little n pop up,
that's our representation of
the size of the input, okay.
So for this particular piece of code,
when the word is our input, and
so its size is n,
the number of characters in the string.
What we'd like to think about is how long
does it take to execute this if branch.
And so, in our previous model,
we counted operations.
But right now what we'd like to
do is maybe not have to count all
the operations, but think about how
does the number of operations change
as the word gets bigger or smaller,
as we have different inputs?
And if we think about what we're
doing in this if branch, we're doing
one comparison, comparing a particular
character with another character, and
then either doing zero operations,
or one operation.
Okay, so this if branch is either going
to have one operation associated with it,
just the comparison, or two operations
associated with it, the comparison and
the return statement.
And notice that all of that calculation,
what we just did, didn't depend
on the size of the word at all.
We had to think about two cases based
on the particular character, but
nothing to do with the size of the input.
And so the number of operations is
constant if all we're thinking about is
the size of the input.
Okay, so this is an example of
a constant time code snippet.
So let's look at another code snippet,
and in this code snippet,
what we're doing really is just counting
the number of characters in our string.
And so let's think about how the runtime
of this code snippet changes
as our input string grows and
grows and grows.
And so what we're doing over is here is
we're taking the input, which is still
the string word, and notice that here
we're still going to call the size n.
And again it's the number
of characters in the word.
But now the size is starting to play
a role in the execution of the code.
Because what we're doing here is
we're stepping through, in this for
loop, through each character
in the string, and so
the number of operations is going
to grow as the string grows.
And how is it going to grow?
For every new character in the string,
we're going to have to go through
one more iteration of the for loop.
Because the length is going
to be just one bigger.
So every time we add one character
to our input, one additional
character to our string, we're adding
one more iteration to the for loop.
And in that for loop, well,
we're just doing one instruction.
So, every new character in our string
adds one more instruction overall.
And this relationship, well,
if we go through that calculation,
we have one instruction for the initial
variable, declaration and assignment.
And then, n times through this loop,
we're going to check
our loop counter, increment the count,
and then add one to our loop counter.
And that's gonna happen n times.
So overall, the run time of this
piece of code is going to be one for
that initial piece, and
then within that body of the for loop,
we're going to have one for
declaring the loop counter i.
And then for
each iteration of the for loop,
we're going to have three instructions.
And then we're going to have one
additional instruction at the very end,
when we've incremented the i too
many times and it's bigger than
the length of the string, and
that's gonna kick us out of the for loop.
Okay, so overall the number of
instructions that we execute is 3n + 3,
putting all of those pieces together.
Notice that that's a linear function of n.
Okay so thinking back to calculus and
definitions of linear functions,
when we have an input being mapped
to some constant times that input,
maybe plus another constant,
that's a linear function.
Okay, so the run time in terms of the
number of operations of this piece of code
is linear, so it's linear time.
So we've seen a code snippet
that was constant time,
relative to the size of its input.
And now we've seen another code
snippet that's linear time,
relative to the size of its input.
And now what we'd like to do,
is phrase this more broadly,
in the sense of big O classes.
And so, when we say that one function
is big O of another function, what we
mean by that is that those two functions
grow in the same way as their input grows.
Because what we'd like to do in this
big O notation is say I don't wanna
care about the constants I don't wanna
have to keep track of the plus one here,
and the plus three there.
What I like to think about is
the rate of growth of the functions.
And so when we looked at that
second function over there,
the one that had the linear time, we don't
want to focus on the fact that it was
three n plus three, but rather that notion
of it being a linear function of n.
That it grew just a little bit with
every time that we increased the input
by a little bit.
Okay, and so this big O notation is
going to be our way of capturing
the rate of growth of two functions,
and so we say that
two functions are in the same big O class
if they have the same rate of growth.
Okay, now disclaimer, in industry and
in practice, this is the way
that most people use big O.
The way I just said it.
The big O class means that the two
functions grow in the same way.
Now, if you look at the text books,
if you Google asymptotics,
you'll notice that there are a lot of
different ways of measuring asymptotics.
So, there's big O,
which we'll be talking about.
There's also something called big theta,
big omega,
little o,
all of these different kinds of classes.
And they're going to represent a
finer-grained analysis of the asymptotics.
Sometimes we just care
about lower bounds or
upper bounds, and
that's going to be useful as well.
But what we're going to do in
this course and in our analysis,
is focus on the big O, and we're going to
use that as shorthand for the tight bound.
Now, that's not exactly how it's
used In the formal definition, but
for us big O is gonna be
the tightest description
of the asymptotics of the function
that we can come up with.