[MUSIC]
Okay, so let's see how that
is going to translate and
basically we're going to start with
seeing how to compute big O and
then afterwards give
the formal definition.
So our big O class is supposed to
capture eventual rates of growth.
And so we don't care about constants.
And so in big O world,
in asymptotic world, whether we have
a million or one, same difference.
The big O is exactly the same.
And so we say that a million is big O(1).
So, notice that the way that I'm
reading the sentence, the equals and
then the capital O and
then the bracket's another function.
The way that we read it is,
the left hand side is big O of
what's ever inside those brackets.
And so
here we have that a million is big O(1).
And the idea here is those constants might
just be that initialization cost when we
start off a new program.
Then we might have to do a whole lot
of busy work at the very beginning, but
that busy work is the same,
no matter what our input is.
And so even if it's a million steps or one
step that's not going to tell us how that
program behaves as our input
gets bigger and bigger and
bigger and so
we don't need to worry about it.
We just lump it all into a single
constant and say that's big O(1).
It's not changing as n changes.
Okay, so that's one of our principles.
Our second principles with asymptotic
analysis is that we only care
about the dominant term.
So we only care about
the piece of the calculation
that's going to make the biggest
impact to our outcome.
And so we only want to keep the part of
the function that is the fastest growing.
So for example, when we think back
about our linear function before,
we had 3n+3 in that calculation
of the number of operations.
But notice that we've got two terms here.
We've got the 3n term and we've got the 3.
Now, 3n grows as n grows.
3 does not.
And so the dominant term of those
2 pieces of the sum is the 3n, and
in our big O analysis we're
just going to keep that.
So 3n+3 is big O(3n).
But now think back to our previous
observation, we're going to drop constants
and so 3n is exactly the same
as n in this big O sense.
Okay, so you've got these two principles.
How do we know they're okay?
Where are they coming from?
Well, before we get there,
let's do some examples,
make sure that we're comfortable.
And so
in the next couple of in-video quizzes,
we're going to encourage you to think
about some calculations with big O.
So, hopefully those quizzes were
helpful for getting a flavor for
how you deal with big O classes and
how you compare two different
functions based on these asymptotics.
But you might be wondering,
how can we make these choices and
what's a principled way for
understanding asymptotic analysis?
So here's the formal definition of
what it means when we say that f(n) is
big O (g(n)).
And what we mean, really, is that there
are these two constants, n and c.
So that eventually, so for inputs of
sizes bigger than this capital N, we
can upper bound our function f(n) by some
constant multiple of our function g(n).
Okay, and so you can spend many pleasant
hours playing with this definition and
figuring out exactly why it means
that we can drop constants and
just keep the dominant term.
But really for practice and for
what we're gonna be doing in this class,
I encourage you to not worry too
much about this formal definition.
And really make sure that you
are comfortable with looking at code and
getting at the asymptotics
based on that code.
Looking through the execution and
really picking out the big O class for
the runtime of that code.
And so
that's what we'll be practicing next.
We'll be looking at a few
different code snippets and for
each one of them computing
the big O classes of its runtime.