[SOUND] So in the previous video,
we talked about the definition of
Asymptotic Analysis and
these Big O classes, and
we got a bit of a flavor from it,
some really small snippets of code.
How to translate from the number
of operations to the Big O class.
But now what we'd like to do is say, if we
have the runtime of two small snippets of
code, and we put them one right after
the other, what's going to be the total
runtime of the code that we're
running in asymptotic notation?
And so, by the end of this video,
you'll be able to combine the runtimes
of smaller code snippets to analyze
slightly more complicated code.
So let's think about
a particular method and
we're thinking about a method that
takes as input an array of integers.
And before we start going,
a really good rule of thumb is
when you're analyzing code, first to
have a sense of what it's going to do.
So take a minute and
the in-video quiz is coming up asks you
just to run this code on some sample
integers and see what it does
So now that you know what reduce does
as a method, let's analyze its runtime.
And really, we can break out this
method into four chunks of code.
And so, at the beginning we're
doing some initialization.
Then, we have a for loop.
Then, a little one-liner.
And then, another for loop.
And so, let's analyze each of
those pieces independently,
because what our execution path is going
to be is to go through one segment,
and then go through another segment,
one after the other consecutively.
And so the runtime of one of them isn't
really going to depend on the runtime
of the other.
They're going to go one after the other.
So let's start easy.
Let's start with a single lines of code.
And remember our rule of thumb is just
a single line of code, is constant time.
The time it takes to execute
that line of code doesn't depend
on the size of the input.
And so, we consider that just a constant
time piece of the algorithm, it's O(1).
So we've got those two under our belts.
They're done.
Now, let's look at that first for loop.
And in this for
loop what we're dong is we're going
through the entire array of integers.
And for each one at a time,
what we're trying to do is find the
smallest value in the array, basically.
And so, we're comparing the value
at the current position
in the array with some smallest
value that we've set, and
seeing whether we found
a new smallest overall.
Now, for analyzing performance, we don't
really need to know what the program does.
It's going to be a good check
at the end just to confirm.
But what we wanna do is
to count instructions or
roughly figure out how the instructions
depend on the size of the input.
And so, let's think through
about what we have to do as we
step through this for loop.
We're executing this for loop once,
the body of the for loop,
once for every position in the array.
And each time we get to
a new position in the array,
what we're doing is
this conditional check.
We're checking whether two elements in
the array, one is less than the other.
And then, depending on the result of that
check, we might be updating a variable.
So if we think about the performance,
we're having and
repetitions of the body of the array,
I'm sorry the body of the for loop.
But the body of the for
loop is just constant time.
So n many times we're just doing
a constant amount of work.
So all in all it's O(n), O(n).
So our for
loop over here as a whole is O(n).
And so, now we have just one more
piece of the method to analyze.
And that's the last for loop.
And so, let's focus in on what
happens in that last for loop.
So similarly to before, we have a for
loop that starts at one end of the array,
goes through the array one at a time,
and then does something as the position
of the array increments throughout
all of the positions in the array.
Now, as before, that means that we
have n many iterations of the for
loop being executed.
And for each iteration we just
do a constant amount of work.
So overall the amount of work that we're
doing is n times a constant amount, well,
that's O(n).
Because we dropped the constants.
So this loop as well is O(n).
So thinking back to the big picture,
thinking back to our overall method,
we've got the first piece is O(1),
then the first for loop was O(n),
the next piece was at constant work and
then the last piece is O(n).
So if we think about the runtime
total of this entire method,
we're adding up all
the runtimes that we've done.
We've done one after the other,
after the other.
And so, that means that our total runtime,
if we weren't thinking about O,
would be 1 plus n plus 1 plus n,
but that's not right.
It's not 2n + 2,
what we want to do is drop constants and
keep just the dominant terms.
And so, dropping constants means that
we can drop those two O(1) pieces.
And then, we're left with two big O(n),
which is kind of like O(2n), but we have
to drop that constant 2 and we have
a O(n) algorithm, or a linear algorithm.