[MUSIC]
So in this video we're going to
continue our work from last video,
where we're looking for
the runtime of more complicated code.
But what we're focusing on now
is how to calculate the big-O class
of code that has nested for loops.
So not consecutive for loops,
but one loop inside another.
So let's do an example and
this example is called maxDifference.
It's a method that takes in as its
argument an array of integers.
And as we did before, start off by
thinking about what this method actually
does and it's a great idea to get into
the habit of describing the higher
level functionality of pieces of code,
so let's start with that.
So now that you've looked at what
max difference does as a method,
let's analyze its performance.
And as we did before, it's useful to chunk
up the method into the pieces that really
don't interact too much with one another,
especially when it comes to run time.
And so for this context we have
the initialization piece at the beginning,
then we have some nested piece
of code in the middle, and
then we have the return
statement at the end.
Okay, so, easy stuff first.
Let's look at the beginning at the end and
these are single instructions that
get executed in constant time.
And so, each of those we
don't need to worry about.
And let's focus in on really
the meaty part of this method.
And we've got a for
loop within a for loop.
And so, it might be a little bit daunting.
How do we analyze its run time?
And so a rule of thumb is to
count from the inside out.
And so let's go as far,
as deep into the nesting as we can and
then work our way out.
And so inside the inner for
loop, we have an if branch and
we've worked with those before.
And so we notice that what happens here
is we're doing a test that can happen
in constant time, we're comparing
the values of two entries in the array.
And then, based on the result
of that test, we may or
may not do a single operation.
And so, that entire conditional statement
will either be one operation or
two depending on the result of the test.
But one, two,
those are both constant numbers.
They don't depend on the size
of the input, and so
that entire if branch
is just big O of one.
And so, the advantage of working from
inside out is that now we don't need to
worry about what operations we had
over there, or what code we executed.
All we need to worry about Is that it
was a big O of one piece of the program.
And so now, we can work our
way back up to say how many
times does that big O of one piece of work
have to get repeated and executed and
so, accumulate together how
much time we need overall.
Okay so, in the inner for loop,
what we're doing is we're going from j=0,
all the way to the end of the array.
So we're stepping through the input array,
and at each point,
we're doing that constant amount of work.
And so that means that if we're focusing
in on that inner for loop, we're doing
a constant amount of work and many
times where n is the size of the array.
And so, overall, we're doing
a constant times n amount of work, but
we drop constants, so
that's big O(n) amount of work.
So that inner for
loop, every time we go through it,
we're doing a big O(n) amount of work.
Now how many times do we go
through that inner for loop?
Well, let's step back out one more
level and we've got the outer for loop.
And so that outer for loop you can think
of as going through the entire array,
from i=0 to the end of the array,
and for each new value of i,
we have to do that inner piece of work,
that big O(n) amount of work.
Okay, so
every time we go through the outer for
loop, we're doing O(n) amount of work.
How many times do we go
through the outer for loop?
Well the length of the array many times.
So that's n many times.
And so
n many times do we do O(n) amount of work,
that's n squared amount of work overall.
So, what we're seeing here is that when
we nest to the for loops, what we end up
doing is we're multiplying the amount
of times we go through the outer for
loop by the run time of that inner for
loop.
Okay, so we've got multiplication
happening here because that inner for
loop is repeated every single time
we step through that outer for loop.
All right, so
now what we've done is we've analyzed
the runtime of each of the three
chunks of the algorithm.
But now we've reduced our analysis to
the case that we had in the previous video
where we have consecutive pieces of code.
And remember that when we had
consecutive pieces of code,
the total run time is just the dominant
term from each of those three pieces.
And so we have, in this case,
big O(1) followed by big O(n
squared) followed by big O(1).
1 doesn't grow at all with n, so
it's definitely not as
fast growing as n squared.
N squared definitely grows as
our input size gets bigger.
And so overall,
this algorithm is a quadratic algorithm or
it runs in big O (n squared) time.
So that's an example of
dealing with nested for loops.