All right.
So
now we have a concept challenge for
you that has to do with big O classes.
So it's just like any
other concept challenge.
What we want you to do is we want you
to try to solve the problem yourself,
then get together with some friends and
discuss.
Watch the UC San Diego learners discuss.
Try to answer the question again and
then verify your understanding
with our explanation.
So the problem for you is we have three
potential equalities here that
relate a function to a big O class.
And what I'd like to know is which
of these represent tight bounds
on the function over here
on the right hand side?
So is O of N a tight bound for
n squared minus 10,000?
Is O of n squared a tight bound for
n plus n log n?
And is O of log base 2 of n a tight
bound for log base 10 of n.
>> Hi, my name is Maya.
>> Hi, my name is Robert.
>> Hi, my name is Christina.
>> For the first one,
N squared minus 10,000 equals big O of n.
Are you saying if the n squared,
if it's a function like this, and
then there's another function
like big O of n that's like that,
you mean like,
which one would grow faster?
>> Yes.
So they're sort of asking,
is n a bigger function than
n squared minus 10,000?
Okay, so it just has to be bigger.
So in the question we have n squared and
O of n, so
n squared would be bigger than O of n.
So O of n wouldn't be tighter big O class.
>> Yeah,
even though 10,000 it's a constant so
it's just n squared
>> Oh yeah, and
with problems like these,
constants don't really matter.
You could cancel them out a little bit.
>> Even if it's multiplied,
it doesn't matter either.
>> Okay.
>> So in the second one we have two terms.
We have n and
n log n equals O of n squared.
So when we have two terms,
I think only the biggest one takes
precedents just like the constants.
>> Yeah, so I guess the second
term would be a lot bigger
cuz since obviously it's n
multiplied to another term.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And whenever log n is smaller than n,
right?
>> Yes.
>> So it would be smaller than n squared
So, n squared is a big O in this case.
>> Okay.
>> But I don't think it's the tightest.
>> No.
So the tightest would be
something like n log n.
Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Okay, so for the third one,
I noticed on the left side there is a 10.
On the right side there's a 2.
>> So, I'm not really sure,
but I feel like they still
kinda grow at the same rate.
So, I'm not really sure.
Yeah.
>> Because obviously they're different.
But, what could you
multiply a constant to it.
So they're coefficients.
>> Yeah.
Because if you do that, it would be equal.
>> Yeah, I'm not so sure which ones.
>> So we're gonna use that method that
Mia showed you for estimating, or
figuring out, what the tight bound is for
a given function.
So let's start here,
with this given function.
And the function is n
squared minus 10,000.
So, what is the tightest
big O bound on this?
Well, what Mia showed you to do
is to basically ignore all but
the highest order term.
So, we look at n squared,
we look at 10,000.
n squared is clearly the high order term
here, so we focus in on that n squared.
And then we're gonna ignore any constant
multipliers on that n squared term.
Well, there are no constant multipliers.
And so what we would have here is that,
if we use our estimation technique
that Mia taught you, this should be
O of n squared as the tightest bound.
But if we compare that
to what we asserted,
O of n, we have to compare n squared to n.
And we can see that clearly n
squared grows faster than n.
So n squared is in fact the tightest O
bound we can have on this function here.
And n is not even an upper bound because
it grows much more slowly than n squared.
So the answer to this one,
is this is a tight bound?
The answer is no.
All right, next question, is O of n
squared a tight bound on n plus n log n?
Again, we'll do the same thing, and
we'll figure out which is the bigger term,
n or n log n.
Well n is just n, and
log n is n times something of n.
So this here is going
to be our bigger term.
We can ignore the n term.
There's no constant multiplier on it,
so we would just,
using again that method that Mia
presented, see that this is n times log n.
And now we have to figure out how does
n times log n compare to n squared.
Well n squared is just n times n.
So here we have n times log n.
Over here was n times n.
This is going to be a slower growing
function, because log n is smaller than n.
So this bound here, O of n log n,
is going to be a tighter bound than
our originally proposed bound of O of
n squared because n squared
grows faster than n log n.
So this tighter bound is
smaller than n squared.
N squared is an upper bound, but
it's not the tightest one we can find,
which is this one right here.
So this one doesn't work
either as a tight bound.
Finally, let's consider our last function
down here which is we're asking is O of
log base 2 of n a tight bound for
the function log base 10 of n.
Now there's no two terms to consider,
there's only one term,
there's no constant multipliers.
So what we're really asking is do logs
grow kind of at the same rate
no matter what their bases are?
And to figure this out you have to
remember that log base conversion formula.
Or if you've never seen it before
I'm gonna show it to you now.
Because we need to be able to express
these logs in terms of the same base to
be able to compare them.
Because right now it's not really clear
if those two functions will grow at
the same rate.
So the log based conversion
formula looks like this.
We can turn log base 10of n into
log base 2 of n by dividing log
base 2 of n by log base 2 of 10.
So there we have it.
We take our old base,
we convert it to a new base but
then we have to divide by log and
the new base of the old base.
But if we look at this quotient here,
we can see what's on the bottom
isn't in terms of n at all.
So that's just a constant factor
which we can now ignore for
the purpose of our big O analysis.
So we can pretty much just ignore this and
we can see that this top turn here is
going to turn into to
O of log based 2 of n.
And if we compare this to what we
originally asserted over there,
we can see those are exactly the same.
So O of log base 2 of n, is in fact
a tight bound for log base 10 of n.
This is why you'll see computer scientists
almost always drop the bases from logs,
when they're talking about big O notation.
Because it doesn't matter.
All bases of logs can be converted into
others using constant, factor, and
multiplication.
So inside the big O, the base doesn't
matter, which is why you can see
that we in fact even dropped it up here
in our first analysis that I just did.