[APPLAUSE]
>> In this video,
we're gonna do a runtime
analysis of selection sort.
So by the end of this video,
you should be able to do this
kind of analysis on your own.
Let's just get started by remembering
what selection sort does.
So the idea behind selection sort is to
find essentially the smallest value in
the remaining unsorted array and
put that at the start.
And then just keep repeating
that process over and over.
It may be easier with an example.
What we have here is
an array that's unsorted.
The first step is gonna be find
the smallest value in this array.
So you're gonna walk all the way through,
you're gonna look at 4, 7, 2, 10, 1, and
8, and figure out that 1 is the smallest.
And you'll put 1 at the start,
as you swap 1 and 4 in the process.
So now you essentially have your
sorted array on the left, and
you have your unsorted array on the right.
You're gonna do the same process again
now for the unsorted array on the right.
You're gonna try to find
the smallest value.
You're gonna look through all
the elements, 7, 2, 10, 4, and 8, and
find that 2 is the smallest, and swap
that with 7, to put that at the start.
Let's do one more example of this, so
we look at the unsorted array again,
we're gonna find the smallest value,
this time the smallest value's gonna be 4.
We're gonna swap 4 and
7 to put 4 at the front.
At this point we just
continue this process and
essentially you end up
with a sorted array.
So that's the idea behind selection sort,
but now let's talk about the analysis.
Here's the code to
essentially do selectionSort.
We have our method name is selectionSort.
It takes in an array of ints which are
just the values that we're trying to sort.
In terms of analysis we can kinda
start walking through these steps.
The first is just the initial
values that you're declaring.
You don't need to worry about
this variable assignment.
This is a constant time operation.
But then we immediately get into a loop.
And when we get to loops we know that
we're gonna wanna do a more careful
analysis.
In fact this is a nested loop and we'll
talk about those details in a moment.
But the idea here is gonna be very similar
to the previous ones that we've done and
we're gonna try to reason about how
many times the outer loop runs and
how many times the inner loop runs.
This isn't gonna quite work out for
us, and
we'll see how that turns out here shortly.
So, let's keep with this approach, though.
So let's try and figure out how
many times the outer loop runs.
The outer loop is actually
pretty easy to reason about.
It's gonna run n times.
So now,
looking at more detail in the inner loop,
what we see that it starts
off with indexMin = i.
This is just a single statement, so
this is a constant time operation.
At the very end of the inner loop
we're gonna do a swap operation.
And though it looks like I'm just
calling it a nice function here,
we have to think about what are the actual
statements within that method.
To do swap it only takes
actually three statements.
So this again,
is essentially a constant time operation.
Now we can dive into
the details of the inner loop.
See, inner loop is gonna do
essentially this testing for
keeping a running count of
the minimum values that it's seeing.
So as it's going through,
it's keeping track of, again,
the smallest value that it's seeing,
and in doing so
it's doing a conditional operation and
then setting that value.
A conditional, along with a value
setting is, again, just two statements.
So we can consider this
a constant time operation.
So now we have this constant
time operation here,
we have to start reasoning about how
many times does this loop execute?
Well, it's gonna execute, essentially, (n-
( i+1) ) and where did I get that from?
n is the essentially
the length of the array,
and if you notice,
j always starts at i + 1.
So it's gonna keep increasing as
we go through, as i increases.
This is going to cause problems for
me in a little bit, but
we'll get back to that in just a second.
So let's assume that our inner loop
essentially fills in this runtime.
We know that those first and
the last operations are constant time.
I can combine all of this into
now one larger statement.
I know those constant time operations
can essentially be dropped, and
I'm left with a fairly clean
term which is just O ( n-i ).
What I'd like to do then is do the same
kind of analysis we've done in the past.
Just take the number of iterations
that executed in the outer loop and
multiply it by the number of
iterations on the inner loop.
If I do that,
I essentially get this nice form.
The problem here is, what is O (n- i)?
That's not what we want,
we want this to be in terms of n.
And i is gonna be changing on me,
so this is really problematic.
I need to know specifically what
does this mean in terms of n?
Now the way I can do this is essentially
look at the fact that as i increases,
this term is gonna decrease.
But it's not enough just to say that.
Because if i increases rapidly and
the term decreases rapidly,
I may get a very different
runtime analysis.
The way I'm gonna wanna do this,
is to instead of doing one loop at a time,
let's look at them together.
So what I'm gonna do then is
look at the entire operation,
the outer loop along with the inner loop,
to figure out at each step how many
iterations have to run of the inner loop.
So when i = 0, how many iterations
have to happen on the inner loop?
Well, when i = 0, n- 0 is n,
and that just gives me n.
Next iteration of the outer loop,
I'm now gonna have i be 1.
n-1 is how many times it's gonna execute.
i is gonna go to 2,
we're gonna have n-2 and
this is gonna go until we hit the end of
the array in that iteration of the loop.
When i is n-1, we're gonna have just 1.
So this sequence is what we're
gonna start reasoning about.
How long does this take?
How many steps is this?
We have the entire performance
within this series, but
let's reverse it to work
with it more easily.
When we reverse it it's
just swap the order.
And now I'm seeing a series that
might be more easy to work with.
I see that's 1+2+3 all the way up to +n.
And this might be a series
you've recognized before.
But let's talk a little bit more detail
about how we might solve for this series.
What exactly is this?
Well, there's a way to solve this.
I actually wanna derive the equation for
this, this is not that hard to do.
And the way to derive this essentially
is by looking at pairings.
We want you to see is that this pairing,
1 and n-1 adds up to n.
Likewise, 2 and n-2 also add up to n.
And you can keep going this
way through the entire list.
So, what I want you to do
is just take a moment and
think about how many total pairs
add up to n within that range.
All right.
So, if you came up with essentially
the number of elements here is n-1.
Each of them have to be paired up so
it would be n-1 over 2 is
the number of pairs that sum to n.
That'd be exactly right.
So, how many operations
are occurring here?
Well, if each of these sums up to n,
I can just say n(n-1) over 2.
This is a pretty clean form.
Now you may notice,
I'm missing one term here.
I'm not adding on the n at the end,
and I can just do that right here.
Now this is a fairly recognizable series.
And the reason why,
is because there's a fun fact about it.
The legend goes that Gauss was
assigned some busywork as a student.
And in doing so,
he essentially derived this formula, and
the busywork that he was assigned was
to add all the numbers from 1 to 100.
And when the teacher assigned this, she
thought, okay, well everyone's gonna go 1
+ 2 + 3 + 4, and it's gonna take them
a while, and I can get a little break.
The problem is Gauss derived
this equation fairly quickly.
He just plugs in the numbers, and
out comes the answer of 5,050.
His work's done, he can move on.
This is a fun story,
I always enjoy hearing about this.
But this is where this equation come from.
All right, let's wrap this up
by looking at the analysis.
So we've got it down to this equation.
What's the tightest correct
classification, then, for this equation?
Nice work!
There's a lot of different ways that
you may have solved this problem.
But almost certainly what you did is
you expanded out that first set to say,
n times n is n2, and then you saw
that the rest were all constants or
just terms of n.
Since n2 is the dominant term,
this is gonna be O(n2),
and we've essentially solved this problem.
So working through selection sort wasn't
incredibly straightforward from the start.
You can see if you do
a careful analysis of it.
You can come up with the solution.