In this concept challenge we're gonna look
at a nested for loop, in fact a triply
nested for loop, to try to figure out what
the big-O running time of this code is.
So same format as the other
concept challenges.
Work on it on your own.
Discuss it and
watch the UC San Diego's learners discuss.
Try the problem again.
And then, confirm your
understanding with our explanation.
So here's the problem.
We've got this code that you can see here.
It's a triply nested for
loop, and the question is,
in terms of n, what is the big-O running
time, tightest bound, for this code?
>> Hi, I'm Tina.
>> Hi, my name is Gev.
>> Hi, my name is Robert.
>> So what I noticed with this code is,
that we have three nested for loop lines,
and so I would think that we could
figure out the run time for each line,
and then multiply those three together,
and see what we get from there.
>> Okay, well for the first outer loop,
that starts at i=0 and
goes all the way up to 2*n.
So that's, I think,
the run time for the first loop.
And then, the second loop looks a little
bit more confusing cuz if we start
it at n- 1000,
I'm a little bit confused about that.
>> So, I think for the second one,
since you're subtracting 1000,
so all you have to do is
increment the 1000, so
that would just be 1000 counts for
the run time.
>> And for the last one, I noticed
our first starting index has n in it,
or in this case n over 2, but
it looks like it's from n over 2 to n.
So I'd think it'd be, overall the run
time for that line would be n over 2,
does that seem like it?
>> Yeah, and you said we had to multiply
them, all of them, to get the run time?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, that sounds right.
>> So, I think that comes out to be 2*n,
times 1000,
times n over 2, and I think we can ignore
the 1000, because it's a constant.
So, that comes out to be n squared,
I believe.
>> Yeah, n squared.
>> Right.
>> All right, so the key to analyzing this
triply nested for loop, as Mia showed you,
is to analyze the number of instructions
that are done in each body of the for
loop from the inside out.
Because the innermost for loop here
is going to be executed to completion
every time the next-outermost for
loops runs once.
Similarly, for
this next outermost for loop,
it will be run to completion every
time this outermost for loop runs.
So let's begin at the very inner layer,
this instruction right here which is
the body of the innermost for loop.
And we need to count the number
of instructions in that body.
Well, of course there is just one
instruction in that body, that sum++.
So, the amount of time that that
body takes is just order 1.
So, now we can calculate how many
times does this innermost for
loop run its body,
which just has one instruction in it.
So, to do that, we need to look at the
loop bounds and where the control variable
starts, where it ends, and
how much we add to it each time through.
So, we have this control variable k.
It starts at n over 2.
It goes as long as k is less than n, and
we add one to k each
time through the loop.
So, how many times is
that going to execute?
Well, it's going to execute all
the way up from n over 2 to n,
stepping along one each time, and
that's gonna be n over 2 times.
But n over 2 in big-O notation
is really just order n, so
this loop runs order n times,
executing 1 each time in its body.
And so
the entire loop Is going to be order n.
So, from start to finish, that entire
inner loop is going to take order n steps.
So now let's back out, and figure out how
many times this next most inner loop runs.
Again, we look at the loop header.
We have j starting at n- 1000, going up
to n, and we're adding one each time.
Now, this one's a little bit tricky,
because if we count the number of steps,
even though there's an n here, this loop
is actually only going to run 1000 times.
Because we're starting at n- 1000,
going up to n.
So, there's only 1000 steps
between n- 1000 and n, and
we're going to do each step once.
So this whole loop only runs 1000 times.
So the total amount of work that it does,
including its body,
is just 1000 times the work of the body,
which is n.
So 1000 times n is just
n times a constant, so
we can replace that entire loop with the
amount of work it does in big-O notation,
and that's just order n again.
Because again, it only ran 1000 times,
which is a constant relative to n.
So, now we have that the body of
the outermost for loop is order n.
So, let's count the times that the
outermost for loop runs, and then we'll be
able to assert how many times
the entire block of code actually runs.
So i this time starts at 0,
and we go as long as
i is less than 2*n, and
we add one to i each time.
So that's gonna be a total number of
steps, total number of iterations of 2n,
because we're starting at 0,
going up to 2*n.
So this outermost loop runs 2n times,
it does order n work in its body,
so now we have 2n times
n gives us 2n squared.
But in big-O notation,
that 2 will go away, and we'll end up with
the work being done by this entire block,
is just order n squared.