[MUSIC]
So, now you have a lot of practice
computing asymptotic bounds.
Which means those big O classes for
various pieces of code.
And when we're thinking about a piece of
code that's executed on a given input.
But what we'd like to do is step back and
think about our original problem.
And our original problem was measuring
the performance of an algorithm,
which was a strategy for
solving a problem.
And so that means that we don't want
to just focus in on a single input.
We wanna think about how
the algorithm behaves for all inputs.
And so, by the end of this video, you'll
be able to define what it means to talk
about the worst case, average case, and
best case performance of an algorithm.
And talk about how that really talks
about the various inputs that
we might have to come across.
And then we'll talk about, also,
why each of these is used.
So, let's think back to this big picture
we have of an algorithm as a problem
solving strategy or machine.
That takes some input and produces output,
and the performance that we've been
focusing on is the time that it takes for
the algorithm to do this.
To report back the answer,
given the input.
So in the example that we've talked about
way back when when we first started.
We were looking at the hasLetter method,
which took as its input a word,
which was a string.
And a character which was the letter
that we were looking for in that word.
And then it returned either true or
false based on whether the character
was found inside the string.
Now, as we saw when we were counting
operations, depending on the specific
word and letter combination, our algorithm
behaved a little bit differently.
It took a different number of operations,
in with each one of these cases.
So even if we were looking
at the exact same word, so
that a fixed length word,
and one character.
We weren't changing the number of
characters we were looking for.
We could still have quite different
behavior in terms of the number of
operations that our algorithm required
before it could output the answer.
And so what we'd like to do now
is capture that variability in
terms of the algorithm run time.
And talk about the different
contexts we might care about.
So we might be optimistic and
say, in the best possible case
how short might be my wait,
how quick might my algorithm be?
So, if I give the algorithms
just the most beautiful input,
whatever beautiful means,
then how quick can it respond to me?
And now still this input is
going to be of a fixed size n.
So, we don't expect
the algorithm to be very quick,
no matter what size input we have.
So we're just thinking about,
within all the inputs of size n,
what's the best possible
behavior of my algorithm.
And so
thinking back to the hasLetter method,
when is this algorithm the quickest?
When does it have to run
very few operations?
Well, think back to what we do.
We start at the beginning and
we look for our letter in every
possible position of our string.
So if we found our letter at the very
beginning, if our letter was the very
first letter of this string, then we'd
be able to quit while we were ahead.
We'd be able to return out
of the method very quickly.
So the best case for this method,
is when the word that we've input,
starts with the letter
that we're looking for.
And in that case, well, this algorithm
just really needs to do one check, really.
It just compares the letter
that we're looking for
with a character at the first position of
the string, and that takes constant time.
So in the best case,
this method is a constant-time method.
So that's interesting, but
most of the time we're not going
to be in the best case scenario.
Most of the time the word that we care
about will not start with the letter that
we care about.
And so this is just a very small
view of how this algorithm behaves.
This is just one special case.
And so, on the other hand,
we might be pessimists, and
say, well,
I think things are gonna be bad.
I think my algorithm's gonna take forever.
And so
what should we prepare ourselves against?
What's the worst possible
performance of the algorithm,
no matter how bad the input,
still for a given, fixed size?
And so what we'd like to do now is look at
our algorithm and say, as pessimistically
as possible, in the worst possible
situation, how many steps will I need?
And so
again with our example of hasLetter,
what's the worst possible situation we
might have in terms of run time here?
Well, we're stepping through
the letters of the word and
each time we're looking for
our desired letter.
And so, in the worst possible situation,
what we're gonna have to do is
go through the entire word and
either just find our letter at
the very end or not find it at all.
So, the worst case for this method is that
the letter that we care about is either at
the end of the word or
it's missing altogether.
And in either one of those situations what
happens is that we've stepped through
the entire input word.
And are only able to return our answer
to the user once we've looked at all of
the characters in the string.
And so in either way,
what we have to do is some constant number
of instructions for
each position in the word.
And so that means that we need to
do big O of N much work where N
is the length of the word.
And so, in the worst case, where we
have to go through the entire string,
this method takes linear time,
big O(n) time.
Okay, so,
we've got the best case situation,
we've got the worst case situation.
And, just if we think
about the meanings here,
the amount of time our algorithm takes in
the best case will always be shorter than
the amount of time our algorithm
takes in the worst case.
Okay, and so when we think about this
best case and worst case analysis,
it's useful to keep in mind why we
might care, how we'll use these bounds.
And so you can think about the best
case analysis as this guarantee
that we'll always have to spend at least
this amount of time doing this algorithm.
We know that we'll never be
shorter than the best case.
Okay, and so if we're budgeting our time,
we know that we have to budget
at least this amount of time.
For the worst case analysis, we know that
we've got a guarantee that we'll never
have to wait longer than
the worst case analysis.
To get back an answer from our algorithm.
And so if we're planning ahead, we'll know
that by a certain amount of time, and
maybe before,
we'll have terminated this algorithm.
And so it's useful to have these extreme
situations analyzed when we're trying
to analyze how our algorithm's going
to behave, no matter what input we get.
Well, now we've understood the extremes.
The thing is that in real life,
we don't usually live in the extremes,
we often live somewhere
in that messy middle.
And so we also have a notion
of average case performance.
And with average case analysis,
what we'd like to do is get a sense of the
performance of the algorithm on average,
if we consider all
possible inputs of size n.
Now this gets really messy.
All sorts of considerations
need to get taken into account.
If we want to be completely
precise about it,
we need to think about
the distribution of possible inputs,
how likely it is to get
different kinds of inputs.
We can also think about what happens with
each of those inputs on their own and
then try to put them together.
As you can probably tell,
this is very messy, very quickly and
what we typically do is just say average
case we realize is more realistic.
But it's too hard and we're going
to use the bounds that we got from
the analysis of best case and
worst case to give us the ballpark.
Understand the sandbox in which we're
playing and that's good enough.
So there we have the best case, the worst
case, and the average case possibilities.
Notice that we're using the asymptotic
notation, the big O notation to describe,
in each of these contexts,
what the run time of the algorithm is.
But what we're computing is going to be
a little bit different in each situation.