[SOUND]
You may wonder,
why is worst-case analysis useful?
After all, that's not what users
are gonna see most of the time.
And it's true that other kinds of
analysis can be really helpful as well.
For instance, best case analysis can
let you know right up front if there's
no way that the algorithm is
gonna work for you at all.
If you know that even the best
case scenario it's gonna take
five years to finish this job,
that's probably okay, great, we're done.
Time to look for something different.
But worst case analysis is important
because that's what people remember.
Google, if most of your searches
take less than a second to complete,
and here's your answers and
it's great, cool.
And we could have the bet
answers in the world, and
we like to think that we
try to give you that.
But if every so often running a search
takes on the order of 10 minutes,
20 minutes to complete
because there's a worst case
divot that just takes that long,
you're not gonna use this.
You're gonna go to somebody else,
because who's got 20 minutes to wait
even if you know you're
answers are gonna be good.
So, best case performance
is great to know.
Average case performance is great to know.
But worst-case scenario
is really the killer, and
that's what we've gotta know, because
if the worst case isn't good enough,
then it's not good enough, and that's it.