[MUSIC]
So now we're ready to analyze
the performance of some of the sorting
algorithms that we've
already talked about.
So by the end of this video,
you'll be able to state and
justify the asymptotic performance, so
the big O classes for the running time,
of both selection sort and insertion sort.
And we'll be thinking about them, both
in the best case and in the worst case.
Now, for both of these sorting algorithms
if you need a refresher just go back
to the first course in the specialization.
That's when we talked about
them in quite a bit of detail.
But, we'll be doing an overview now,
as well.
So, our goal is to fill in this table with
big O classes that represent the best and
worst case performance for
these two sorting algorithms.
So let's start with selection sort, and
in selection sort we take a list or
an array of data.
And what we'd like to do is organize it so
that it's presented
in order from smallest to biggest based
on some measure of smallest and biggest.
And so our strategy is going to look
at each position in the array in turn.
And for each of those positions,
find the right element to put in there.
And so we look at all of the possible
elements remaining in the array.
And figure out which one
of those is smallest and
put it in this current position.
Okay, so that's the algorithm.
And so now, let's think ahead about what
insertion sort algorithm is going to do.
It's a little bit different.
We're still going through all of
the positions in the array in turn.
But instead of looking for
the correct elements to put in each time,
what we're doing is looking at the current
value that we're focused in and nudge
it over to its correct position relative
to the elements that are already listed.
So we're still going step by step and
increasing the part of the array that's
sorted each time, but
doing it in a slightly different strategy.
And we'll see the impact of
these different strategies
on their performance
of the two algorithms.
So let's start with selection sort, and
let's think about the performance
of this sorting algorithm.
So we actually used selection sort
in a previous support video where
we went through the code for selection
sort and computed its performance.
This was an example of nested for
loops that were really interesting to
analyze and we used some cool identities.
But notice that when we did that analysis,
we could say,
this algorithm is big O of n squared,
it's quadratic, and when we did that,
it was before we said anything about
best case, worst case, average case.
We weren't even thinking
about the input or
how it was organized, because this
sorting algorithm, if you think about it,
doesn't really care what the input
looks like when you first get it.
It goes through and
does the same sequence of steps no
matter how its input is organized.
So the number of steps,
the performance of the sorting algorithm,
only depends on the size of
the array that it starts with.
It doesn't depend on how the contents
of the array are organized and
that means that the best case and
the worst case performance of this
algorithm are exactly the same.
It's the same as the average case.
It's the same as any case, so for
any array of size n, the best case and
worst case performance of selection sort,
is big O of n squared.
Okay, so that's the one algorithm.
Now let's think about
the insertion sort algorithm, and
try to fill in some of those questions
marks, and we haven't analyzed it yet.
So let's do it now, and
what we're trying to do,
as I mentioned earlier, is focus on one
new element of the array at a time.
And for that new element put it in its
correct location relative to the earlier
ones that have been sorted already.
And so we assume that at each
point we have that initial
piece of the arrays already sorted.
And so what we need to do is figure
out where the next element goes and
we do that by comparing
that next element to,
well, the highest element in
the sorted part of the array and
see, well should I swap their locations or
not?
And then maybe I'm gonna
need to swap again, and
maybe I need to swap again until
the new element gets to its correct
relative location based on the previously
sorted pieces of the array.
Okay, so what would the best case
of this algorithm look like?
And in order to do that,
we need to focus in on that for loop.
Where that for loop looks at
each position in the array and
says, I'm going to put the element in
this position, in its correct location.
And the piece that really depends on
the values is the inner while loop.
So, the inner while loop
maybe gets executed
a different number of times,
based on the relative
size of the consecutive pairs
of elements in the array.
So, let's think about the best case first.
So, in the best case,
what we would have, is that we don't
need to make very many swaps at all.
So we're looking at a new element in the
array, and we'd like to find its correct
relative position, relative to
the earlier elements in the array.
And if we're really lucky then it's
already going to be in that position.
Well what that would
mean is that it's bigger
than the biggest element in
the already sorted part of the array.
And so, what we need to check
is that the current index has,
the value of that current index
is already bigger than the value
at the last piece of the already
sorted part of the array.
So when does that happen?
Well, it happens when the array that
we start with is already sorted.
Every time we look at a new element,
it's already in its correct location
relative to the earlier ones, so
we don't need to do anything.
The body of the while loop never executes.
And so when we look at
the performance in this case,
that means that every time we try
to start executing the while loop,
all we need to do is do that just one
test, and it's going to evaluate to false.
And we go away from it, and we go to
the next iteration of the for loop.
And so that means that the body of the for
loop in this case,
when the array's already sorted,
every time we go through the for loop,
we just execute a constant
number of instructions.
And so all in all, we have n iterations
of the for loop, each time doing
just a constant amount of work, and
so all in all we have just O(n) work.
So when the array is already sorted,
in this best-case lucky,
lucky scenario,
insertion sort just takes big O(n) time.
Cool.
That's much, much better than quadratic,
which was selection sort.
So that's interesting, okay.
Is it gonna be good all the time?
Is it a big win?
Well, so let's think about the worst case.
So what input might we get that would
require us to run many, many steps?
And remember the piece that we're
focusing in on is that inner while loop.
Where we're nudging the current value that
we're looking at to its correct location
within that first part of
the array that's already sorted.
So, if we think about what
might make us really unlucky
is if we have to do a lot of the nudging,
a lot of the swaps over.
And so, if we think of our arrays being
really far from sorted, then we're gonna
have to do a lot of work to keep moving
these elements to their correct location,
relative to the sorted part of the array.
So, thinking about an array that's
given to us in reverse sorted order,
we're going to have to do a lot of work
in this algorithm in order to get it
to the correct form,
namely going from one through five,
rather than from five through one.
So in this worst case analysis what we
see is that when we are looking at,
for example, at the second position,
so position equals 1,
then when we want to nudge 4 over to its
correct location we have to do a swap.
And then when we look at the next index
at position 2, then in order to move 3
to its correct location we're
going to have to swap it twice.
And so every time we're going to
have to swap all the way over to
the head of the array and so all
together what's going to happen is that
on average we're gonna have about
O(n) many swaps for each position.
And that happens n many times as
we go through all the positions.
And so
we get to O(n) squared amount of work.
And so the analysis at the end
was a little brief but
it's really similar to what we do when
we think about analyzing selection sort.
So go back and
revisit that support video if you'd
like to see a little bit more detail.
Now what we wanna keep in mind,
though, is that the worse case for
insertion sort happened when our
input array was in reverse order.
And so this is really illustrating how
the structure of the input can determine
the performance of our algorithm.
And when we're thinking about worst-case
analysis, we want to think about
the kinds of inputs that will make
us do the most amount of work.
So here is our table so
far for sorting algorithms.
And in the next video we'll introduce
a couple of new sorting algorithms
just to expand our vocabulary, expand
our toolbox of sorting algorithms and
compare how they're run as well.