[MUSIC]
So this is a slightly different
kind of When I Struggle video.
This isn't when I struggled when
I first learned the material.
This is when I struggled
basically last week.
What happened was,
I bought a padlock for my backyard.
So that my son isn't able to get out of
the yard when he's playing back there.
And as you know, with padlocks,
you can set the combination.
Well, something went wrong when I was
trying to set the combination and
somehow or another it was locked and
I didn't know the combination.
So I'm stuck with this quandary, go buy
a new lock or essentially brute force.
One by one, check every combination.
And this ties in so well to what Mia's
been explaining about algorithm analysis.
Because, I essentially have a best case,
an average case, and a worst case, and
I had to compare that against
the cost of buying a new one.
So the best case, is I try the very
first combination, say zero, zero, zero,
and it works.
That'd be fantastic,
the worst case though,
is I might go from 000 all the way to 999.
And that could take a really long time.
And that'd be really bad.
And then the average case really is well,
on average I'm gonna find this around 500.
So being a bit frugal,
I decided I actually want to try it and
I ran through all the combinations.
I actually got to 338 when it opened.
So I got lucky.
It's a little bit better than my
average case expectation on the time.
So what I encourage you to do when you are
learning about all these abstract concepts
related to computer science,
try to relate it to the real world.
See how it's applying to
you in your everyday life.