[MUSIC]
>> So we've looked at three
different algorithms for
solving the exact same problem,
that of sorting.
And so now let's step back and think about
how would we choose which algorithm to use
and how does their performance compare.
So, by the end of this video, you'll be
able to state the best case, worst case,
and average case performance,
in terms of run time for
each of these sorting algorithms.
And you'll be able to think a bit
about which situations call for
one of these algorithms
rather than another.
So let's think about our results so
far, and
this table encapsulates what
we've been thinking through.
And we've computed the best case and worst
case performance of each of selection
sort, insertion sort, and merge sort.
And something to notice here is that
we've got the n squared term, or
the quadratic term, showing up in the
first two algorithms that we talked about,
and then this n log n performance for
merge sort.
And n log n is quite a bit
better than quadratic.
Now, I'm just going to stick
another algorithm into the table.
We haven't defined what quick sort is,
how it works.
It's another algorithm
out of a huge collection
of sorting algorithms out there.
It's sort of a cottage industry of
defining more and more sorting algorithms,
and we'll talk a little bit more
about why a little bit later.
But just so
you have a reference to another algorithm,
the Quick Sort in the best case
performs like n log n, and
in the worst place can have quadratic
performance, so On squared.
So, so far we just have best case and
worst case, but
let's add in that average case
performance in there, and
then think about what this
table is really telling us.
So for example, we might look for
which sort is going to be
the fastest in the best case.
So perhaps, we really just care about
performance and we're willing to maybe put
in some work to make sure that we lined
in the best case as often as we can.
And so, in that case we want to narrow in
on the cell on the table that
has the best performance.
And linear time beats every
other time in this cell, and
grows more slowly than n log n,
or than n squared.
And so O of n time is really great.
And so if we can have any sort of
confidence that we might stay in
the best case relatively often, then
Insertion Sort might be the way to go.
And in the next lesson Leo will be talking
about some cases in which Insertion Sort
might be really appealing.
Okay.
So, we've got this very optimistic, or
aggressive, approach that we
wanna get to the best case and
stay there as well as we can.
We might also wanna compare Merge Sort and
Quick Sort because if we look at their
best case and average case performance,
they both perform like n log n.
And so then we might focus in on the worst
case and say, well, why would we ever,
ever use Quick Sort if Merge Sort
has the same best case performance,
the same average case performance,
and does,
well, way better in the worst
case than Quick Sort?
Is there ever a reason in which we use
Quick Sort rather than Merge Sort?
Why did I even bother
putting it in the table?
And this leads us to the observation
that the asymptotics,
this performance bound that we've
been computing of the big O
class of the run timer, the number of
operations that the algorithm performs,
is really not the only measure
of goodness of an algorithm.
So this goes back to when we first
started talking about sorting
in the first course in the specialization.
We talked about other properties
that a sorting algorithm might have.
It might be stable, or it might use
very little auxiliary memory so
it might have, it'd be very nimble.
>> And so, when we're thinking about
choosing a sorting algorithm we want to
choose amongst the whole
array of possible algorithms,
taking run time performance as one
indicator of which one to use, but
also thinking about the use case and
the actual real-world factors
that influence which algorithm
is going to be right for us.