[SOUND] All right, we're ready to wrap
up our discussion of performance,
and I just wanna mention that
we're really only touching the tip
of the iceberg here in
terms of performance.
But we'll talk a lot more
about big O analysis and
asymptotics as the course progresses and
throughout the rest of the specialization.
So by the end of this particular video and
this lesson, you'll have a sense
of organizing the big O classes
according to their rate of growth, so
you'll be able to compare two classes.
And you'll also be able to avoid
some of the common pitfalls
in asymptotic analysis.
So let's start by thinking about
the classes that we've been talking about.
We talked about constant time, so O(1).
And those are really operations or
pieces of code that don't depend
on the size of the input at all.
And then we went on and
talked about O(log n).
And so, here you saw in the concept
challenge earlier on that the base of
the logarithm doesn't matter,
but log n does grow as n grows.
And then O(n) even faster,
and so we have linear time,
which grows more quickly than log n time.
And then as we keep going,
we see the, for example,
quadratic goes even faster than O(n).
Now, we haven't even touched
most of the complexity classes.
These are some standard ones
that are very useful for
the analysis of the code snippets
that we've been thinking about.
But there are others that come into
play very often when we do complexity.
For example,
exponential functions come in quite often.
And we'll talk about those
a little bit later on.
But also, basically any normal
usual function on integers
can be use as a complexity
function often if it's increasing.
And you can do similar
asymptotic analysis with those.
What you wanna keep in mind isn't all of
the complexity that comes into play there,
but rather, that these are useful
measures for giving us a sense
of how we can expect our algorithm
to perform as our input size grows.
And what we'd like is for
our run time not to go too fast so
that we can actually run our code and run
our algorithms on really big data, okay?
So that's one thing to keep in mind.
Now, let's think about if we have
two separate algorithms, and
we've done this computation, and
we've looked at the asymptotics of their
run time, of their performance, and we've
decided that algorithm 1 is O(log n) and
algorithm 2 is quadratic, so
its big O time is n squared.
So thinking back to the progression of
complexity classes that we just saw,
we might think that algorithm 2
is way worse than algorithm 1,
it's quadratic instead of logarithmic.
And so the question that
we might ask ourselves is,
does Algorithm 1 always run
faster than Algorithm 2?
Is it always going to be the case that
Algorithm 1 uses fewer operations?
And this is a really common
misconception that just because log n
grows more slowly than n squared, that
Algorithm 1 will always beat Algorithm 2.
And what you wanna keep in mind is that
the answer is no, it's not always going to
be the case that a logarithmic algorithm
will outperform the quadratic algorithm.
But in the long run,
as you get to bigger and bigger inputs and
really huge data sets that you're
processing, in that case then yes.
In that case,
the quadratic algorithm will be slower.
But, at the beginning, we might
have some initialization processes.
We might have some constants that will
mean for small cases, you might wanna
go with the n squared algorithm,
maybe because it's easier to implement.
It's easier to code up.
And so, you might want to go with
a slightly slower algorithm.
Slower in the worst-case, but one that,
for the cases that you care about,
the inputs, the real-world inputs
that you're using might be just fine.
And so that's a useful piece of
thinking of an asymptotics and
bringing it back to the real world.
All right, last but not least, we have
to think about what's an operation.
When we've been doing all of this
asymptotic analysis, really at the heart,
we've been counting operations.
At the heart of this process,
And at the beginning, we said that
an operation is some basic unit of
computation whose time doesn't depend on
the size of the input that we've given it.
And so the example that we started
with was this hasLetter method, and
we were going ahead and counting all
sorts of pieces of this code, and
each of the statements that
are boxed in yellow on the slide,
we counted as a single operation.
But, I wanna caution you about
counting methods as single operations,
because here for example, what we're doing
with this charAt method, is we're asking
for the character that occurs in index
i in a string, in the string word.
And so what the means is that we need
to interact with the string object and
ask for it to give us some piece of it,
the character at a particular index.
And what's going to happen is that
the run time of that operation
may depend on what that object looks like
and the internals of that object and
what that method charAt does.
And so when we're actually looking at
method calls as part of the analysis
of a bigger code snippet,
we really have to think about
whether that method call represents O(1)
work, just a constant amount of work.
Or whether that single
method call might represent
a whole lot more time that we might need
to include in our asymptotic analysis.
So as I said, this is really just the tip
of the iceberg, but we'll be continuing to
revisit this cycle of thinking about the
algorithm and data structure design, and
then thinking about the performance
implications of those designs.
And then going back and maybe refining
our algorithm or data structure design
to get better performance, and going
back and forth in this productive loop