[MUSIC]
Congratulations, you worked
through a difficult project and
hope you're proud of what you achieved.
>> Think back on all the code that you've
written, the theory that you've learned,
the data structures that you've analyzed
and even if it doesn't feel that way right
now, this material is really at
the heart of computer science and
will serve you well throughout
your career, and especially if and
when you choose to apply for a new job
that uses some software engineering,
this stuff will be really useful.
>> So,
we've had a lot of fun in this course.
And we hope you have, too.
And we hope that you'll also join us for
our next course in a specialization.
In that next course,
we're going to be looking at a new
data structure called a graph.
We'll also be looking at some
more advanced algorithms for
working with data in the graph.
So, we hope to see you there.