[MUSIC]
So now we're gonna dive in to
working with strings in Java.
This video is gonna introduce the basics,
and this may be familiar to many of you,
and if it is just go ahead and watch
this really fast or even just skip it.
But if not we wanna make sure
we've got the basics down for
everybody before we move forward.
So by the end of this video you'll be able
to describe how strings are represented
in Java, and then perform some
basic operations with strings.
So, going back to our task which is to
estimate the Flesch readability score for
a piece of text.
Again, our motivation here is that we
wanna be able to count the number of
words, syllables and
sentences in a string and
the way we are gonna represent
in a document that is.
And the way we're gonna represent
a document is just as one big long
string in Java.
So let's take a look in more detail
about how strings are represented.
Here are some basics about strings.
Strings in Java are objects, so they're
not primitive types they're object types.
And this means that they're represented
in your computer's heap, in the memory,
and the variables that refer
to them have references.
So I'm gonna draw you a memory model
diagram, and if you took our first course
in this specialization,
this will look familiar to you.
And if you didn't,
this our typical way that we draw
memory models of data in our programs.
So we have a variable declaration.
It gets a box.
We have a new object,
that's going to get created on the heap.
And remember that little
symbol next to that object,
that's just our way of representing
an actual object of a particular class.
Then the assignment operator
connects the variable
to the object with this reference,
which we represent as an arrow.
So here we have one string variable and
refers to a string object in memory, and
that string object stores some text.
How does that string
object store in the text?
It actually stores it as
an array of characters.
So we have one slot in the array for
each character in the string, including
that space between those two words.
All right, we can add to this code.
We have a second line of code here,
which declares another variable and
gives it the value of our first variable.
So just like any other object,
this results in two references to
the exact same object in memory.
Now you may get concerned at this
point and say wait a minute,
we have two objects, sorry two
references to the exact same object.
What if one of those
references changes our string?
Turns out, that's not possible.
In Java, strings are immutable, which
means that the objects that are in memory,
that are the strings,
can never be changed.
So there's no way to change
a string object once it's created.
Now, this doesn't mean that
you can't build strings.
Obviously, you've probably
done this already.
For example, you can append strings
together using the built in append method
inside the string class.
So here we have our first string,
which says Hello World!
And we append to that string,
It's a great day.
But it doesn't actually change
that first string object.
What it does is it creates
a whole new string object,
takes the text out of the first string
object, puts it in the second one, and
appends that text that we
want to append onto the end.
So one more object,
no change to that first object.
You can also use the + operator
to do string appends in Java.
I'm sure you've done this before, and
this does the exact same thing as that
appends method that I just showed you.
Again, no change to that
first object there.
Now this could get messy with all
these different string objects being
created in memory.
Strings could end up taking a lot of your
heap space and Java is aware of this fact
so they provide an optimization, which
is something called an interned string.
And I'm gonna tell you a little
bit about how that works.
This is a detail.
You don't have to worry too much
about it when you're programming, but
it's good to keep in mind.
So, we have on top the way that
we created the string before,
with that new operator, so
we said new String ("Hello World!").
That gave us the first string object
that you see over there in memory.
The second and third lines also create or
refer to string objects with
the same text, Hello World!.
However, this string here without the new
string before it, creates what's
called an interned string object.
Which is a single string object the Java's
going to use whenever we don't explicitly
create a new string object with the
keyword new and a call to the constructor.
So that first line there explicitly
creates a new string object, but
the second and third lines just refer to
the same interned hello world string,
that Java will create for
us if it doesn't exist.
So there's that intern string,
both of those variables refer to that.
So, let's talk about ways
of comparing strings.
There are two ways we can consider
comparing string objects in Java,
.equals, which is a method on the string
class, or equals-equals, which
is just that operator we've seen before
to compare the values of two variables.
And these two ways behave
quite differently when we consider the
underlying representation of the string.
So in this example, we have two strings
that we've created by calling new and
the constructor of the string class twice,
but
they store the exact same piece of text,
Hello World!
If we call .equals on one of the strings,
so text.equals (text2), this will return
true, because what .equals does is it goes
into the string objects and compares them
character by character, returning true if
they represent the same piece of text.
However, equals-equals behaves exactly
the same way it's always behaved.
It just compares the values
of the variables themselves.
And if we look in the box,
we can see that the variables themselves
store references to locations in memory.
So these two variables
store different references.
Therefore equals-equals is going to
return false when we compare them.
The lesson here is that we almost always
wanna use .equals to compare strings and
not equals-equals.
So that's a basic introduction to strings.
They're really powerful objects in
Java and they can do a lot of things.
We're gonna look at just some of
the things they can do in the next video