[MUSIC]
All right, in this video we're
gonna pick up working with strings,
looking at some of the built in functions
strings have so that you can learn about
strings enough to use them in
that first part of the project.
So by the end of this video you'll be
able to work with the built in String
functions in order to manipulate Strings.
Now as I mentioned, at the end of the last
video, Strings can do a lot of things, and
you can see on the slide the URL to
the API documentation in the Java docs.
And I am not going to put in this video an
explanation of every single method in that
library that would take forever and
it would be very boring.
What I am going to do is
just highlight five methods
that we think will be particularly useful
for you when you're doing your project.
But, at the same time, keep in mind
that whenever you have a doubt
you can always go back to those
Java docs to learn more and
to find more methods
that you might wanna use.
So we're going to look at these methods
in the context of solving problems.
So the first problem we're gonna
wanna think about solving is,
how do we calculate the number
of syllables in a piece of text?
That's needed to estimate
this Flesch score.
And in order to do that,
what we're going to need to do is,
we're gonna have to look at words,
character by character.
So, let's look at a function
that I've written.
This method takes in a String word,
and a character letter and
it just tries to determine does that
letter appear anywhere in the word.
The way it does this is it uses a loop, so
it's going to loop through each character
in the word and remember that Strings are
represented by a raise of characters so
Strings have a length method that will
return back to us the number of characters
in that String.
So this for loop's gonna execute once for
every position in the String.
Then it's going to check,
is the character at that position equal
to the letter that I'm looking for?
Again, this illustrates the use of
another built-in string method,
this charAt method.
So charAt takes an index,
i, in this case, and
it returns the character that's
at that particular index.
The character, remember,
is a primitive, so
we can compare this with the equals,
equals operator.
So if it's equal to the letter we're
looking for, we'll return true.
If the loop finishes and we didn't
find the character, we'll go ahead and
return false.
Okay, so this method works and
it illustrates a couple of things
in the built in String class.
Next I wanna use it to illustrate a kind
of for loop that you may not have seen,
or if you have seen it,
maybe you forgotten about it.
It's called a for-each loop and
this can be very handy.
So, the for-each loop
looks kind of like a for
loop, only the headers
a little bit different.
Instead of those three parts,
we just basically have two parts.
We declare a variable.
In this case, a character type variable,
C and then we have a colon.
And after the colon what we
have is some sort of list or
array that we want to loop over.
And what's gonna happen, each time for
each loop is C is going to get the value
of each position in that array.
So in this case our array,
is the array of characters inside
the word that we're looking at.
So a String class has this
built-in method called toCharArray
that returns back the array of
all the characters in the String.
Now, it's not the actual array of the
characters in the String, it's a copy of
the array of the characters in the String
because, remember, Strings are immutable.
So we're not allowed to get in there and
change the characters
in a particular String.
So c is going to iterate taking on
the values of each element in that array.
In this way, c will first get
the first character in the String,
the next time through the loop it'll have
the next character in the String and so
on and so forth.
So inside the for
each loop we just compare c directly
to the letter we're looking for.
If they're the same we return true,
otherwise,
if the loop ends we know it's
not there and we return false.
So at this point, what we're gonna do is,
we're gonna give you a couple of
end of year quizzes to see how well you
really understood what I just said.
And then we're gonna pick back
up working with this code.
All right, now that you're back, we
actually have one more challenge for you.
It's not gonna be a quiz, but
we do want you to pause the video and
think about this.
What I would like you to do,
is I would like you to modify this code,
so instead of just returning true or false
it returns the index of the first position
where it finds this particular
character that it's looking for.
So one thing we're gonna have to do is
we're have to change that method header
from boolean to returning an int, but
let's just assume that's already done.
Just focus on what you have
to change inside the code.
So go ahead and pause and
work on this now.
Okay, so we hoped you figured this out,
there actually aren't very many
changes we have to make to this code.
All we have to do is, because we have
this variable i that's tracking through
the position in the String, is that when
we find the character we're looking for,
instead of just returning true,
we can go ahead and change the code so
that it returns the index
where we found that position.
And that of course is
stored in the variable i.
If we get to the end,
we didn't find it, we wanna return that
flag that indicates we didn't find it,
which was negative 1, so we just replace
that return false with return negative 1.
And that's it.
So, it turns out that this method that
we just implemented is very similar to
a built-in method in the string
class called index of.
Index of takes, rather than
a single character, a String and
returns the index position in
the String that it was called on
where it first found the substring
that it was passed in.
So let's take a look at how this works.
Let's assume we have this piece
of text that you can see here.
Can you hear me?
Hello, hello?
And I wanna know what is
the index of the substring he.
Well if you asked Java this using
the indexOf method in the String class,
it will return eight because he first
appears at position 8 in this String.
Remember we start counting at 0 so
the index of c is 0 and the spaces count.
The spaces take up positions
in that String array.
So then when we count, you'll see that
h is the position eight in the array.
On the other hand, if we ask for
the substring He with a capital h,
it won't find it until position 17.
Because Java distinguishes between
little h's and capital h's.
Now, if you're worried about case,
Java has a couple of string methods
that can help you with that.
So and check out the equals ignore case,
two lowercase, and two uppercase methods,
also in the String class, which you can
read about in the Java documentation.
If you look for a String that's not there,
like help, Java will return negative one,
because that String does not appear at
all in the text that we're looking at.
Okay, now let's switch gears a bit.
We've talked about some methods
that would be useful for
counting the number of
syllables in a particular word.
Let's now look at how we're gonna count
the number of words in an entire document.
And in order to count the number of words
in an entire document, we need to be able
to split the String apart into
individual words, so we can count them.
Fortunately, Java has a built-in
method called split, and
what it takes is a pattern that
you would like to use to split on.
So in this example here,
with that same piece of text,
I'm calling the split method
with a space passed in.
So that's a space between those
two quotes, a single space.
And Java will say, okay, every space is
where I wanna split that String up and it
will return to me an array of the Strings
that are essentially between the spaces.
So it will be the words in that String.
That's great.
But what happens when we,
say, add an extra space?
I like to put two spaces
between my sentences.
Well split isn't quite gonna
work as we want it to.
So it's gonna interpret
that space quite literally.
And instead of giving me back a nice array
of all the words, it's gonna give me back
an array of the words with this
extra empty String in the middle.
And what that empty String is,
is it's the text that's between the two
spaces that are between the sentences.
There's no text there, the spaces
are right next to each other, but
because it needs to split there,
it needs to split among those spaces,
it says well, there's this thing here,
and there's nothing there, so
I'll just put an empty String in my
array of Strings that I'll return.
Well that's kind of unfortunate, but
the fortunate part is that
we can fix this problem.
So if you look at the Java
documentation for
the split method, you'll see that
it doesn't take a String, per se,
what it takes is something
called a regular expression.
We're gonna talk a lot more about regular
expressions in the next video, and
they're going to be our key to solving
the problem of splitting on not just
one space, but
any number of spaces in a string.