[APPLAUSE].
>> So, in this support video, what we'd
really like to do is take some time to
think about for-each loops, and
in particular, how they relate to strings.
So, by the end of this video you'll
be much more comfortable using these
programming constructs, and we'll see
a few examples of both pitfalls, and
advantages.
So in the core videos,
Christine presented this method,
hasLetter, which searches through
a given word and looks for
a particular letter, and she showed you
two implementations of this method, and
the second implementation she went
through uses a for-each loop.
And so what we're going to do now is think
about changing up this method a little bit
and seeing if similar constructs
can be used there too.
So, the method we'll be focusing
on is a replace method.
And what we'd like to do is replace
every occurrence of the character gone,
or we'd like to make it gone, and instead
put in a character that we'll call here.
Okay?
So we'll have two input characters and
this input string.
And what we'd like to return
is the modified string
that replaces all of the occurrences
of one character by the other.
Let's think about what would
happen if we gave it this string,
a space happy, a happy.
And what we're doing with this particular
replace method is we're going to replace
all the characters a by the character i.
And so if we're successful what we should
get returned back is i space hippy.
All right, so that's going to be our
test case that we always check our
work against.
And it's useful to have a small
example that we work with
when we're developing a new method.
So that's a good habit to get into.
So let's have our first attempt.
And we have some code up already.
And think about whether this
particular implementation of the method
successfully returns a modified
word that does what we wanted.