[APPLAUSE]
>> So
let's trace through the execution of this
particular implementation of the method.
And see what it does on
a sample piece of input.
And then we'll have a sense of
whether it's gonna work for us or not.
So when we're tracing through code,
we're going to
use the concept of Memory Model Diagrams,
and if you were with us for
course one of the specialization,
this will be very familiar.
So what we're going to do here is
illustrate the values of the variables and
how they change as we execute the code.
And so we're going to keep track of the
scope of the variables in different parts
of our diagram.
So in this method we're going
to be in the scope of replace,
which is the name of our method.
First, are the arguments or
the parameters to this method.
And so we know we've got the word
variable, and so we have a box next
to the name of the variable that is going
to store the contents of that variable,
the other parameters are gone and here.
And in this particular example,
let's figure out what the values
of these variables will be,
we're passing in a happy,
which is a string to the variable word.
Now strings are objects in Java,
which means over here in the heap.
When we put a happy in the quotes,
we create a new string object.
And within that string object is the array
of characters that are in that string.
And so we'll have that a happy.
Okay, so that's our string object
living here in memory, and
when we pass that object into our method,
what we're doing is we're creating
a reference from the variable
to that object in the heap.
All right, so
that's the first argument to our method.
The second two arguments are characters
and those are primitive type data.
And so that means that when we
pass them in we're actually
going to have copies of those characters
that are stored in these variables.
So gone is the character a and
here is the character i.
That's our memory model so
far for this method.
Now we can go into the body of
the method and see what happens.
The first line allocates space and
memory for a character array.
And so we're going to have the variable
cArray as part of our
memory model diagram.
And we have to figure out
what to put in the box,
the value of that variable and
that's the value that it's initialized to.
And what we see is that we
are going to give that variable
the value of word.toCharArray.
And so what that means is we're calling
the method toCharArray on the object word.
And so when we are trying to figure
out where the methods are and
how they behave, we're following the dots,
following the arrows.
And so we go to word,
that's in our memory model over here,
and then we follow the arrow and we see
that word refers to a string object.
And string objects have
these methods toCharArray.
The return, well, they don't
return the actual character array
that's stored in the object
because strings are immutable.
So Java doesn't want us to have
access to this particular CharArray.
Instead, it's going to create a copy
of this character array, a memory,
and then return to us a pointer
to this new array of characters.
And so cArray will point to this copy
of the character array that
was stored in the string.
And so now we can go on to the rest
of the method that we've written in replace,
and we notice that in this for loop, and
throughout the rest of
the execution of the method,
all we're working with is cArray, and
then characters associated with it.
And then at the end we're
trying to return word.
And so what we're going to return
is the object that was pointed
to by this variable, but
all of our work is over here.
And so there's no way for us to change
anything to do with this variable,
because all we're working
with is the copy.
So in this method,
what we return will just be
a pointer to the original string
that we came with, and it won't have
had any of the functionality to it that
we hoped for in the replace method.
In particular, all the a will still be a,
they won't have magically turned into i.
And so
this implementation is not going to work