[SOUND]
So we saw, when we went through that method,
that it actually didn't quite work for us.
And the problem that we ran into is
even though we declared this pointer
to an array of characters, cArray, and the
issue is that to toCharArray that method,
which was a copy of the words,
arrays of characters.
It doesn't let us access that
array of characters itself, and so
we ran into troubles as you saw, so let's
try to modify our method a little bit and
say what if we returned
a new string with cArray
as its input character array,
maybe that will work for us.
Does this method now successfully
return a modified word?
So we've tried again,
let's focus on what we've changed.
It's this last line over here where we
return something at the end of our method.
And notice that the beginning of the
memory model is really the same as what we
had because right now we're just
representing the input arguments,
the arguments and
parameters to the method.
Now as we did before the first step of
this method is to create a variable
that points to a copy of of
the character array of the string,
and so we're going to have that
represented in our memory model as well.
And just as before, what it's pointing to
in the heap is not the character array
that we had before, but
rather a copy that we create in the heap.
All right, and notice that what
we're returning at the end is a new
string object and the string object
is built out of this character array.
And so, maybe this will work.
So, in order to see that,
let's trace through what happened.
And so after we've declared and
initialized the character array cArray,
we now go into this for each loop.
And in this for each loop what
we're doing is we're going through
every character in
the cArray of characters.
And for each one,
we're looking at the character c, so
that so means that c becomes a new
variable in our memory model.
And so this is the new part for this
method so I'm using a different color.
And now we have to think about
what gets stored in this box, so
when we go through that
first iteration of the for
each loop we've declared this character
variable c, and what we store in it is
the contents of the first element of
the array pointed to by the cArray.
And so the contents of this first
element of the array is the character a.
Now notice this is a primitive type.
And so what that means is when we assign
the variable c to have this value,
what we're storing here is a,
the character a.
And notice that there's no
connection between this a and
the a that's stored over here.
They're different copies
of the character a.
And so in particular, when we go
through this body of the for loop and
we're checking whether the contents
of c agree with the content of gone.
And we say, oh this guy's an a and
over here we've stored a as well and so
that means we have to reassign.
The contents of c to,
instead of it's current value,
it gets the new value, whatever was
stored in the variable here, so that's i.
Notice that what that
assignment variable does,
is it changed the content
of the box pointed to by c.
But it doesn't change the content of
the character array pointed to by cArray.
And so even though we've noticed that
this a actually was the same as this a,
where we've changed the character
was down here and not up here.
And so even though we could go
through this for loop and make all of
the modifications to c that are necessary,
when we go ahead and return the value,
we're returning a new string object
that's based on this character array.
And this character array has
not been modified at all.
All of our modifications,
all of our assignment statements, have
just changed the contents of a variable c.
And not inside this character array.
And so this method implementation still
doesn't do what we're looking for.
It's not going to be our replace method.