[APPLAUSE]
>> As you saw,
again we ran into difficulties,
and this time,
the error was in a slightly
different place.
What happens when we do a for
each loop, is that when we ask for
every character c in the character
array cArray, what we get
is a copy of each value from the character
array stored in the variable c.
And so when we change the variable c,
we're changing that copy of the character.
We're not changing the contents of cArray.
And so
this implementation didn't work either.
And so try, try again, we don't give up.
Let's look at yet another implementation.
In here we're thinking, okay,
let's create a new array of characters and
let's access its elements one by one.
And maybe now we're going to have
a successful implementation.
And so what we're going to
do is trace through and
start our memory model from scratch.
So we can see how
everything fits together.
Cuz as you can see,
there's a little bit more code to
this candidate implementation.
So, we're working with
a replace method and so,
we're working in the scope of this
replace method call at the moment.
And, let's think about the candidate
method call down here.
And so, we start our memory model
with the parameters for this method.
So we have three parameters, we've got
word, we've got gone, and we've got here.
And remember that word is of type string,
and so that's an object type in Java.
And what we're going to be referring
to is an object in the heap
which we're going to denote in
our memory model over here.
And so in this object we have
stored the character array for
this particular string, and so
this character array is riding
out the string a space happy.
And so here's its representation
in our memory model.
For gone and here,
they're variables of type characters.
And so we're going to store copies of
those characters inside these boxes,
because these are primitive types in Java.
And so we've got gone is the argument,
the first argument and
it's got the character a,
and here is the character i.
All right, so far very similar to before.
But now let's look at
the body of the method and
what we've implemented this time.
So our first line declares
this variable c array.
And so, this is pointing
to an array of characters.
And in this case like before,
what we'd like to point to is
the array of characters that were
in this string pointed to by word.
But because strings are immutable
the method to character array
doesn't give us access to this particular
array, it gives us access to a copy of it.
And so in the heap we have a cop of this
array of characters and so here it is.
And then the method that we
called will give us a reference
to that copy of the array of characters.
Now what we're doing is we're creating yet
another array of characters.
Who knew we needed so many?
So now we're going to define
the variable cArrayMod
and what we're initialize this variable
to is a new array of characters.
Now remember,
when we declare an array of characters,
we need to specify
the length of that array.
And so the length that we wanna use is
the same length as the character array
pointed to by cArray, and
so that's length seven.
And so we're going to
allocate space in memory for
an array of characters that
will store seven characters.
Now we haven't said what the contents
of this array yet will be,
what the characters in there are, but
we've just got this space in memory and
then, cArrayMod will point to this array.
All right, one more variable declaration,
and that's this i over here.
And so
we create a box in our memory model for
this variable of type int,
and it's initialized to zero.
All right, so we've done all of the
preparation before getting into the for
each loop, and so now we're ready to
dive right into that for each loop.
And remember, what we're hoping that this
method does, is take this input string and
somehow return to us at
the end a version of this
array of characters where
each a is replaced by an i.
So we're really hoping to
see i hippy come back.
All right.
So in this, for
each loop we're going to step
through the characters in cArray.
And for each one of those characters,
we're going to store
them in the variable c.
So we also, in our memory model,
need space for this variable c that stores
the characters that come from stepping
through the array pointed to by cArray.
So the first one that we
point to is the one located
at the very beginning of the array and
that is a.
So the first value of
c is the character a.
And now what we do with that
first iteration of the for
loop is we first of all go immediately
into this conditional statement.
And we check whether the value of c is
equal to the value of the variable gone.
And in this particular case
those values are equal,
they're both have the value
of the character a.
So what we need to do is update the value
of cArrayMod at the index i, so zero.
And so what we wanna do is copy this
a into this position of the array,
and so here we go.
All right, so
we've completed the conditional branch.
And so we notice that at the end
of the body of the for loop,
what we still have to do is increment i,
the variable i.
And so we have a new value for
the variable i, it's going to be one.
And so we go back up to the top of the for
each loop and what that means is we want
to pick up the next character in
the array of characters cArray.
We've taken care of the first one and
now we're going onto the next one.
Now, what that means in terms of our
memory model, is that we update the value
of the variable c, to now be the value
that is next from that cArray.
Okay, so we go back to the top of the for
each loop, and
we do the same conditional branch.
We compare the value of c,
with the value of gone.
In this case, they're different,
they've got different values.
And so we have to look at the else
branch of the conditional statement.
And in this case, what we need to do is
still to update cArrayMod at index i.
So now we're at this
location in this array.
But instead of updating
it with the value here,
what we're updating it with is the value,
stored in c, and so that's a space.
Okay, we've done that, I'm not gonna draw
a space here, we'll just have the space,
and so we're done with the conditional and
we increment i.
And so i now becomes 2, and
we finish with this go around of the for
loop, we've taken care of
this character from cArray.
And so, next up would be h and so,
we'd have to update the value of c,
and we'd keep on going.
And, notice that, if we think
about this in a high level view,
as we iterate through the values of
cArray, updating c and updating i.
What we're doing each time of execution
of the conditional branch is whenever
this character happens to be an a,
we would replace it with
i.
Over here I put the value of gone instead
of here, so both of these should be i's.
But in all of the other locations, we just
maintain exactly the value that we had
in cArray as we go on and go on and
go on throughout the entire cArray.
Okay, so the only two places where we
have a different value in cArrayMod
from where we did in cArray are those
places where the character from cArray was
the one that is stored in gone which was
our cue for making sure that it gets gone.
Alright, so
after we've completed the for loop,
the for each loop, then we're ready
to return a value to the user.
And what we're returning
is a new string object.
That new string object is
constructed out of this new
character array that we created over here,
cArrayMod, and then filled in with values.
And so, the characters that are returned
to the user into the form of a string
Are really what we wanted, i space
hippy just like we created over here.
Which is fantastic because we've been
working on this replace method and trying,
and trying, and trying and
finally we go it.
But notice how much work we had to put in.
We had to create not only one but
two copies
of the character array that was given
to us inside that word string object.
And then we had to do some fancy
things with indices, as well.
So, we'll talk in a minute about
what this solution does and
what it tells us about for-each
loops in this context.