[APPLAUSE] So we finally succeeded in
implementing the method that we wanted to.
But it was a lot of work.
And, what you'll notice when you think
back to the work that we did is that we
were kind of implementing the usual old
for loop, where we start with some index.
And we incremented as we go through and
iterate the for-loop a bunch of times.
And so, even though we have
a for-each loop in our method body,
we're not really using the for-each loop.
We kind of have to do a regular old
indexed for loop in addition to it.
And when you see yourself trying to work
really too hard to implement some sort of
functionality, that's a clue that
maybe we're using the wrong construct.
And what's at the heart here with the
trouble with using the for-each loop is
we're trying to change
the contents of an array.
So, the moral of this story
is that in this context,
the for-each loop is not
the right tool for the job.
The other thing we'd like to keep in
mind is that even when we successfully
implemented this method, when you think
back to the parameters that we were given,
and the fact that we were given
a string to begin with, the word,
even though we return
a modified version of the word,
we output something that looks
like i-hippy instead of a-happy.
What we're outputting doesn't actually
change the parameter that we gave,
that we started with.
So the input variable, the parameter that
we have, that string object doesn't get
changed, doesn't get impacted by the work
that we've done in this replace method.
And that's because strings are immutable.
So, even though we were
able to produce hippy,
even though we were able to do that
replacement of the characters,
in terms of giving back a return object,
the original string object didn't change.
And that is a useful thing to keep in mind
when we're working with strings in Java.