[MUSIC]
All right, in this video we'll look at
just the basics of something called
regular expressions.
Regular expressions themselves
are a really big field of study,
way too much to fit into a single video,
or even into a single lesson perhaps.
So we're just gonna very much
touch on the basics that you will
need to accomplish your project.
So, by the end of this video you'll be
able to write regular expressions to match
String patterns in Java, as well as write
regular expressions to split strings.
And this is the functionality
you'll need for your project.
So again, going back to the problem here
that we left off in the last video with,
we wanted to be able to split the sentence
apart using not just a single space but
any number of spaces to
use as a split delimiter.
And we said that the key to this was
going to be regular expressions.
So let's look at what regular expressions
are and how we can use them in Java.
And we're gonna build them
sort of from the ground up.
In a nutshell, a regular expression is
just an expression of a pattern that we
are trying to match, and
from the most basic point of view,
a regular expression can
be just a simple character.
And this is why it worked when we passed
a space character into our split method,
because we are telling Java,
match literally a single space as
the pattern you are trying to look for.
So Java matched a single space, and
every time it saw a single space,
it said, okay,
here's where I want to split.
But that's pretty, pretty basic,
there's not too much we can do with that.
So we can also combine regular expressions
to form more complicated ones and
there are three ways
that we can combine them.
We can combine them with repetition.
We can combine them with concatenation,
in other words, putting them together.
We can combine them with alternation,
meaning either/or,
choose one expression or the other.
We're going to start by
looking at repetition
because that's what we're after.
We're trying to figure out how can
we match not just one space but
any number of spaces.
So we saw that we can match one space
just by passing it in as a string.
If we wanna match more than one string,
we can use the plus operator
in a regular expression.
So this is the first way we can do
repetition in our regular expression.
If we put a plus after some regular
expression, this case just a space,
what we're indicating is
that we want to match one or
more of these regular
expressions in a row, so
in this case we're going to match
against one or more spaces in a row.
So now when Java does the split,
it always tries to match as many spaces
as possible when it does the match.
So it will match just one space but
in this case it will also match two.
And it will consume those two
spaces as the token it matched and
give us back just the text on
either side of those two spaces.
Now it can get a little bit tricky
to think about regular expressions
when we're splitting strings.
We find it's much easier to think about
regular expressions in terms of matching,
what it actually gets matched.
So, we're going to transition over
into the way you'll be mostly using
regular expressions in the project.
So, let me introduce to you a little
bit of the code from the project, and
it's this abstract class called Document,
which you're going to use to
represent a document of text.
It has a member variable
called text that stores
all the text in a particular document.
Now notice that this class is abstract,
so we'll be providing you with some of
the code that makes the Document class but
we'll also have some abstract methods in
there that you're going to have to
override when you write your code.
You'll be writing subclasses
of this Document class.
One of the methods that we are providing
for you is this method called getTokens.
And what the getTokens method
does is it takes a pattern
which is a regular expression of
the tokens that you are looking for.
So this is a regular expression that
describes what kind of tokens you
want to get back from this method.
And then the method will
return a list of those tokens
that match that regular expression.
So, let's apply this back to our one or
more spaces example.
If we have a document that contains
the text Hello, space space, hello?
And we call the getTokens method on it,
what it's going to do is it's going to
find those two spaces between the words.
And it will just return us a list
containing a single string
with those two spaces.
So again, now we are preserving the text
that matches the regular expression,
rather than getting rid of it
like we did in the split method.
So we're gonna use this
getTokens method to illustrate
some of the other ways we can
combine regular expressions.
The second way we're gonna look
at is called concatenation, and
this is the idea of just putting regular
expressions together one after another.
So if I have a slightly
more complicated string,
say I have a document with the string,
splitting a string, it's easy as 1 2 33!
Right?
And I now call getTokens using
the regular expression IT,
this is actually concatenation
of two regular expressions.
It's a concatenation of
the regular expression I and T.
And this is going to match whenever it
sees those two regular expressions,
the I, T, one after another.
So in this case it will match on I, T,
in splitting, and it will match on I,
T in it's, we get back a list of
just the two strings, "it", "it".
We can combine concatenation and
repetition, so
now I've got a regular expression that has
i followed immediately by one or more ts.
So let's see how this changes what we're
going to get back from the get tokens.
This time, we not only get
the i t out of splitting, but
because we've asked for one or more ts,
Java is going to be greedy and
consume as much of that text as it can
that matches that regular expression.
So here it will match i t t, and then that
i after i t t doesn't match anymore so
it will stop and just say ok, i t t,
that's the first match that I found.
The next match it finds again is
just that I-T in it's, once again.
If you're not sure of the grouping
of the precedence order,
you can always use parentheses to do
explicit grouping in regular expressions.
So if I wasn't sure if that plus
was going to apply to just the T or
to the I-T,
I could have put the t in parenthesis.
It turns out that plus binds
tighter than concatenations, so
it applied only to the t.
But when in doubt, just go ahead and
use those parenthesis.
There's another form of
a repetition operator, a star.
It's very similar to the plus, but
this time it means zero or more.
So this regular expression, if you might
want to take a moment to think about, what
this regular expression is going to match
against in our string that we have there.
Alright, so it's going to match an i
followed by zero or more ts and in
this case it's going to return that list
that you see there and I've highlighted
the places in that document string where
it matches that regular expression.
So you can see that
because it matches zero or
more Ts sometimes it
matches just a plain I.
So we've talked about concatenation,
putting two regular expressions together.
Repetition, repeating
a regular expression.
And now we have this notion of alternation
or an either or kind of choice.
The way we represent or in a regular
expression is just with a vertical bar.
So what you see here is
a regular expression that
actually combines concatenation and
alternation and
will match either the pattern I-T or
the pattern S-T.
So if we apply that regular expression
against this string, you can see the text
highlighted in blue is what's going to be
returned, which is just it, st, and it.
Another way we can do alternation
is by creating these things
called character classes.
So when we put characters in square
brackets inside the regular expression
that we're looking for, what Java will
match is any character inside that set.
So here I have the character class 1,
2, 3.
Java is going to match any single
character 1, 2, or 3, and I'll get
back the list that you
see there of 1,2,3,3.
Notice that it matched the 3s
separately because that character
class says that I want a single
character that's either a 1 a 2 or
a 3, not more than one character,
just a single character at a time.
You can think about how you might
change that to be multiple characters.
And that's just a foreshadowing of what's
coming up in our concept challenge.
We can also express inside these
character classes ranges using a dash.
So if I say one dash three inside
a character class that means match
any number, any numeral,
any character between one and three.
So in this case it matches one,
two, three, and three again.
I can use this same range
functionality with letters.
So I can say match any character
between a little a and a little f.
And that will match all the characters
in this string that are alphabetically
between little a and little f.
And I'll get back this.
And then finally, the last piece of
these regular expressions that I want
to introduce to you is this carat.
And what this carat does
inside a character class
is it excludes all of the characters
inside that character class.
So you're basically saying, match anything
that is not one of these characters.
So let's break down what this regular
expression that I've written here actually
does.
I'm saying that carat, which means NOT,
so none of these characters should match.
So I don't want any characters that
are between little a, and little z.
I don't want a 1, I don't want a 2, I
don't want a 3, and I don't want a space.
So all of those characters,
don't match them.
Anything else, please match them and
give me what you find.
So when I use this regular
expression to get Tokens
what I'm going to get back
is all the single characters
that are not one of the character
class that I just set out.
And so that includes the capital S,
remember in Java lower case letters and
upper case letters
are represented differently.
So the capital S, the comma,
the apostrophe, the exclamation point, and
the capital R all match
the regular expression.
So those are the very basics
of regular expressions.
We've got a concept challenge,
and some support videos, but
this should be enough to get
you going on the project.