[MUSIC]
So I remember the first few times that
I learned about regular expressions,
I was thoroughly confused.
And this happened quite often, actually,
because my research area turns out to be
something that uses regular expressions,
and thinks about regular
expressions all the time.
And so I would go into these pretty
advanced seeming seminars, and right from
the get go, I was going back to basics and
saying, what does this mean again?
What are all these symbols?
And I felt kind of embarrassed that I
wasn't able to get it right away, and
it seemed like everyone else around
just sort of knew the lingo, but
then I realized that it's okay not to
have sort of internalized everything.
And that I just needed to
cut myself some slack.
And go back to thinking
about the definitions.
And think about what each
of the symbols meant.
Because what was really confusing for me
is distinguishing between the pattern and
how we denote the pattern, and then,
thinking about the strings that match it.
And so having these two different kinds
of strings that are being involved in
the regular expressions.
And really understanding
the different roles that they play.
So what really helped me is,
actually thinking about these regular
expressions in a few different ways.
One of the ways that you can
do that is using automata.
And that's something that if you
continue in computer science and
when you continue in computer science,
you can learn a lot more about.
But, the moral of the story is that
when you come across something that may
seem some kind of intimidating,
what I find really helpful is to,
first of all, try to take a deep
breath and cut yourself some slack.
But, then also,
try to think of the different ways to
understand the definition and
to think about the problem.
And sometimes,
one of those alternate perspective
will just click a little bit better.