For those of you who have already
taken a course of this before,
you're already pros at
doing concept challenges.
For those of you who are new to us,
let's talk through the details
again of a concept challenge.
The idea behind a concept challenge,
is for you to pause and
trace all the problems yourself.
We're gonna pose a problem and
then give you an end video quiz about it.
Try to solve that problem and then after
you've come up with an answer for it.
Try to discuss that with friends or
colleagues that are taking the course.
This is a great time to get them all
together and talk about the concepts.
If you don't have them around you can
always watch the UC San Diego learners
talk about the concepts themselves.
After you've listened to those
explanations and talked about it.
Then you can try to answer
the question again.
After you've asked the question again,
you can confirm your understanding
based on our explanation.
All right, so
let's just dive right into it.
What we're gonna try to do is keep
working with regular expressions.
So what I have here is the string below,
which is splitting a string and
it's easy as one, two, 33, right?
If I try to do getTokens on that and
give it a regular
expression which is [1-3].
It's gonna give me back one,
two, three and three.
But what I really want
back is the numbers here.
I want one, two and 33.
So your challenge here, is what
regular expression should I put there?
>> Hi I'm Joshua.
>> My name's Brianna.
>> And I'm Allen.
>> Okay, what do you guys think about B.
I think it might be
the correct answer because,
I think the comma would be used as
a delimiter and separate one, two, and 33.
>> Yeah.
>> But, because it's in the brackets,
it might be taken as a literal symbol.
So it's gonna be looking for commas.
>> Oh, okay.
>> Yeah, I'm kinda, hm.
I think I'm kind of leaning
towards what Bree said.
That the commas might be like,
it's not a symbol like we use
to separate different terms.
>> Since it's in the brackets.
Like, if you look at E,
there's no brackets in there.
>> Yeah and I think I remember that
the brackets kind of say that look for
a comma specifically.
Rather than separate one, two, and 33.
So I don't think it'll quite
give us what were looking for.
>> Okay, and then C has numbers zero
through nine, and then it has a plus sign,
which means one or
more of any value from zero to nine.
I think that would work.
>> You think?
I think, hm, but won't it give us one,
two, three and three?
Because it'll split up the 33,
cuz it's looking for
just one digit between zero and nine.
So it'll give us one, two, three, three.
Instead of one, two, 33, right?
>> No, because the plus sign let's you
have more than just one individual value.
>> So it would be like, how do you
mean more than one individual value?
>> So you can have a zero, and then you
can have a one, you can have a two.
You can also have a zero, zero, a one,
one, a two, two, a three, three.
>> Oh okay, I see.
So, it could be like three,
three, or five,
five, or six, six or things like that.
>> I think that's just more than one.
>> Oh but, would it also work for
the list that the last character we were
looking for ends up, 33 would be 34.
>> So it wouldn't work for 34 or
57, or something like that.
>> Yeah, it's like,
instead of like one, two, 33.
It was one, two, 34, or some letter.
>> I think it would.
>> Yeah I think it might work,
because it'll just look for
any digit, like three, four.
It doesn't have to be
the same one exactly.
Okay.
>> Okay.
>> Let's move on to answer d, then.
So answer d has a star,
and it's asking for
characters one through
three rather than a plus.
You think that changes the answer?
Cuz I'm leaning towards,
if I think it'll be the same.
Where, like Bree said before,
it'll search for like one or one one,
or two and two two, or
three and three three.
So it'll give us this, what we have right
here, one two and three, three right?
>> Yeah, except you'll also
be counting for zero one.
So every time you have no ones,
you're gonna get a space.
>> So, basically anytime
you have an empty string.
I think it would include
those empty strings.
>> Oh right, cuz it's a star.
So, star means like zero, okay.
Okay, so I guess D wouldn't work either.
So, what about E?
>> As one, or two, or 33?
>> What do you think?
>> I think it wouldn't work,
because I was thinking more about
the ones of one and two and three.
But this has a line, which means or.
So I don't think it would
be looking exactly for
the list that we're looking for,
one, two, and 33.
>> Right, we are looking for
one and two, and 33, so.
>> But the and
might put them all together.
So that it's one and
two and 33, all together.
So if you're evaluating-
>> Right, one and two and 33,
that's our answer, right?
>> Right, but if you've got,
you're scanning through each and
every single number, right.
So you're gonna look at the first one.
Is the first number a one,
and a two, and a 33?
That wouldn't really make sense.
>> Okay,
we should look at them separately.
>> Yeah.
>> Look at one separately,
and look at two separately-
>> With the or.
>> and look at 33 separately.
And that's the point of the or.
So okay.
>> Welcome back.
I hope the UC San Diego
learners video was helpful.
Somewhat similar to what they did.
What we're gonna do here is
essentially walk one by one, and
talk through whether or
not that approach would work or not.
So option A was bracket 1233 bracket.
The idea here is well maybe
that would capture 33.
The problem here is if
it's within the brackets,
all it's gonna say is include one more
three, but you've already included three.
So all you get is the same thing.
In fact if you try to run this.
All you'll get back is the same thing
you had before, which is just one, two,
three and three.
So this didn't quite work.
Option B tries to split
this up using commas.
The problem is, just like the last
example, all that adding those commas did
was to simply add comma to the group of
letters that we're already looking for.
So, now we're gonna look for
one, two, three, and comma.
If I run this on the code,
what am I gonna get back?
We're gonna get comma,
one, two, three, three.
So this didn't work either.
All right, next one, option C.
This one said in brackets [0-9]+.
Remember that plus means one or
more of these elements.
If this was your answer, you were right.
What this is gonna do is look for
anything between zero and nine.
If it finds at least one,
look for more adjacent ones.
So what this is gonna do then is find one,
two and 33,
which is exactly what we were looking for.
Let's keep looking at our
other options though,
cuz this was a select all that apply.
So there may be more
than one right answer.
The next idea is to look for
one through three with an asterisk.
Now, the asterisk,
in regular expressions means zero or more.
This might look like it's gonna work, but
you have to be careful about the zero or
more.
Because if you look at the letter S,
are there zero or
more one through threes there?
Well, yeah, there's zero.
Oh, shoot.
That means it's gonna match everything,
right?
So what you're gonna get then is you're
gonna get every single letter matching and
give you back an empty string, because
there isn't a one through three there.
It does, in fact,
give you one, two, and 33,
but it gives you a whole
bunch more garbage.
So this is not what we want either.
Now what if we just said,
I want either one, or two, or 33?
Would that work?
Yeah, actually that's
gonna work just fine too.
The problem is, now that we have two
right answers, it'd be useful to say,
well which one's better than the other?
So, given [0-9]+.
And either one, or two, or 33.
Which do you think might be better?
Go ahead and take a few seconds and
think about it.
If your answer is C, you're spot-on.
[0-9]+ is gonna capture essentially
any non-negative integer.
That's fantastic.
Whereas if I try to do
the same thing with E.
How am I gonna capture
any non-negative integer.
I have to do something like zero,
or one, or two, or three, or
four, all the way out to
any possible integer.
I can capture it so concisely with option
C that, that is just far more versatile.
And that's essentially
the better of these two choices.
Regular expressions
are incredibly powerful, and
I hope you continue to use them as
part of your programming arsenal.