So in this support video, our goal is
to walk through some of the regular
expressions that you'll
be using in the project.
So, by the end of this video,
you will be able to
write the regular expressions that you
will need in the programming assignment.
So, big caution, spoiler alert,
by the end of this video,
you will really see the solution.
So if, like me, you like to try to
figure these things out on your own
before someone spoils the end and
tells you the answer, stop now.
Try to work through it yourself, and
then if you get stuck, do come back and
we'll work through it together.
But if you watch this video,
you will see the solution.
So let's get to it.
But if you need to go away and
then come back, please do that.
All right, so just remember the context
what we're doing in this project
is we're processing this text document.
And what we'd like to do is break it
apart into constituent pieces, and
then we'll be able to compute that flush
index by looking at the numbers of words
and the number of syllables and
the number of sentences.
And so we have the helper method that's
given to us in the abstract class
Document, and
this helper method is called, getTokens.
And what we do is we feed it in a string,
and it outputs a list of strings.
So what we give the getTokens document,
sorry, getTokens method
is a regular expression that defines
the tokens that we want out.
So that regular expression is going
to match to what we want to see
out of the big text that we give it,
the big string that we give it.
Okay, and
then what's returned to us is a list
of all those pieces of the big text
that match the regular expression.
So then, our task is to fill in what
regular expression we want
depending on the context.
So, for example, one of the first methods
that you'll be writing in this project
is the getNumWords method.
And so what we'd like to do is figure out
what the words are that are part of this
big, big string that represents
the document that we're processing.
And so
we'd like to separate out each word, and
then we'll have a big list of those words.
And then all we'll have to do afterwards
is look at the size of that list, and
that size of that list of tokens that are
returned is exactly the number of words
in the document.
So, the big conceptual challenge and
nugget in this getNumWords method
is really focusing in on what
the regular expression it is that we
should be using to separate out
the words in the big document.
Okay, so we want to fill in
those red question marks.
And what we'll be filling in
those red question marks with
is the regular expression
that will match any word.
Now, in order to understand what
it means to match any word,
we need to figure out
what constitutes a word.
So we're going to not try to
delve too deeply into grammar and
dictionaries and language theory.
And we're going to use the definition of
a word that we suggest in the project
description, and we're going to say
that a word is a contiguous sequence of
alphabetic characters.
So that means that we're going to
ignore things like apostrophes.
We're going to ignore numbers,
numerals, and we're just going to
focus in on consecutive sequences
of alphabetical characters.
Okay, and so
let's take a minute or second and
try to think about how we would fill in a
regular expression that represents whether
it matches any contiguous sequence
of alphabetic characters.
So pause if you'd like and think about it.
And now let's at least try one approach.
So perhaps we might fill it with saying,
well,
alphabetic characters are anything
that's either lowercase or uppercase.
And I would like my regular expression
to match any character in the set
a through z lowercase, or
A through Z, uppercase.
And that seems like a reasonable approach.
So let's think about what's now
circled in the regular expression, and
think about whether it works.
Well, what do you think?
There's a bit of a bug here, and
the bug comes with wanting words
that have more than one character.
So, if you remember
the square brackets notation,
what it means is I wanna match a single
character that is within the collection of
symbols that I'm putting
in the square brackets.
But for our words what we'd like
is a sequence of characters.
And so what we're going to say one or
more of the following set of characters.
And so what we need to do is to add that
plus symbol after the square brackets,
and that will let us match to any
contiguous non-empty sequence
of alphabetic characters.
All right, so this is the correct regular
expression now for matching two words.
And so now the getNumWords method
will process our big string that
represents our document and separate
out each of the consecutive sequences
of alphabetic characters, and spit
them out into one big list of strings.
And then we'll be able to
return the size of that list
as the number of words in our document.
Okay, so we've got this method sorted out.
And now let's move on to the next method
that you're implementing in the project.
And this would be a good point as well to
pause if you feel pretty confident about
how, about this solution, and
you want to try yourself for the next one.
The next method that we'll
tackle is the getNumSentences.
So take this opportunity to work
on it yourself, if you like.
And then come back to confirm your answer,
if that's what you would like to do.
Okay, now that we're here, let's
remember what constitutes a sentence.
So a sentence, well again we're not going
to be to worried about grammatical,
and this isn't going to
be a perfect solution.
But a pretty good approximation of what
a sentence looks like is a sequence of
characters that at their end have
an end of sentence punctuation.
So when we think about a sentence,
we know that it's usually ended by either
a period or an exclamation mark or
a question mark.
And so what we're going to do is that
think about any sequence of characters
that has that at the end,
we'd like to consider a sentence.
Now, we don't wanted to include that
last symbol as part of our sentence.
And so we'd like just the beginning
part to be considered the sentence.
And so now what we have to do is
figure out what regular expression
will exactly match to the sentence part,
without the punctuation at the end.
All right, so
how do we fill in those question marks?
And this is a little bit different from
what we were doing with the words before.
With the words, we were talking about what
each character in the word would look
like, and we knew that they
were alphabetical characters.
Whereas here, we're talking
about some perhaps ill-defined
collection of characters, but
all we care about it the very end.
And so
that seems a little bit harder to do.
In order to rephrase this definition into
something that maybe is more amenable to
writing as a regular expression,
we wanna think about a sentence as, well,
it's a collection of things that don't
in the middle of them include the end
of sentence punctuation.
So a way of working with this
definition in a way that lets us
write it as a regular expression
is to actually tweak it a bit, and
try to find an equivalent formulation
that maybe matches the operations that we
have a little bit better.
And so, one way of thinking about this
definition is that it says, we want
a sequence of characters that doesn't
include the end of sentence punctuation.
So we want all of the characters
in the string that we matched to
not to be end of sentence punctuation.
And we have a way of doing
that in regular expressions.
So remember the caret symbol.
So this caret symbol says,
I don't want things
from the following collection of
characters in the string that I match to.
And so, which characters don't we want?
We don't want exclamation marks.
We don't want question marks,
and we don't want periods.
But all the other characters are okay.
And we want any number of them.
So that + at the end of
the regular expression
says that we would like to match
a non-empty sequence of characters.
And all the characters that are not
in that non-empty sequence have to
be something other than
the end-of-sentence punctuation.
And so here we have the regular
expression that will correctly match to
each of the sentences.
And so once we call getTokens
with this pattern as its input,
then the result is going
to be a list of strings.
Each string is going to be a sentence,
and we can count the size of that list
to give us the number of
sentences in our document.