[MUSIC]
So the last lesson we talked a lot
about the processing library, and
we've had some people ask us hey, is this
a course about processing or about Java?
What's going on here?
Why do I need to know all these details
about processing when really I want
to become a confident
Java software engineer?
And there's a lot of merit to that.
But what we're hoping that you get
out of this course is how to use
whichever tools are at your disposal to
come up with a really exciting project or
product that you want to build.
And sometimes that means using
libraries like processing.
And that's a good thing.
So as you use these libraries,
as you develop your code,
you're not necessarily going to become
an expert in one particular library, but
you want to become proficient and
comfortable enough in figuring
out what pieces of those libraries
are going to be useful for this project.
And so what we're doing now is building
on our confidence and comfort level with
processing so we can apply that
knowledge to building the graphical
application that displays geospatial
data and earthquakes around the world.