[SOUND] In this support video, I'm gonna
talk to you a little bit more about
documentation and how you'll be
using it throughout this course and
particularly in the homework assignment,
in the programming assignment that you'll
get started on at the end of this module.
So in the last lesson, I showed you this
page for the processing documentation.
And it has a bunch of methods that
you'll find really useful when
you're trying to draw shapes and
change the colors of your GUI display.
So let me just highlight a few,
it's a pretty big page.
The few that we looked at.
So we're here in this 2D Primitives.
We wanna look at ellipses, lines,
points, rectangles, so on and so forth.
We've got the color methods over here.
You can change the background color,
you can change the stroke color,
the fill color of shapes,
so on and so forth.
And you can play with any of
these methods if you want but
let me give you a couple more
that you might find useful.
Particularly implementing the key of
that map which is these typography
functions down here.
So these are methods that you can
use to draw text on your GUI.
So in particular this method here text(),
that's what's gonna create a little
box where you can put
some text on the display.
And then down here are a bunch of methods
that allow you to change the attributes
of that text.
And again, with any of these methods,
the best way to get to know how
to use them is to click on them.
And it'll take you to a page that
gives you a whole bunch of examples
on how to call that method and what visual
implications that will have when you pass
different arguments into the method.
The other thing I want to talk
about is the documentation for
the unfolding maps library.
So this is at this URL that
you'll open up when you're
doing your programming assignment.
unfoldingmaps.org/javadoc/ and it gives
you information about all of the classes
and methods that are built in to
the unfolding maps library and this is
a library that you've downloaded as part
of that starter code that you set up.
But it can be pretty overwhelming because
it seems to have a lot going on here.
So, let me help you navigate.
What you see up here in this corner
right here, this is all of the classes,
or sorry, all of the packages that
are defined in the unfolding maps library.
And as you know, from looking at the
Eclipse starter code, packages are just
little ways to organize your classes, so
that they're a little bit more organized.
And this windows's only really useful if
you know what package your looking in.
If you just know the name of the class,
you don't necessarily want to look here.
But if, for example you know that you
only care about the map providers,
which is this package right here, you
could click on this and what it will do
is it will limit this display down here,
which is where you see all the classes.
So if I click providers up here then what
I see down here are only the classes
that are part of that package.
And that can be useful because this can
give you all the different possibilities
for what map providers you can use.
So here's the Google map provider,
here's a whole bunch of
different Google map providers.
There's a bunch of different other,
there's some Microsoft map providers,
there's an open map surfer provider.
So there's a lot of different
map providers that you can
play around with and perhaps you already
played around with in that first module.
But if you don't know what
package you're looking in,
then you can just click
here to All Classes, and
this will give you a list of all the
classes that are provided by this library.
All right, so let me go to some classes
in particular that you'll find useful for
this part of the project.
The first one is down here.
It's called SimplePointMarker.
This is the class that you're
gonna be implementing.
You're gonna be creating instances of this
class to create those markers on your map.
So you can click on it, and
what you're gonna see on the right hand
side is all of the different methods and
fields that this class has.
So you can see that it has a few
different constructors and
we recommend using this constructor
here that takes a location.
That will just create a simple
point marker at a given location.
And if you want a little more information
about this constructor you can
click on it.
It gives you a slightly expanded
view of the documentation so
you can learn more about it that way.
And then there's a whole bunch
of different methods that you
can use that are already implemented here.
Now just a caution
against this draw method.
This draw method,
you should not call explicitly.
This is called automatically for you, so
do not call the draw method explicitly.
We're gonna learn more about
that in the next module, but for
now just know, don't call draw
on the simple point marker.
So then that might raise the question
of how are you going to draw the simple
point markers?
Well, it all goes back
to the unfolding map.
So here's the other class that you'll want
to rely on this Java documentation for,
which is the sort of main class that your
adding everything to to visualize the map.
And so this unfolding map class
you can see we've already
looked a little bit at the various
constructors that is has.
But you can see that it has a whole
bunch of different constructors.
So you can play around with
constructing these unfolding
map objects using different
parameters as you like.
And then, you can see that
it has a bunch of methods.
It has a lot of methods.
And in particular, for this assignment,
some of the methods that you're going to
find useful are things like addMarkers.
For example, this method here takes a list
of markers and adds them to the map.
And once those markers are added to
the map, you'll see them appear.
This is, once they get added to the map
that's what causes Java to automatically
call the draw methods in the markers,
and displays those markers for you.
So those are just a few useful classes and
methods that you'll want to use on your
programming assignment for this module.
So in addition to the documentation for
processing and
for unfolding maps, Java itself
actually provides documentation for
all of its libraries and classes and
all the methods on those classes.
And you can find that at this URL here and
you can do a Google search for
Java documentation.
One thing to note is that if you're
working in Java version 7, you'll wanna
change that 8 to a 7 so that you match the
version of Java that you're working with.
But what you can see basically here is
every single class that Java implements.
And this can be really useful when you're
working with a class that you don't really
know that well or
that you've forgotten a little bit about.
So we encourage you to also use
the standard Java documentation as well.
In general it's really to your
benefit to start to get comfortable
playing around with this documentation and
using this documentation.
Because in the real world, and
even in this class, we're not gonna tell
you every single thing you need to know
in order to use some library code.
Using library code is extremely common.
And there's no instructor sitting there,
telling you, oh,
you should use this class and
you should use this method.
It's up to you to read
the documentation for that library, and
hopefully it's good documentation,
so that you can figure out how to use
those classes and those methods yourself.
This will also drive home the importance
of documenting your own code.
When you start writing code that
you will provide to others to use,
all they're gonna have is this
documentation to go by, so
it a really good idea to make it as
complete and as useful as possible.