[MUSIC]
People always say that it's important to
document your code, but we don't always
talk about why, and there's a couple
different reasons we do it.
One is because you want your code
to be usable by other people.
If you've written the world's best
library for string parsing or
other stuff like that, but no one can
figure out how to use it, it's no good.
And so there's one reason right there.
Documentation might be in the form of
an external document, a how-to guide,
a design document or something like that.
Or it might be in the form of something as
simple as documents inside of your code
saying, here's how you use this function,
these are what we're looking for, for
these parameters, and stuff like that.
There's other reasons for
documenting your code too, though.
Somebody once said, you should always code
as if the person who ends up maintaining
your code will be a violent
psychopath who knows where you live.
That's a little extreme, I haven't run
into too many violent psychopaths in my
professional career, but
it is something to bear in mind.
You're writing code that other people
are gonna have to maintain, and so
this means not just writing documentation
for the parts that other folks will use,
here's how you use my object or
here's how you call this function.
But it's also writing documentation for
the people who will have to go in and
fix your code, or extend it to do
different things or other stuff like that,
as needs or the environment changes.
And sometimes that violent
psychopath might be you.
There have been times when, as
a professional, I've had to go back in and
revisit code that no one has looked at for
years.
And I go in there, I'm like,
wow, who's the idiot who wrote
this stuff in the first place?
Oh, wait, that's my name on this file,
I'm the idiot, yeah, okay.
It's not always somebody else,
or from a different perspective,
that somebody else might be
an earlier version of you.
And so leaving a trail of breadcrumbs for
yourself or for
others that'd help to understand
what the code was supposed to do,
how it was supposed to work, and
maybe why you made the choices you did.
It can be very helpful, sometimes
that last one is the most important.
It may be that you come up against a case
where this mechanism over here seems like
the right way to do it, and then you find
out it's just not gonna work for some way.
Maybe, recursion is the right way to
do this and then you find out, well,
okay but it's running on hardware
where you can't have more than
six functions calling each other or
you run out of space on your stack.
So okay, fine, we gotta do it differently.
You make choices like that,
you make design decisions.
And leaving those documented for
other people later on, can help them
understand why you did what you did.
And to help avoid making mistakes
that maybe you made along the way.
So it's important, do it.
And the best time to get in
the habit of doing it is early on.
Even when you know you're the only
one who is gonna write the code and
you don't expect to look
at it three weeks from now.