[MUSIC]
So now we're ready to
lay the foundation for
the specific graphical application
that you're doing for the project.
And so remember that what we'll be
doing here is placing earthquake
data around the world.
By the end of this sequence of videos,
you'll be able to place markers on a map
of the world that you're displaying, and
format those markers in
whichever way you choose.
Now the way that you'll be doing
that is by really delving deeply
into the documentation for Java, for
Processing, for Unfolding Maps, and
really learning how to become comfortable
using other people's code and
their interfaces in
developing your own project.
So all of this is in
the service of the really cool
project that we hope your
excited about diving into.
So let's start by thinking about
the map that we want to build and
the information that we
want to lay over top of it.
And if you think back to how Christine
introduced the ideas behind objects and
classes, we really want to think about our
map as representing real world data and
modelling that real world data with
the Java constructs that we use.
So some of those real world objects
that we care about include things like
location and geographical information, and
then those points of interest that
we want to highlight using markers.
In our case,
those points of interest are earthquakes.
So let's think about how we implement some
of this in Java, and we've got the two
faces the project being setting up the map
and then adding the content to that map.
So, thinking back to our graphical
applications from the previous lesson,
we know that the PApplet class
lets us display data visually.
And so,
when we want to customize that display,
we can extend the data type PApplet.
And so our skeleton code for this new Java
class would have the name of the class,
and just a reminder that the class
name needs to be the name
of the file that we're
saving this code in.
So our file name would be
EarthquakeCityMap.java.
Now in this class,
what we need to define in order to
specify how we're customizing the output
are the two special methods that we have,
the setup method and the draw method.
Notice that,
right now in the skeleton code,
we also have declared a private instance
variable that we'll be referring to,
and it's a variable of type UnfoldingMap.
And so let's see how we fill some of this
skeleton code and what that all means.
As we're getting more comfortable with
this code, we want to trace through it and
see what the methods are doing and
why they are placed in
the code where they're placed.
So take a moment, please, and
see which of these methods you recognize
from the previous work that we've done,
and which one seem new.
Okay, so let's start with the familiar
methods, and you'll notice that some of
these methods we used before when we
were building just a simple graphical
application by extending PApplet
before from the processing library.
And for example, the size method
that we're using here in setup lets
us specify the dimensions of
the canvas that we're displaying.
And the background method in
the draw method that we've got here,
let's just specify the background
color of the canvas.
So those methods we're familiar with.
Now in order to implement the project
that we care about that has
quite a much more sophisticated output
than just some colors on a canvas,
what we're using is
the UnfoldingMaps library.
And that library gives us access to
a whole array of new data types.
And one of those data types that's very
important that's sort of at the crux
of what we'll be doing is
the map object itself.
So that data type is called UnfoldingMap,
and
you see that we're using the constructor
to build an UnfoldingMap type object
in the second line of the setup method.
So, as we're building that object,
we need to tell Java
some parameter information about
the object that we want to create.
So some of those parameters indicate the
size of the map that we want to display.
And so we have the height and
the width dimensions of the unfolding map.
But that map is going to be
associated with a canvas.
And so we need to tell the display
where on that canvas to locate the map,
and so we need to also give
the coordinates of the map in the canvas.
Now notice in the particular example
that we're working on right now,
the map is much smaller than the canvas,
and there's a reason for that.
Remember that in the project for
this week, what we'll be doing is putting
the map and a key for
that map together on the same canvas.
And so we can't have the map
taking up the entire space.
The other piece of the puzzle that we
needed to specify when we're building
a new unfolding map object is where
that unfolding map object learns
about the map features, in particular,
the boundaries of continents for
example, or countries, or any road data
that we want to display in our map.
And in order to do that, Unfolding Maps
has this infrastructure of map providers,
and for now we could just use this
long constructor as a bit of a magical
incantation with all of its parameters.
And we know that if we want to display a
map, that last parameter needs to be a new
map provider, and we're choosing
to use the Google Map provider.
So one of the things that you're working
with in some of the end-of-module
assessments is playing with
the different map providers and
seeing what the effects
of that would look like.
Now as we continue setting up our map,
we are modifying the map
object that we just created.
We're calling a method on it
that says zoom to level, and
we're specifying the level two.
We can choose the default zoom
level of the map that we're using.
Now for those of you who are working
through this course offline,
you'll notice that we've put
in some functionality for you.
We've put in some options for you that
let you still work and program without
accessing the map providers online in
real time as you're running your applets.
You will have to be a little careful
though with zoom levels, so in particular,
the offline version of the map
only has three zoom levels.
Now some of those methods, then,
allow us to incorporate some really cool
functionality in our maps without having
to code it all off some scratch, and
the MapUtils library also lets us do that.
So the
MapUtils.createDefaultEventDispatcher
basically sounds like magic at the moment,
but
we'll talk more about events
later on in the course.
And what this event dispatcher
does is it makes our map come to
life in the sense that we can double-click
on it and change the zoom level.
We can drag-and-drop the map, we can
zoom to different parts of the world.
And so without us having to write up
a whole bunch of code to implement
that functionality,
by using what other people have done,
we can already boost
the interactivity of our application.
We're using another method from
the map object in the draw method.
And notice that, in the draw method,
as soon as we've set the color,
what we've said is map.draw.
And map.draw is actually
a very powerful method.
In that one line, what we're saying is,
take the map object and
anything that's associated with it, and
refresh the view of that map object.
And what you'll see as we go ahead and
customize our map is that instead of
drawing each one of the new pieces
that we've added to our application
everytime we invoke the draw method,
what we're going to do is associate each
one of those new pieces to the map object.
And then map.draw's method
will refresh them all.
So we've talked in a fair amount of detail
about a lot of the methods that you see
here in this starter code.
But there's one yet
that we haven't defined or discussed, and
that's the addKey method, and
you get to design that method.
That method is a private
helper method in this class
where you will design how to interpret and
display the markers
that indicate the magnitude of earthquakes
that you're showing on this map.
And so the definition for this method
occurs a little bit later in this file,
and as you look through
the starter code for
this week's project,
make sure to trace through the code and
find where you'll be filling in
the body of that method In this class.
So as we trace through the code,
it's important to know what all
the methods are doing,
not just where they come from.
And so now that we have a sense of what
each of the methods do individually, let's
think about what we expect to see when we
run a piece of code like this in Eclipse.
So let's start by predicting
what you would expect to see.
Okay, so what you probably predicted
was a canvas that has a background
that is almost completely black and
which displays a map that doesn't
take up the whole canvas, but
that shows up on the canvas.
Now my question is,
what if we wanted to display something
just a little bit different?
For example, if we wanted this to be
our canvas, what would we need to do?
So you probably have honed in on the
background method as what we would need to
change if we wanted to change the
background color from almost nearly black
to this light gray.
And you might remember that in
the processing library documentation,
we have the definition of the background
method and it's various parameters.
And if we want to switch our color from
almost black to gray, what we could do is
just pick up value for the gray
level that is much closer to white.
So for example, if we picked a value,
say 220 or 230, then we'd
achieve the effect of having a light gray
background like we were anticipating.
So at this point, we've done a really
thorough job of setting up our map.
And the next step is to add some content,
so that's what we'll do next.