[MUSIC]
So we're going to continue building our
map application displaying earthquakes,
and we're ready to start adding content
to the map that we set up before.
So then the question is how
do we add that content?
And we know that our map is, well, it's
part of a class that extends p applet.
And so,
the two main methods that we've got
where we're doing a lot of the hard work
are the set up method and the draw method.
And so, it's a question where
do we put the definitions
of all of these new objects that
we want to create that will let us
point ad various parts in the map and
remember that the setup method gets
executed exactly once at the beginning
of when the p upload is launched.
Whereas the draw method
that gets executed over and
over again,
every time we want to refresh the view.
And all of these objects that
were creating the pointers
to various milestones and
features of the map
we don't want to create a new object
every time the screen gets refreshed,
what we love to do is just have
a single instance of those class
that represents a particular
point that we're thinking about.
And have that point somehow
associated with the map as a whole.
And then every time we need to
refresh the map we just say
hey refresh every thing
that we've already created.
And so for
that reason all of these definitions.
All of the work that we're about to do
will get put in the set up method and
then when we execute the map.draw method.
It within the p draw method,
that mapped our draw method,
will go through all the objects
that are associated with or
attached to a map object and
will refresh them as well.
So, let's think about,
adding a specific marker,
to denote a particularly significant
earthquake that happened in Chile in 1960.
And so, what we'd like to do perhaps,
is indicate that location as something
o note, and then put a dot on that
location in our graphical representation.
So let's think about some code
that we could use to do that.
In the first line of code, notice that
we're working with coordinates, which
should be a little bit familiar to you
from what Christine was doing earlier so
one of the great things about working
with a library of methods and
data types that were special built for
a particular purpose is that a lot of the
data types that we would naturally need
have the defined focal ready and
location is one of those examples.
So in our earlier videos we actually
defined a class called simple location and
we tried to built in some of
the functionalities that location
ought to have but
we see over here in the documentation for
unfolding maps that we already
have that in the location class.
And so notice that there are a couple
different constructors depending on which
parameters we want to use and
then some public methods that we can use
to both access and modify some of
the properties of the location objects.
So the first thing that we would want
to do when putting a marker on this
significant earthquake on its
location in the world is to create
a location object and set its coordinates
to be the coordinates of the epicenter.
Now once we have that location object that
still isn't associated with the map, and
the way that we can associate or
highlight a particular location
on the map Is to create a marker.
So, a marker is, well,
it's what you think it might mean, and
this is the beauty of having our Java
objects mirror the, it'd be really
models for the real life objects, so
that our code is readable and intuitive.
So a simple point marker
represents a single location, and
it represents it using a circle.
Now, notice that there's something
else in this documentation.
Notice the documentation points out
that the simple point marker implements
something called a Marker, and
it's an interface called a Marker.
Now, an interface is
something that indicates that we're
dealing with an abstract data type.
It's like a promise
between the programmer and
the person using the library's
code that any data type
that implements the abstract data type
marker will have certain behaviors,
will allow certain functionalities and
what the interface let's us do is hide
some of the details of the implementation
of how those functionalities
are actually put into practice.
So in our particular application,
we don't really care
whether our marker is a SimplePointMarker
or some other kind of marker.
All we care about is that it's a way of
denoting a specific location on the map.
And so in our code what we might
say is that the variable val
of type marker gets assigned to
the object of type SimplePointMarker.
So when we're creating an object we
have to give it a concrete data type.
So that it can actually,
you can actually use a specific details
of the implementation of that class.
But when we're going to be using or
pointing to that object,
all we'll need to know about it
is that it's some kind of marker.
And in particular, what we'll be doing
with it is adding that market to our map
so that it gets displayed, and so
that then when we execute the draw method,
that marker will show up on our map.
And so, what we see is the map that
displays the location of the Chile
earthquake and coming up,
we'll add richer data and more date.