So right now what we had was a map
with a single gray dot on it to
indicate the epicenter
of the Chile earthquake.
But really where our map
comes to life is when we add
changing data based on the current
earthquake data from around the world.
And what we'd like to do that
then is think about handling and
displaying multiple markers and
having those markers be customized
based on properties of the earthquakes.
And so, let's think about how
we can get to that level.
So, in order to deal with more complicated
data and more complicated displays on our
maps, it can be useful to
separate two aspects of the data.
We can separate out the properties
that we're thinking of defining
an earthquake from how we might want to
represent visually those properties, or
that earthquake.
And unfolding maps actually let's
us do that in a very clean way,
using different data types.
So, one of these data types we're more
familiar with the marker interface,
that tells us about how to place dots
on particular locations in the map.
And then how to style those dots, and
so we've already talked about that.
But the new piece that we're going
to add in now is the feature class.
And this feature class is a way of
grouping together certain properties and
saying, this collection of
information is somehow connected.
And I want to encapsulate
it in a single object.
And so what we might do if we're thinking
a little bit further about that important
Chilean earthquake is we might want to
add properties about that earthquake,
like what was it's magnitude?
When did it occur?
Where was it's epicenter?
Which is the only
the information we had before.
And so what we might do
now is create a feature or
a variable of type feature that points
to an object of type PointFeature.
And that PointFeature says that it's
associated with some location in a map,
and then we can add
properties to that object.
And we get to decide what
those properties are.
So every time we'd like to add some
attribute or some property to this object,
to this collection of information
about some location in our map,
what we can do is use the add
property method that's supplied to us
by the data types that
built into the library.
And this method takes in two parameters.
One is the a string that represents
the title of the the title
of the property that we're about to set,
and then the second argument
is the value of that property.
And so, we can see here that we've
added properties for the title, for
the magnitude, for the date,
and then for the year.
Now, once we have all of this
information bunched into
a nice tidy object of type hoit feature,
what we can do is create a marker that
uses that information and for example
we can feed into this marker all of the
properties that we had bundled together.
And then add the marker to our map and
so at this point, when we
run this in Eclipse, we won't see anything
different from what we did before.
The end result of what we've just
done is still just to add a marker
in the location of the epicenter of
this Chilean earthquake from 1960.
But in the background, under the hood,
there's actually a lot more that we could
access about that marker if we then
wanted to style it in various ways.
And we'll see that in a minute.
So that's what we wanted to do if we had
just a single marker that had some
rich data associated with it.
But maybe we want to think about not
just the worst earthquake that was ever
recorded but maybe about,
say, the top five.
And so we can look up some of the most
significant earthquake events
that have happened in the world and
say we wanted to add those into our map.
And so we want to translate this data
into objects that then we
can manipulate in our map.
And so we can go ahead and
do that in our code, and so
we could create feature objects for
each one of these earthquakes.
And what we'd like to do now is instead
of having to deal with each one of these
individually every time, and remember
the names of all the variables that we've
associated with it, et cetera,
we'd like to somehow group them together
into some data type that
we can iterate over.
And lists are fantastic for that.
So what we might do is, we might declare
a list that contains point features.
And it's going to point to a new array
list that will contain point features.
And so, notice that in this
declaration we're doing two things
that seem a little bit sophisticated.
One is that we're using
that inter play between and
interface and
a class that implements that interface.
And so
notice the variable here is of type list.
Where as the object we created
is of type array list.
Which is a data type that implemented
that abstract data type of list.
And We have a support video coming up that
will talk through some of those details.
And we'll also in a lot of
detail about interfaces, and
abstract data types, next week.
So there's more coming to that,
but for now we want you to be comfortable
using some of these constructs.
The other piece here that we'll go
into more depth in the support video
is the fact that we're using generics.
So we're not just defining any old list,
but we're also
telling Java What kind of objects
are being stored in this iterable list.
We're saying that in particular
each one of the elements
in this list is a point feature.
And the advantage of that then is
that when we go through the list and
read off the objects one by one,
we'll know that what we're getting
back is a point feature, and so
we'll be using all the methods that
are associated with those point features.
So once we've declared and
created this object,
now we can add elements to that list.
And so we can go ahead and add those five
significant earthquakes to that list.
And the big advantage comes now when
we want to represent those features
on in our map.
And so we want to create markers for
each of those features.
Now because we put all of those
earthquake features in a list.
In order to create the markers what we
could do is iterate through that list and
we could say for each point feature
in the list that we just created.
What we're going to do is add a new
marker to a list of markers and that new
marker is going to be constructed
from the information that
we get from the particular PointFeature
that we got back from this list.
So every time we create a new marker,
what we're doing is we're giving it
a particular location and
particular collection of properties.
That are read off from one of these
features that we created before.
So the effect of having this for
each point feature in this list of
point features loop is
that our markers list
will be populated with a single marker for
each one of these significant earthquakes.
And then we can go ahead and add those
markers to the map that's nice and
all but at that point,
all of those markers look the same.
And so we have dots.
We have five different dots on our map.
But maybe we want to distinguish them,
one from the other.
And so we could do it different for
each loop and
look perhaps through our list of markers
and customer the markers that we have.
And in the documentation for the folding
maps library is a bit of a theme here.
If you want to look at that documentation
we want to make sure that we understand
what functionality is available to us
as we use these different data types.
One of the things that we can do to
customize a marker is to change its color.
And so we can go ahead and check for
each of the markers in our list.
Is it relatively recent, the event
that is associated with this marker?
Or is its event older, more historic?
Vertical and so we could set
some thresholds for ourselves.
For example, we could decide to style
the more recent IE after 2000
earthquakes to be yellow.
We could style the older ones,
the more historical ones to be gray.
And there's lots of opportunities for
customization here.
We'll invite you to do that as part of
your project when you're working through
the real live data.
Now, as we're doing this,
you might have noticed that we had
to type in all of the features for
each of these five earthquakes,
that we wanted to represent on our map.
And that's cumbersome.
It's time consuming,
and it's not scalable.
And it's also not very dynamic.
So If an earthquake happened today or
tomorrow, and I want to
depict it in my map, I would need to sit
down and write down all of its attributes.
And create a new object and feed it
into And I feed it into the list and
do everything I've just done with
every earthquake that came in.
And so what we'd like to think about is,
is there a way to dynamically update this
list of feature and then the list of
markers that are associated with
them that will be more scalable?
And one thing that we've provided for
you in the starter code that we hope
you will find interesting is a parser.
And that parser is designed to
read in data from the USGS and
what the USGS provides to anyone who is
interest in this data is an RSS feed.
Which is basically bulletin
that get's send out As
a text stream with updated information
about earthquakes from around the world.
And so we can download the current
version of this text file, and
you'll be doing that as
part of your project.
And if we feed that through the parse
feed library that we've provided for
you What we could do is translate all
of the earthquakes that are depicted
in this text file to a list of features.
And so, we invite you to read
through the ParseFeed class.
It will be a bit of an exercise
in tracing Java code,
there's some complicated
Constructs that we use there, and
as you work your way through
the various courses and specialization
you may feel more comfortable with
some of the methods that we use.
It's not required for you to understand
all the details of the parser for
this project or for this course.
But that's part of the beauty of extending
libraries as you're building code.
The focus of your developments time and
energy is to design and build
the project that you want, and you can
use any tool at your disposal for that.
And some of those tools may be
written with techniques that you're
not comfortable with, or that you don't
have mastery over but that's okay so
long as you know how to incorporate
the end results of those techniques, and
the end results of those tools into
the work that you're trying to do.
So in particular you'll notice that in
the parse feed class we have a method
that will return to us a list of point
features but then we can reiterate over,
just like we did before and create a list
of markers but then we can add two r nap.
So At the end of all this
what we create is this
beautiful map of the world where
we've got the markers corresponding
to the most up-to-date information
that we have from this RSS feed.
And then we can go through the list
of markers that we create,
iterate over it, and customize
the display of each of these markers
Based on whichever features you find
most interesting and most important.
So good luck and I hope you enjoy that.