[MUSIC]
In this part of the project you'll be
customizing a map using dynamic data.
So in the next three videos what we'll be
doing is stepping through an example that
has a similar objective.
So you can see how you might
want to design your thinking for
the next part of the project and
also see how we might do it in practice.
So by the end of this sequence of videos,
you'll be able to
approach customizing maps, and
you'll be reading in data files and
working with the data that
you get from those files.
And then you'll organize that data using
objects both from the unfolding libraries
and objects that you define yourself, and
we'll be thinking about organizing
data using some abstract data types.
So let's start by setting up the problem,
and this example I just
find really striking.
So what we'll be doing is
annotating a map of the world, so
we'll look at all
countries in the world and
we'll be thinking about data for
average life expectancy at birth.
You can think about a person born on
the other side of the world from you,
and as they start off their life journey,
how long might they expect
to have on this world?
So there's data collected by
the World Bank and you can read it in.
And what we've done is annotate
this picture of the world,
this map of the world, so that
the bright red spots are countries where
the average life expectancy at
birth is somewhere around 45 years.
And the bright blue spots have average
life expectancy around 85 to 90 years.
And so just in this visualization
we see that the range of life
expectancies we find globally.
And this is pretty striking, and so by the
end of the videos, you'll be able to do
similar visualizations with all sorts of
data sets that are available online and
in other sources and that we'll also make
available for you through this course.
So the life expectancy data that we
might get, say from the World Bank,
for example, comes to us as a spreadsheet,
comma separated values.
Lots and lots of rows in this file.
And we want to make sense of it,
we want to present it in a way that's
easier to understand and organize.
So when we have a high level
objective like drawing pictures or
visualizing data on a map, it's useful
to break it down into manageable
chunks before we sit down
to program a solution up.
And so for this particular problem, we
can think of our project in three stages.
First, we might setup the map, configure
the window and display the countries.
Then we might go to reading in the data,
and looking at the data file that we have.
And finally we can convert that data
into a visualization on the map.
So the videos will be separated
into these three stages and
we'll wrap up this video
by setting up our map.
So this is a good opportunity to think
back to the beginning of your project.
And you've already played around with
similar code where we declare a class, we
create a new class, that extends PApplet
and uses the UnfoldingMaps library.
So in this class definition we are in
a new file, the LifeExpectancy file.
And remember that the file name
has to match the class name.
And what we're going to
do is create a map and
then we have to define two methods, the
two methods that will setup our applet and
then draw it continuously while
the applet is running to update the view.
Okay, so
let's start by setting up the map and
that first line of code is setting
up the size of the canvas.
We've seen that in a few earlier videos so
hopefully it's familiar at this point.
And then beyond that
we're creating a new map.
So we're using the constructor for
the UnfoldingMap, and we're creating a new
map object that we'll be manipulating and
using throughout the project.
All right, this is slightly new and
what we're doing here is using
one of the built-in methods
in the UnfoldingMaps library.
And what this method does is allow
the user to interact with
the map in some limited ways.
So by invoking
MapUtils.createDefaultEventDispatcher,
which all seem like magic words at this
point, but if you invoke this little
magic command, What that happens when we
run our applet is that double-clicking
leads to zooming in in the map and we
can do some panning around in the world.
Now, computer science is not magic and
we will make all of this
clear in a future module.
We will talk about event handlers.
We'll talk about what's going
on under the hood, but for
now in order to add some added
interactivity, we use this line of code.
Okay, so
we've set up the map a little bit,
we've created a map object and
we've configured its size.
And now if we go ahead into that draw
method, we can call the map's own
draw method, each UnfoldingMap comes with
its own draw method, that will refresh
the screen based on the current objects
and parameters associated with the map.
And so at this point what we have is that
default canvas with the map of the globe.
And what we'll do in the next two videos
is start bringing in our data and
shading the countries of the world based
on the life expectancy data that we
talked about earlier.