[SOUND] Welcome back to this
second of three videos.
Where we'll be developing
a project together.
We're going to build a map that visualizes
life expectancy around the world and
we've broken up that
task into three pieces.
In the first video we talked
about setting up the map.
And I hoped that you've
opened up the clips and
tried out that beginning setup procedure.
And that now you're ready to work
with me to read in the data file from
the world bank with
the life expectancy data.
And then we'll display
the map in that third video.
So, this is our end goal what we'd like
to see when we finish this project is
the range of colors from bright red to
indicates countries with a very low
average life expectancy at birth to
a bright blue color for countries with
a very relatively high life expectancy,
average life expectancy at birth.
And all of that data is encapsulated
in this data file that we can read in
from the World Bank, and this file is
formatted as a whole bunch of rows,
and each row contains data
about a single country.
So there's some header
information in the file and
then we see that each of the fields
is going to be separated by commas.
And so understanding how to read files and
manipulate files where
we have formated data.
Rows each with a similar format and
each row containing fields separated by
commas will be very powerful because lots
of data is passed around in this way.
So what we'd like to do is
to store data's associated,
associating countries with
average live expectancy at birth.
And a really powerful data structure for
doing so is the Map data structure.
Now take a minute, we're gonna use Map
in two different ways in this video.
And so you want to make sure to keep
straight which Map we're talking about.
And so at this point, when we say Map,
we mean an association or a function
that relates something that you wanna
think of input values to output values.
So a map is going to associate keys like
countries with values,
their average life expectancy at birth.
And so, we're going to take the data
from that file, that CSV file, and
store it in a data structure in our class
and that data structure is going to
keep track of what life expectancy
belongs to each country.
So this is an example of a general data
type, an abstract data type called Map.
And you can keep in mind this image
of keys being associated with values.
And what's important here is that every
key is associated with exactly one value.
You're not going to have one country.
With two different values
associated with it.
And so in our particular example,
the keys are the country identifiers.
And the values that we want to store for
each country is that
average life expectancy.
And both the keys and the values have
types, and those types are going to be
different because they're
different kinds of objects.
But there is some
relationship between them,
which is why we're storing
them as Ordered pairs.
So there is that word abstract.
We're talking about
abstract data types and
we haven't talked about
those in this lesson yet.
Or nor in this course.
We will talk about those.
Stay tuned in an upcoming module.
In our application, we'd like to create
a map with country IDs as the keys.
And the life expectancy as the values.
Now, it's a little bit complicated
to read in the data from a file and
create this data structure and
then put the information from the data
file into the data structure.
And we don't want to
clutter up our setup method
that talks about setting up the applet
that we're displaying to the user.
We don't want to clutter up that method
with all of this code that's very detailed
and maybe isn't so hard to follow,
it is pretty hard to follow.
And so what we're going to do is
carve it out of the setup method and
create a new helper method that
we can follow through separately.
And so
in the setup all we say is that the map,
lifeExpByCountry is going to be created
by invoking this helper method.
Now in terms of class design,
a good rule of thumb,
to extend what Christine earlier said
is that when we have helper methods
that are really for this organization
purpose, we want to keep them private.
We don't need to send
them out into the world.
Okay so, we want to have
a private helper method and
let's think about how we're specifying
what it takes in is the filename.
That's going to lead us to the data and
then what we want to return
after executing this method is the Map
that associates countries with expected.
With life expectancy.
Okay, so we can go ahead and
think about what we to have in there, and
the first thing we need to
do is to construct the map.
Just construct that object that's gonna
hold the counties and the life expectancy.
Now there's something a little funky here,
and you'll notice that
the data type of the map that
we're declaring here is just map.
But when we invoke a constructor,
we're saying we want a new HashMap.
And that's different from other
times that we've used constructors.
Other times that we've used constructors
when we've created a new object,
the type of the object that we're creating
matches the constructor that we're using.
Now this is a subtle point and it comes.
You'll see a lot more details about that
one when we talk about abstract classes
tying into that abstract data type.
But for now the way that you can think
about this is that we want a map and
the kind of map,
the way it's being implemented,
the details of it is going to be
a HashMap, but the functionality that we
care about is that it's a map
that it has keys and values.
Okay, so that's the first thing we do.
We construct it.
Once we have the map declared,
what we'd like to do is populate it.
And we're populating it
from fields in the file.
And so we'd like to read in all the files
and we're going to do that taking it one
row at a time and sticking the contents
of a single row into an array of strings.
Now we iterate through all of
the strings that we've just read in.
So each row one at a time.
And we can use the for each row in
the array of strings rows construct.
So it's a special for loop that lets
us iterate over an entire array.
And what we're going to do is for
each row, we'd like to parse away
just the relevant information.
If you remember in
the data file each row had
some beginning junk columns that told
us the title of the data series and
then it had that relevant
piece that we cared about.
The country and then also the average
life expectancy at birth.
And so what we'd like to do is parse
the string that comes to us from the file,
the entire row, and
pick off just the important parts.
And so
what we can do is take a single String,
which is that entire row, and
split it based on a separating character.
And so we know that in a comma
separated values file,
a CSV file, every time there's
a comma we have a new field.
And so we're going to split the rows
String into an array of strings,
each of the elements in the array of
strings is another string that is a field.
Okay, but now what we'd like to do is just
read off the fields in particular values
and so we have some logic to pick out
exactly the columns that we need okay?
So looking in a little bit
deeper into what we're doing,
what we'd like is the country ID and
the life expectancy.
Now the country ID is a string,
will be a string forever and after.
We don't need to worry about that.
But we are doing something
in that the first line
that is highlighted in that box.
And that is we want to read off a float,
a number type for
the life expectancy, but
in the data file we just read it in as a
string, and so we're casting this string.
We're converting the string to a float,
and so
we have a method that lets us do that.
So now that we've read all of the rows
from the data file into our map,
we have access to all of the information
that pairs the country ID
with its average life expectancy at birth,
and we are ready to move to the next part
of the big picture of our project,
which is to display the data
that we've just read in and convert it
into some visualization on the map.