[MUSIC]
All right, we're in step three of three
of this project to visualize average life
expectancy around the world, and
in this video we're going to build on
what we've done in the previous two.
So we've already set up the map, and
we've already read in the data from
the CSV file, which tells us the average
life expectancy for each country,
and now we want to translate that
data into the colors of this map.
And so hopefully you've implemented
everything that we've done so
far in Eclipse, and you're ready to get
going and do this last piece with us.
So the data we need in order to annotate
the map with this information is not only
the life expectancy for each country, but
also how the countries look on the global
map itself, what their coordinates are and
how they occupy space in the map.
So that information is located
in a file in the data directory
of the unfolding maps library, and
it's called countries.geo.json.
Json is an extension that indicates
we've got formatted text.
Now in order to pull all of this
information together, the geographical
information about the countries as
well as their life expectancy's, we
want to design some objects, or use some
predefined objects, that help us organize
both geographical locations and features,
or properties, of these locations.
So what we're going to think about are the
underlying groupings of the properties and
locations as distinct from their
visual representations on the map.
And in fact unfolding as a library,
has some classes that are able to
manage that distinction for us.
So when we're just thinking about
a particular location in the world and
it's associated properties,
we wanted to find or use the type feature.
So use objective type feature for
talking about locations with properties.
But then when we want to translate those
into some sort of visual representation on
the map, then we could use the marker
class in the unfolding library, which then
lets us style how these properties might
impact what we display on the map.
So let's think about how we are going
to store all of this information,
because we have a lot of countries, and so
we want to have a list of features,
and also a list of markers.
So this is another example
of an abstract data type.
In the previous video, we saw the abstract
data type math, which let us store
pairs of pieces of information,
pairs of objects, and now we've got lists.
And lists are relevant whenever we want
a collection of objects that
are ordered in some way.
Okay, so we've already seen
other examples of lists.
For example,
when you think about ArrayLists,
then that's a particular
implementation of a list.
And we'll talk more about this data
type and its implementations later,
but for now,
we want to think about a list of features,
each one associated with a country.
So, in our output we're going to
think about all of the countries,
each of the countries has associated
its life expectancy in some
other pieces of information, and so
each of that is going to be a feature.
We're going to have a feature object for
each country, and
we'll store them all,
all of those feature objects in a list.
Similarly, we'll have an marker object,
a different marker object for
each one of our markers, for
each one of our countries, and so,
in our class we need to
declare a list of features and
a list of markers, and
this is how we do it.
Now, instead of just declaring
that's not good enough,
if we want to work with these objects,
we've declared them but now we need to
build them, and so we need to create
one feature and one marker per country.
So here's the code that we might
include in our setup method to do so.
We're not gonna go into the details
of how this goes about.
We're using helper methods that are
provided by the UnfoldingMaps library, and
these are standard methods that you will
use in your project and thread when you
want to create features and markers for
a list of countries that you already have.
Once we have these features and markers,
we want to add them to the map,
which means that we display the markers,
but
not only do we want to add them to the
map, we want to manipulate them, and what
we'd like to do is shade them based on
the colors, based on the life expectancy.
Okay, so let's dig deeper into what
this shading will look like, and
we've defined a new helper method that
will let us do that in some detail.
Okay so this is our helper method,
remember that our rule of thumb is that
they are private unless there's a reason
to open it up to the world,
we're going to keep it private.
And what we're going to do is go through
all of the markers that we created,
remember there's one marker for
each country.
And what we'd like to do is for each of
the markers, for each of the countries and
their associated markers, we're going
to decide how to color the marker, and
the coloring is going to
depend on the life expectancy.
Now, that life expectancy is a number.
The number's typically between 45 and
90, and
that number is stored in
the map data structure, right?
We can access it by saying, hey map,
I would like the value
associated with a key country.
And so if we pass as
an argument to the get method
of the map the countryID, or the string
that has that countryID, and then the map
object gives us back the value associated
with that key and that's a float.
Once we have that number, well we'd like
to translate that number to a color,
and this is where I apologize, because
not only do we have two ways of using
the word map in this sequence of videos,
we now are including a third.
So let's think back to all
of the maps that we've used.
We've got the global map,
the picture, the map of the world.
We've got maps of data structure,
which associates keys with values.
And now we've got map the method, and
this is a built in method in the library
and it's a really useful one.
So this method map lets us take
a number in a predefined range,
and map it into its comparable location
in a different range of values.
So in this particular instance,
we're taking
the number which is life expectancy of the
country that we're currently focusing on.
And we know that the life expectancy
ranges from between 40 in countries
with the lowest average life
expectancy to 90 at the top end, and
we'd like to translate that to
something to do with color.
And if you think back to
a couple of videos ago,
when we first introduced colors and
the RGB codes for colors,
remember that those RGB channels had
minimum value zero and maximum value 255.
So we'd like to translate the range 40
to 90 over to the range of zero to 255,
so we're in a range of numbers that's
more compatible with color codes,
and this map method lets us do just that.
Okay, so we invoke it.
What we get back from it is a float, and
we're going to cast it to an integer,
because for the RGB colors,
we just deal with integers.
So in the RGB coding of
colors we want an integer
between zero and 255 for each of the three
color channels, red green and blue.
All right so, we've translated the life
expectancy of the country that
we're focusing on to some
integer value between zero and
255, and what we'd like to do is,
countries that have really
low life expectancy relatively speaking
are going to be colored bright red.
So bright red means that the red
channel should be at highest possible,
somewhere around 255.
And if we want the countries
that have very high life
expectancy to be colored bright blue, then
for those the blue should be high, 255,
and all the other channels
should be pretty low, and so
we can define the color of
the marker appropriately.
So the red channel is going to be
the first argument of the color method,
and it's going to be 255 minus
the number that we just calculated.
So if the color level that we calculated
is zero, then the color that we're setting
our marker to is going to be very
close to 255, it's gonna be 255.
So it's gonna be a very, very red marker,
and the other two arguments are going to
be very low, and so
we'll see that bright red color.
And on the other side,
if the color level that we calculated
corresponds to a really high life
expectancy, then we're gonna get a large
number, which means that the red channel,
that first argument to the color method,
will be very low, and so
our marker will be a bright blue.
Now, think back about this logic
that you see in this code,
and we have an if else in there, and
if that if else is dependent
on the conditional statement
if lifeExpMap.containsKey(countryId),
well what on Earth does that mean?
It could be that the marker that
we're looking at currently has
a country ID that doesn't show up
in the file of life expectancy's.
It could be that when the World Bank
put together all of their data on life
expectancy's, they weren't able
to reach the statistics of one
particular country and we don't want our
code to crash just because we don't have
information about a particular country.
So what we're going to do is check,
we're gonna ask our map,
the map that associates countries with
life expectancy if they actually have
a value of life expectancy for
the country that we care about.
And if there is such a life expectancy for
the country we care about,
then we go ahead and
do our calculation that we just did, and
we color the marker appropriately.
But if we don't, then we want to have
some sort of default setting for
what that color's going to be, and
remember when Christine was talking in her
supplementary video about color codes,
she mentioned that if we set
all three colors, R, G, and
B to the same value,
then what we get is a shade of grey.
So our default color for the marker is
just going to be a shade of grey if we
don't happen to have information about the
life expectancy of a particular country.
All right, we've done it.
What we've done now is we've
colored the whole world
based on the data in
the life expectancy file.
And what's really powerful about
the techniques that we've gone through in
these three videos, is that really most of
what we're talking about doesn't depend
on the fact that we're talking
about life expectancies.
Any time we have a data file that tells us
some values associated with country IDs.
We could do exactly the same process and
color the world based on all sorts
of other information and data.
So I hope now you're excited about
doing these kinds of projects.
What you might wanna do is look for
additional data sets about
things that you care about.
Or, you could also punch right
back into your project and
think about how to use these techniques
when you're customizing your markers and
displaying the data that you're
working with in the project.