[MUSIC]
All right,
we're in step three of three of this
project to visualized average
life expectancy around the world.
And in this video, we're going to build on
what we've done in the previous two so,
we've all set up the map and we've ready
read in the data from this CSB file.
Which tells us the average life
expectancy for each country, and
now we want to translate that
data into the colors of this map.
And so, hopefully you've implemented
everything that we've done so
far in Eclipse, and you're ready to get
going and do this last piece with us.
And so the data we need in order to
annotate the map with this information is
not only the life expectancy for
each country.
But also how the countries look
on the global map, itself,
what their coordinates are and
how they occupy space in the map.
So that information is located
in a file in the data directory
of the unfolding maps library.
And it's called countries.geo.json
Json is an extension that indicates
that we've got formatted text.
Now, in order to pull all of
this information together,
the geographical information
about the countries.
As well as their life expectancies,
we want to design some objects or
use some predefined objects.
That help us organize both
geographic locations and
features or properties of these locations.
So what we're going to think about are the
underlying groupings of the properties and
locations as distinct from their
visual representations on the map.
And in fact unfolding as
a library has some classes
that are able to manage
that distinction for us.
So when we're just thinking about
a particular location in the world and
its associated properties,
we want to define or use the type feature
to use objects of type feature for
talking about locations with properties.
But then when we want to translate those
into some sort of visual representation on
the map,
then we could use the marker class.
In the unfolding library,
which then lets us style how these
properties might impact
what we display on the map.
So let's think about how we are going
to store all of this information,
because we have a lot of countries, and so
we want to have a list of features,
and also a list of markers.
So this is another example
of an abstract data type.
In the previous video,
we saw the abstract data type, map,
which let us store pairs of pieces
of information, pairs of objects.
And now we got lists and
lists are relevant whenever we want
a collection of objects that
are ordered in some way.
Okay, so we've already seen lots of
examples of lists for example, when you
think about array lists then that's
a particular implementation of a list.
And we'll talk more about this data type
and it's implementations later but for now
we want to think about a list of features
each one associated with a country.
So in our in our applet, we're going
to think about all of the countries,
each of the countries has
associated its life expectancy and
some other pieces of information.
And so,
each of that is going to be a feature.
We're going to have a feature object for
each country and we'll store them all,
all of those feature objects, in a list.
Similarly, we'll have a marker object,
a different marker object for
each one of our markers, and
for each one of our countries.
And so in our class we need to
declare a list of features and
a list of markers, and
this is how we do it.
Now, Instead of just declaring
that's not good enough.
If we want to work with these objects,
we've declared them, but
now we need to build them.
And so we need to create one feature and
one marker per country.
So here's the code that we might
include in our setup method to do so.
We're not going to go into
the details of how this goes about.
We're using helper methods that
are provided by the UnfoldingMaps library.
And these are standard methods that
you will use in your project and
throughout when you want
to create features and
markers for
a list of countries that you already have.
Once we have these features and
markers, we want to add them to the map,
which means that we display the markers.
But not only do we want to add them to
the map, we want to manipulate them.
And what we'd like to do is
shade them based on the colors,
based on the life expectancy.
Okay, so let's dig deeper into what
this shading will look like and
we've defined a new helper method that
will let us do that in some detail.
Okay, so this is our helper method.
Remember that our rule of thumb
is that if they are private,
unless there is a reason
to open it up to the world.
We're going to keep it private and
what we're going to is go through
all of the markers that we created.
Remember there's one marker for each
country and what we'd like to do is for
each of the markers, for each of the
countries and their associated markers.
We're going to decide how
to color the marker and
the coloring is going to
depend on the life expectancy.
Now that life expectancies a number.
A number is typically between 45 and
90, and that number is stored in
the map data structure, right.
We can access it by saying,
hey map I would like the value
associated with the key country.
And so we give, if we pass as an argument
to the get method of the map,
the countryID, or
the string that has that countryID.
And then the map object gives us back
the value associated with that key,
and that's a float.
Once we have that number, well we'd like
to translate that number to a color.
And this is where I apologize,
because not only do we have
two ways of using the map in this sequence
of videos, we now are including a third.
So let's think back to all
of the maps that we've used.
We've got the global map, the picture, the
map of the world, we've got map the data
structure, that associates keys with
values, and now we've got map the method.
And this is a built in method in
the library that's a really useful one.
So this method, map, let's us take
a number in a pre-defined range and
map it into its comparable location
in a different range of values.
So in this particular instance, we're
taking the number which is life expectancy
of the country that we're
currently focusing on.
And we know that the life expectancy
ranges from between 40 in countries
with the lowest average life
expectancy to 90 at the top end.
And we'd like to translate that
to something to do with color.
And if you think back to a couple of
videos ago when we first introduced
colors and the RGB codes for colors,
remember that those RGB channels had
minimum value zero and maximum value 255.
So we'd like to translate the range
40 to 90 over to the range 0 to 255,
so we're in a range of numbers that's
more compatible with color codes.
And this map method lets us do just that.
Okay, so we invoke it.
What we get back from it is a float and
we're going to cast it to
an integer because for the RGB colors,
we just deal with integers.
So in the RGB coding of colors,
we want an integer between 0 and
255 for each of the 3 color channels: red,
green, and blue.
All right, so we've translated the life
expectancy of the color of the country
that we're focusing on to some
integer value between 0 and 255.
And what we'd like to do is countries
that have really low life expectancy,
relatively speaking,
are going to be colored bright red.
So bright red means that the red
channel should be as high as possible,
somewhere around 255.
And if we want the countries that have
very high life expectancy to be
colored bright blue, then for
those the blue should be high 255 and all
the other channels should be pretty low.
And so, we can define the color
of the marker appropriately, so
the red channel is going to be
the first argument of the color method.
And it's going to be 255 minus
the number that we just calculated,
so if the color level
that we calculated is 0.
Then the color that we're setting our
marker to is going to be very close
to 255, it's going to be 255.
So it's going to be a very
very red marker and
the other two arguments
are going to be very low.
And so, we'll see that bright,
bright color.
And on the other side, if the color
level that we calculated corresponds
to a really high life expectancy,
then we're going to get a large number.
Which means that the red channel,
that first argument to the color method,
will be very low.
And so, our marker will be a bright blue.
Now think back about this logic
that you see in this code and
we have an if else in there.
And if that if else is dependent
on the conditional statement
If lifeExpmap.containsKey(countryID)
well what on Earth does that mean?
It could be that the marker
that we're looking at
currently has a countryID that doesn't
show up in the file of life expectancies.
It could be that, when the world bank
put together all of their data on life
expectancies, they weren't able to reach
the statistics of one particular country.
And we don't want our code to crash
just because we don't have information
about a particular country.
So what we're going to do is check.
We're going to ask our map, the map
that associates countries with life
expectancy if they actually have
a value of life expectancy for
the country that we care about.
And if there is such a life expectancy for
the country we care about,
then we go ahead and
do our calculation that we just did.
And we color the marker appropriately but
if we don't,
then we want to have some sort of default
setting, for what that colors going to be.
And remember when Christine was talking in
her supplementary video about color codes.
She mentioned that if we said all three
colors are GNB to the same value,
then what we get is a shade of gray.
So our default color for the marker is
just going to be a shade of gray If we
don't happen to have information about the
life expectancy of a particular country.
All right, we've done it, what we've
done now if we've colored the whole
world based on the data in
the life expectancy file.
And what's really powerful about
the techniques that we've gone through in
these three videos, is that really
most of what we were talking
about doesn't depend on the fact that
we're talking about life expectancies.
Any time we have a data file that tells us
some values associated with country IDs.
We could do exactly the same process, and
color the world based on all sorts
of other information and data.
So I hope now you're excited about
doing these kinds of projects.
What you might want to do,
is look for additional data sets
about things that you care about.
Or you could also plunge right
back into your project and
think about how to use these techniques
when you're customizing your markers and
displaying the data that you're
working with in the project.