[APPLAUSE]
>> All right,
in this support video,
we're gonna look at Java's List Interface,
the ArrayList class, as well as how to use
generics, which are these different types.
You've already seen Mia working with
lists and ArrayLists, and using generics.
And you're gonna be using these
classes and generics in your project.
But if you're feeling like you need
a little bit more review or overview of
what these classes, and what generics are,
then watch the support video.
So by the end of this video,
you'll be able to comfortably work with
ArrayLists and Lists in Java,
which are both built in to Java.
And you'll also be able to create these
objects to work with Java generics.
So let's go back to one of the examples
that Mia used in her video.
She created this list countries
that stored an ArrayList object.
So for now in this example,
I just want you to ignore this piece
right here inside the angle brackets.
That's the generics part of this, and
we're gonna talk about that later.
But for now what I want you to focus
on is the types of the variable
as well as the object that gets created.
So the variable that gets created
countries is of type list.
And you can see over here that the object
that gets created is type ArrayList.
So you might be kind of
worried at this point.
And you might be thinking what's going on?
These two types are not the same.
Is that even allowed?
And the answer is that yes,
this is absolutely allowed in Java.
And we're gonna explain
briefly what's going on here.
So a List, as Mia mentioned in her video
is what's called an abstract data type.
And what it i,
is a Java interface which we're going
to get into more in the next module.
But what that means is it implements,
it specifies,
some behavior that this
object has to have, but
doesn't talk about exactly how that
behavior is going to be implemented.
So you can use that as the type
of a particular variable.
On the other hand,
over here when we actually create
the object itself, that's an actual class.
So the ArrayList is an actual
class that's built into Java.
And it implements all of the behavior
that's specified by the list interface.
This class can be instantiated.
And it's perfectly okay to have an
interface as the type of the variable, and
the actual class as the type of
the thing that you instantiate.
That's done a lot.
And again, don't worry too
much about the details here.
We're going to get more into this in the
next module as well as in future courses
in this specialization.
For now let's just ask the question.
Okay we've got anArrayList object,
let's think about what can it do?
Well if I wanna know what a class
that's built into java can do,
where should I look?
How about the Javadocs?
That's your go-to place to figure out
what can my classes built into Java
actually do?
Here's the URL for
the Javadocs for version 8.
If you're using a different
version of Java,
you'll need to change that 8 to a 7 or
whatever version you happen to be using.
Or my favorite is I just google for
javadoc documentation and
then whatever version of
java I happen to be using.
And this link will come right up.
So if I click on this link, it's going
to take me to this page here and
that's the overview for
the Java documentation.
And now the question is,
where the heck is ArrayList?
How are you gonna find it.
Well there's a couple ways.
You can either look down here.
This is this full list of all the classes
and libraries that are built into Java.
So you will find ArrayList in this
big long list, but it's pretty long.
So a faster way to get yourself to
ArrayList is to know what package it's in.
So the packages are listed up here.
And if you know that ArrayList is in
java.util, which I'm telling you now, so
know you know,
you can look in this package list
to find the java.util package.
Then you can click on java.util
in that package list.
And that will narrow down the list
of classes to only the classes and
interfaces that are in java.util.
So then you can go down here to
the list of classes that are shown.
Click on the ArrayList class and up will
come the documentation for the ArrayList.
Okay, so now you've got the documentation
page for the ArrayList.
And it's pretty long, and it talks about
a lot of things the ArrayList can do.
And I just wanna call out a few different
methods that you're going to find useful.
Okay, now let's talk about setting an
element in an array and in an ArrayLists.
To set an element in an array, you just
use that square bracket notation and
you put it on the left hand side
of your assignment statement.
So, in this case, we're taking a feature
that stored in the variable f and
were putting it into the 0 index
position in our array, countryArray.
To do this in an ArrayList,
we're going to use the method called set.
Set takes two arguments,
a index location, in this case,
0, and
the thing we're trying to put there.
And again, countries is our ArrayList and
we can call the set method on our
countries variable, passing in 0 for
index position, and
f the feature we want to store there.
Now again, our ArrayList in both cases,
our Array and
our ArrayList, have to have at least one
element in them, space for one element.
Otherwise we're gonna get another
index out of bounds exception.
Again if you wanna see the Java
documentation, it looks like that.
Finally, let's talk about how to get
the length, or the size, of an ArrayList.
So with an array, you know that you
can just call that length field.
So I say countryArray.length,
that will give me back the number
of elements in my array.
But for an ArrayList it's
just a little bit different.
Instead of calling a length field,
we're going to call the size method.
So down here,
we can see a method called size which
is just like length in an array.
It returns the number of elements
that are in the ArrayList.
Now notice one important thing,
that size is actually a method.
So we have to have these parentheses
even though they're empty.
It takes no parameters.
It just returns the size
of the ArrayLists.
So, we can see that arrays and
ArrayLists are very very similar,
just some minor differences in
how you interact with them.
But arrays, it turns out,
are actually a bit more powerful.
Sorry, ArrayLists are more powerful than
arrays, because arrays, as you know,
once you create them and
set their size, they're fixed.
But ArrayLists can expand to
incorporate more elements.
So there are these two
methods of ArrayLists add,
they take different numbers of parameters.
And what they do is they actually
append the new element onto the end of
the list increasing the size
of the ArrayList as necessary.
So that's kind of cool.
Of course, it doesn't force you to specify
how big you want your array beforehand.
Java will automatically
resize the ArrayList for you.
So that's one of the reasons
we often use ArrayList
instead of arrays cuz they provide for
this extra flexibility.
Okay.
So now let's go back to
this issue of generics.
So now we're gonna talk about the code
that's inside those angle brackets.
Notice that we're creating
here two different lists.
There's countries and countryMarkers.
And they're both lists, but the difference
is that countries stores features.
And markers store, oh sorry,
the country markers, store markers.
So this is what this generics
capability allows us to specify.
What we put in the angle
brackets is the type of object
that we want Java to store inside
the container that we're creating.
So in this case we're creating a list.
The first list is allowed
to store features.
And the second list is
allowed to store Markers.
Now, when we go to create these objects
that are referenced by these variables,
we again have to say what kind of
thing goes into the container object.
So we can see over here
on the left hand side,
we've said the first list
is going to store Features.
The second list is going to store Markers.
And so on the right hand side
the first ArrayList stores Features.
The second ArrayList stores markers,
and these types have to match.
Now what this allows us to do if we
add a bit more code, let's say we've
got some code here that will put some
elements into both of these lists,.
The cool part about generics is now
when we get elements out of the list,
when we get elements out of country.
Say we get the element at position zero.
We know that countries stores Features.
So we can get back
a Feature type reference.
On the other hand, countryMarkers,
we declared was going to store Markers.
So when we get an element
back from countryMarkers,
it's going to be of Marker type.
So it's the same exact method, this
getmethod, is gonna return a different
type depending on what we
declared the container to store.
So that's really cool.
We don't have to use any casts,
or anything like that.
It just happens automatically for us.
And bringing this back around to the Java
docs, if you look at that getMethod
in the Javadocs, you'll see that
it lists the return type as E.
And what that means is that it's
this generic type that's gonna take
on whatever type you declare
the container to hold.
So, generics are really useful,
ArrayLists and lists, really useful.
You're gonna work with them in
the project which is coming up next.