Welcome back.
You have already written code
to read a web server log file,
parsing each line into a log entry object,
and creating an array list of them.
Now it is time for you to write some
code to analyze the data you have read.
The first problem you're
going to solve is finding out
how many different people
visited a website.
You don't want to just look at how many
elements there are in your array list,
since some people may have visited
your website multiple times.
So you need some way to distinguish
requests from different places.
You can use the IP address as recorded
in the log file to tell where
the request came from.
Using the IP address is not perfect,
since you cannot distinguish between
different people using the same computer.
But how many different IP addresses
you see is a very good estimator for
how many different
people visited the site.
As you might recall from programming and
the web for beginners,
an IP address is the address of
a device on the internet, whether that
device is a traditional computer,
a mobile phone, or something else.
So what you are going to need
to do to solve this problem
is take the array list that you
have read the log entries into and
find out how many distinct
IP addresses are in it.
Have fun.