You've already written code to read in
the entire contents of a web server log.
And now you wanna find out how many
unique IP addresses it contains.
As always, you're going to want
to approach this problem with
the seven steps you use for every problem.
We're going to walk through this problem,
starting at step one.
And we're gonna use color
names instead of IP addresses.
This problem is really the same problem.
You're finding out how many unique values
there are in an array list of strings, but
color names are easier to say and
to see which ones we're talking about.
When we look at this list of ten values.
You might be able to tell
just by looking at it that
there are only four unique values.
But if this list had
a million elements in it,
we'd like to develop a method
that would still work.
There are many ways of
solving problems in general.
And in this case,
there are a couple that I'll mention and
one that we'll realize in code.
One method that we won't do is
to as we look down the list,
cross out values that we've seen before.
Crossing out values in a list is a problem
in Java programming because if we
replace the values in our parameter with
other values we've caused a side effect,
something we've spoken about before
as a thing to avoid if you can.
So instead we'll use an idea of visiting
every value in the list in turn,
which is typical for array problems, and
if we've haven't seen a value before
we'll copy it into a new list.
So first I'm copying the value pink,
because I haven't seen it before,
in my new list.
Then I'm gonna visit green.
I haven't seen it before.
So I'll copy it over into my new list.
Now I'm gonna visit pink.
I've already seen it, so I don't copy it.
Then green.
I have seen it, so I don't copy it.
Pink, pink, pink, I've seen them all.
Orange I haven't seen before, so
I'll copy that into my new list.
The next value's blue.
I haven't seen.
So I'm copying it into my list.
Finally, I get to pink,
the last value in my original list.
I have seen it before,
so I don't copy it over.
Now, I look at my list that I've created.
It has four values, and so I'm gonna
return the value, four, for my method that
I'm writing that determines the number
of unique values in the array parameter.
Developing this algorithm follows a lot
of the same patterns you've seen before.
You'll see that sometimes you add an
element to the copy, and sometimes you do
not, and you'll want to think through
the conditions under which you add.
Once you've done that, you can express
the main portion of the algorithm
in terms of steps to do for
each element of the input.
We'll let you work through steps two and
three.
Hopefully, you came up with
pseudocode that looks like this.
Now for this particular problem,
you'll want to do things just
a little bit differently.
Remember that you have log
entries in the field records.
And you want to use
the get IP address method
to get the string out of
the log entry object.
There are a couple ways to
deal with this difference.
The simplest is to just use the same
algorithm but adjust it slightly to
reflect the fact that you want to use
records, the fields in the class and
you want to get the IP address out of
each element of records, check to see if
that IP address is in copy, and
if not, add the IP address to copy.
At this point,
you'd wanna test out your pseudo code,
then you're ready to
turn it into Java code.