Great, now you have completed your first
analysis of the web server log file data
that you read.
You wrote code to figure out how
many unique IP addresses there were,
which gives you a good idea of how
many people visited your site.
Doing this gave you some great practice
with ArrayLists which are useful for
solving a wide variety of problems.
And you also learned about Java's
two different notions of equality.
== which, tests if it's operands
refer to exactly the same object and
the .equals method which checks if two
objects have the same logical meaning.
Each class can define this method however
it needs to, so that it can provide
the appropriate definition of
having the same logical meaning.