[MUSIC]
In this lesson we're gonna
start learning about trees.
Trees are incredibly powerful and
versatile data structure that are used
commonly throughout computer science.
In fact, many of the data structures,
built in data structures that
you've used in java before,
almost certainly have trees on their
back end, in their implementation side.
So, where gonna do today is just
look at why are trees valuable and
why are they so common?
So, trees somewhat naturally
represent data in the real world.
So, you've almost certainly seen
a family tree before where you have
a parents whose children
are below them in the tree and
then you've got the children of those
children even further down the tree.
And this is a tree from a fairly
popular TV show these days.
Decision trees are also fairly common.
If you ever gone to a medical health site,
you almost certainly went through a
decision tree if you were trying to figure
out what to do based on your symptoms.
Similarly, this is kind of a fun anecdote,
if your house is clean,
you might make a decision.
Yes, my house is clean, so I just relax.
No?
Well.
Is my floor clean?
Well, no, so I better sweep the floor.
So these kinds of decision trees
help guide decisions you might make.
Well think of it in science,
you might do an expression tree.
Now we're not gonna dive into
the details of this, but
if you wanna evaluate the expression
45 / (3 +6), you actually represent
it really cleanly as a tree and
be able to evaluate it much more easily.
You almost certainly have file
systems on your computer.
And file systems are perfect
examples of trees.
Where if I want to know that
my path is users, porter,
well I know it based
on the tree structure.
You can see that there's a root,
then users, then porter.
So there's lots of trees
in computer science.
In fact, you almost certainly
have heard of some of these.
But there's just regular trees, there's
binary trees, there's heaps, there's
binary search trees, there's Huffman
trees, there's AVL trees, randomized
search trees, red black trees, tons of
these, all throughout computer science.
Why are there so many trees?
Well, there's two reasons why trees are so
powerful.
The first is that they're
a dynamic data structure.
What I mean by that is, it's really
easy to add a new directory say,
for Professor Alvarado.
So dynamic data structures just like
are nice, cuz it's easy to add and remove.
The more powerful feature to trees is
that their structure conveys information.
So the fact that users
is a child of root and
that porter is a child of users tells me
that that path exists to users/porter/.
In fact, if you just change
the structure around a little bit,
you get all these
different kinds of trees.
If you make the structure such that root,
the very top level,
has to be the most important.
Well now you've got a heap.
If you wanna organize it based on
character frequencies in say a body
of text, well now you've got
a compression tree or Huffman tree.
If you wanna organize it based on
the natural ordering of the nodes,
well now you've got a search tree.
And there's all these different ways
that we can organize these trees
to get different data structures.
We'll look in detail at a few of these
trees, in these following lessons.