[MUSIC]
Hi, in the last video we saw why we
value trees and why trees are so
common in computer science.
In this video we are just going
to dive into some of the basics,
of saying what do we mean by a tree?
So, by the end of this video you should be
able to describe a tree data structure.
So first off, let's talk terminology.
So, I'm gonna use the example here,
of the family tree just like
we did in the last video.
And the reason I'm using a family tree is
that some of this terminology is related
to how family trees work.
So if we're thinking of the relationship
between Tywin and Jamie,
we know that Tywin is the parent of Jamie.
I also wanna point out in this slide,
that you'll notice I didn't
keep all possible parents.
So there's only one parent
of each of these children,
to essentially keep it a cleaner tree.
Other terminology.
So, where do you start in the tree?
That's called the root node.
The root node is gonna be the only
node that doesn't have any parents.
Leaf nodes are any node
that has no children.
So there's a number of leaf nodes here,
Tyrion, Myrcella, Joffrey,
Tommen, and Jaime are all leaf nodes
because they have no children.
Now that we know the basic terminology,
what actually makes for a tree?
Well, you have a single root and
again, that is gonna have no parent.
Each node can have only one parent,
except for, again,
that root node which is
allowed not to have one.
And then there can be no cycles in a tree.
And all I mean by a cycle is
that there can't be a loop.
We'll see an example of
that in a little while.
All right, so now that we have
a basic definition of a tree,
which of these do we think are trees?
Go ahead and answer this in the in-video
quiz, and we'll come back in just a bit.
Welcome back.
So, hopefully the in-video quiz helped.
Let's just walk through each
of these in more detail.
So, is A a tree?
Absolutely.
You have a single root.
The root has no parent.
And that's okay.
And then each of the children
have exactly one parent.
And that's fine too.
What about B?
Is that a tree?
You've only got a parent and a child.
Is that enough to be a tree?
Yeah, it is.
Again, you've got one root, that's fine.
Each node has only one parent, and there's
no cycles here, so this is a tree as well.
Can you have just a single node?
Is that sufficient?
Yeah, it is.
Again, I've got a single
root that has no parents.
There are no other nodes, so we don't
have to worry about the others, and
there is no cycle.
What about the last one here?
Is this a tree?
Well, no, it's not.
This has two things wrong with it.
The first is that the very bottom
node here has two parents, and
we said from the very beginning every
node has to have one parent except for
the root who can have none.
The other thing that's wrong with
this is this is a perfect example of
a cycle, right?
If I start at the very top, and
I go to the left and then I go down,
well I get to the same node that I
could have gotten to the other way.
And that's the cycle.
What about this last one?
Is this a tree.
No, it's not either.
The reason why is because I have
two nodes that have no parents.
Which means I have two nodes
which are root nodes and
that's not permitted either.
So now that we have a better feel for
what makes for a tree,
in the next video, we'll start talking
about how to code them in Java.