[MUSIC]
In the past few videos we've
seen why trees matter and
how you can define a tree
in computer science.
What we're going to do next is look at
how to actually code a tree in Java.
So by the end of this tree you
should know what a binary tree is.
And you should be able author
essentially a tree node class.
So with a generic tree,
a parent can have any number of children.
So you can see here that
Tywin has three children.
Now, there are many cases in which
you're gonna want a generic tree,
but when we start coding this it's gonna
be a little bit easier to start with
something known as a binary tree.
And a binary tree just restricts parents
to having, at most, two children.
So I can prune this tree
to essentially create it so
it's a binary tree just by making sure
that Tywin has only two children, and
Cersei only has two children.
And that's what we mean by a binary tree.
So then how are we gonna construct this?
How are we gonna write the code for this?
Well let's look at what we're gonna need.
First off,
that's gonna have a linked list structure.
So, just like linked lists,
trees are gonna be built essentially just
by connections to different references.
It's gonna seem very similar in nature to
the linked list that Christine described.
The tree itself only needs a root node,
kind of just like a linked
list only needs a head.
It can also have a tail, but for a binary
tree, we only just want this root node.
So that's pretty easy.
You just have one reference to a node.
But then, what do the nodes look like?
So if we focus in on Cersei,
we can realize that there are four things
that you'll need with a binary tree node.
The first is a value.
You know that this node is Cersei.
You also need a parent.
So in this case, Cersei's parent is Tywin.
You need a left child,
in this case, Joffrey, and
a right child, in this case, Tommen.
So these four components
are all we're going to need for
instance variables in our
binary tree node class.
Lastly, what if we were doing this just
for the general tree that we first started
talking about, the generic tree where
you could have any number of children?
Well, for that general tree, all we'd
change here is replace this left child and
right child with a list of my children.
So it's actually not a large change to
go from a binary tree to a generic tree.
When we start looking at the code, what
we have here is our class BinaryTree and
all it's going to have is a single root,
a reference to a tree node element.
You'll notice that we're using generics
again just like they were described
in the linked lists by Christine.
So we've got a TreeNode root.
And that's gonna be most of
what we're gonna need for
the BinaryTree to get started.
But I can't have a reference to a TreeNode
until I define what a TreeNode is.
So let's look at what
we mean by a TreeNode.
And I could have called
this a BinaryTreeNode.
I just kept it TreeNode for simplicity.
All right, here is my TreeNode.
I've already filled in the private
instance variables that we already
just described.
It's gonna have a value,
a parent, a left, and a right.
So with those four instance variables,
we can essentially describe our TreeNode.
So what we wanna do next is just
briefly code the constructor together.
So what I'm going to create for
a constructor here is a constructor that
takes the value, but also the parent.
So it's gonna help us by
essentially starting the linking
right at the beginning.
In order to write this constructor, first
thing I'm gonna do is set value to be
the parameter val, just like we've
done it in many classes already.
Next I'm gonna set my parent
to be that parent parameter.
And that now set up that link, so
that node has a parent automatically.
Now you might say but wait,
what do I do if this is the root?
Well you would just pass
null as the parent.
Then I'm gonna set up this.left and
this.right, and I'm just gonna make
sure they're null for my own clarity.
Now the next step now that we have this
constructor is to think about how we
would write code for a setter and
a getter of children.
So first off, getters for
the children isn't gonna be too difficult.
You're just gonna write getLeftChild,
and you're gonna return left.
But let's look at adding a left child or
a right child,
I think that's more interesting.
So what I have here is, I've blocked out
the TreeNode constructor code just for
space on the slide, and what we have
then is the addLeftChild method.
So I'm gonna set this.left
to be a new TreeNode.
I'm gonna pass it that value that
we want for the left child, but
I need to pass it one other thing.
What I want you to do is take a moment and
go to the in video quiz.
See what you think we should put there and
come back, and I'll see you in a moment.
Welcome back.
So what do we put here?
I need to essentially hook
up the parent through this,
the second section that's
fill in the blank.
Who's gonna be a parent of this node?
Well, this TreeNode is, right?
So all I have to do is pass this.
So our next step, now that we have
an idea of essentially how to write these
tree nodes, is to start thinking about how
we might want to walk through the tree,
or how we might traverse the tree.
And we'll do that in the next video.