[MUSIC]
When we started thinking about trees, one
of the things that we really need to know
how to do is essentially,
how to traverse them.
If I'm trying to look for
something in the tree, how do I find it?
What order do I want to
go through the notes?
So we're talk through in this video is
essentially a number of different ways
that you can do traversals.
In this video and the next.
So by the end of this video,
you will be able to explain the need to
visit data in different ways or
in different orderings.
You should be able to author
a preorder traversal in Java.
So first, we're gonna look at
some traversals in graphs.
And I want to say there's
a big warning here,
and we're gonna be looking at graphs here.
But we're not gonna cover
graphs till the next course.
I'm just doing this to help motivate why
you might want to look at different data
in different orderings.
So let's start with a maze.
So if I'm at the start of, and I want
you to imagine this is a hedge maze.
You can't see the whole maze,
this isn't like you're working
with some paper and pencil.
It's you physically in this huge maze.
And you start in the maze.
You've got choices to make.
And let's just say that you make the
choice to keep going straight, initially.
Now, what's your next step?
So, you've gone straight.
You made the choice already.
And now you have to make another choice.
Do I go left?
Do I keep going straight?
Well, you might do the going straight.
You might turn left.
But I almost guarantee you what you won't
do is say, well maybe I was wrong making
that step forward, let me go back and
go the other direction.
You wouldn't do that.
When you're traversing a maze, you want
to go until you find a dead end, and
then you go back to the last choice
you made and make a different choice.
And mazes lend themselves
well to this approach.
Another example would be a social network.
Let's say I'm trying to figure out,
I've got you in the center here, and
I'm trying to figure out how closely
are you connected with person D.
Now let's imagine that I
have a list of your friends.
So you have a list of A, B, C, D.
And your friend A,
has a list of friends E, F, and U.
So, how am I gonna find how
closely connected am I with D?
Well, I'm probably gonna start walking
through my list, and I'm gonna look, and
I'm gonna see that I'm friends with A.
Well, what's my next step?
Should I start looking at A's friends, or
should I start looking at my next friend,
to figure out how closely
connected I am with D?
You almost certainly in this case are now
gonna look at all of your friends first,
and then branch out.
And this kind of traversal is known
as Breadth First Traversal, and
we'll see how these apply for
trees in the next few videos.
But the bottom line here is the order
in which your nodes matters and
we need to make choices based on
the needs of our data structure.
So we're talking about tree traversals,
we're going to do the same thing.
We're gonna be walking through
nodes in different orders,
to essentially see what we're looking for.
So let's start with a preorder traversal.
And we're gonna do four traversals
between this video and the next.
The idea for preorder traversal,
is to visit yourself,
then visit all of your left subtree,
in the exact same way
as you did for yourself, and then you're
gonna go visit your right subtree.
That is known as a preorder traversal.
What I want to do is walk
through the steps of this, and
then we'll come back to thinking
about how we might code it.
So first off, let's start with ourselves
at A, and we mark A as visited.
Next thing is to visit
all of my left subtree.
So now I'm gonna go to B, and
I'm gonna mark B as visit.
I'm running the same code now for B.
B is next up after visiting itself,
so look at B's left subtree is D.
And that's the one I'm
gonna mark now as visited.
So D has already marked itself as visit,
it's next step is to
visit it's left subtree.
It doesn't have a left subtree, so
we're not gonna do anything there.
The next step for
D is to visit it's right subtree.
It doesn't have a right subtree either,
so were not gonna do anything there.
And since we've done all the work for
D we're gonna step back up the tree,
back to B.
So we visited all of B's
left subtree right now, but
we haven't visited all
of B's right subtree.
So next step is to run the same code on E.
We're gonna visit E and then we're gonna
look at its left subtree which is empty.
We're gonna look at its right
subtree which is empty.
At this point, I've finished doing all
the work that I was supposed to for
E and B, but
I haven't finished doing the work for A.
So A, I still need to visit
all of its right subtree.
So now I'm going to go in and visit C.
I'm gonna visit C's left subtree,
which is F.
And we're gonna learn at F's left and
right subtree.
Both of those are empty.
I'm gonna come back to C.
And we're now gonna
visit C's right subtree.
And we're gonna visit G.
And now, I finished all the work for G.
I finished all the work I need to do for
C.
And I finished all the work
I needed to do for A.
And I've done my preorder
traversal at this point.
So this problem is going to
lend itself well to recursion.
And we've seen a little bit of that so
far.
The idea here is that
when we are looking at A,
I have the problem of visiting all of my
left subtree and all of my right subtree.
Right?
But the same thing is true, so
for this tree A is the root.
But if you imagine a tree that's rooted
at B, the same thing would apply.
So when I try to run this on B,
I'm gonna do the exact same thing.
I'm gonna look at B and I'm gonna look
at its left and its right subtrees.
So the approach I'm gonna take here
is recursive and what I wanna do
is I wanna give you a method and
we're gonna kind of trace through it.
What we're gonna do is
start by just asking.
It's gonna take in a node and this is
the node that's the root of a subtree or
the whole tree.
And it's gonna say, is this node null?
If the node's null, that subtree
doesn't exist, we can just quit.
But if it isn't null, I'm gonna visit and
then I'm gonna visit it's left subrtree.
And to do that i'm gonna call
the same method within itself, and
that's what we mean by recursion.
So, I'm gonna call my whole left subtree,
it's gonna do all the work for it's
subtree, it's gonna come back and then
we're gonna do the whole right subtree.
And this may seem really short and
really clean.
It is.
This is why I'm doing this recursively.
To do these kind of traversals
recursively, it's short,
it's clean, it's nice for the code.
There are ways to do it iteratively, and
we'll talk about those in a little while.
Last step here is to have a public method,
which is called preOrder.
And there, I'm just gonna pass
in root to my helper method and
everything's gonna work just fine.
So this is the code to actually
do a full preOrder traversal
just like we talked about.
In the next video, we'll start looking
at three different kinds of traversals,
and we'll go from there.