[SOUND] Welcome back.
In this video we're gonna continue
our work with traversals.
Specifically, we're gonna learn
how to perform an in-order,
a post-order, and
a level-order traversal on a tree.
So remember from the last video
that we had a preorder traversal.
And the idea for the preorder
traversal was to visit a node itself,
then visit all that's left subtree and
then visit all that's right subtree.
And that produced this order of nodes
being visited, as you can see there.
Our goal here is to come up
with some different orderings.
So the first is,
this is called PostOrder, and
the idea here is to visit in the order D,
E, B, F, G, C, A.
And is essentially going very deep and
kinda coming back.
So we can actually do this just by
rearranging this steps of visit yourself,
visit all your left subtree and
visit all your right subtree.
If you just done with this order,
you could actually produce
a postorder traversal.
So what's you gonna do is to take
a moment, pause, think about it and
I will come back in just a moment.
So hopefully you saw that
the current ordering won't work.
This ordering is, again,
a preorder traversal.
So I need to rearrange this.
And the very first thing you probably
saw is that I can't visit myself first.
If I visited myself first and I start
with the root, I'd be visiting A, and
A's the very end, not the very beginning.
So I can't visit myself first.
I'm gonna have to push visit yourself
down at least one step to make this work.
So now at least I can visit
my left subtree first.
I'm gonna go visit my left subtree for
A, then visit my left subtree for B, visit
my left subtree for D, which is nothing.
And then finally, I visit D and
when I do that I wanna print D.
Then I'm gonna come back up to B.
I'm gonna print B.
Oh, wait, that's not what we wanted.
What we want is to essentially
print E before we print B.
So to do that, I just have to
flip the order one more time.
So all I have to do is swap, and
now I have the ordering that I want.
We'll trace through this again.
So I'm gonna visit all my left subtree.
Start at A.
Then I move down to B,
visit all B subtree.
Go to D.
Visit all of D subtree,
and now I come back, and
I visit all of these right subtree, and
then I come back, and now I print D.
Come back up for B, and
we'll visit all of B's right subtree,
which is gonna print me E, and
then I'm gonna come back to B and print B
and now we've got the ordering we want.
So just rearranging these steps
gave us the PostOrder Traversal.
So I want you to do next, we have one more
ordering of these which is interesting,
and I want you to think about what
order will these nodes be visited.
So now, I'm gonna visit my left subtree
first, then I'm gonna visit myself,
and then I'm gonna visit
all my right subtree.
This is commonly called
an InOrder Traversal.
So go ahead and take the end video quiz,
see which one you think is gonna
be the right ordering, and
we'll come back in a moment.
Welcome back.
I'm hoping that one wasn't too tricky.
So if you're starting to get a good feel
for recursion this probably wasn't to bad.
If your struggling with recursion though,
again,
we are gonna have some support
videos in the next few videos.
So what does this do, you are gonna
visit all of your subtree first, so
I'm gonna go all of B,
I'm sorry, from A I'm gonna
all of B subtree then I'm gonna do
all of D, and then I'm gonna visit.
Now, all of D's subtree,
which will give me nothing.
And then I come back to D, and
I visit it, and I print D.
And then, I come back and I print B,
and then I'm gonna go down and
I'm gonna print E.
So this is actually the one that we first
started exploring when we were talking
about the postorder traversal.
So this ordering gives us InOrder.
So just again,
we're rearranging these steps,
all you need to do to get
these different traversals.
There's one more traversal
that I'd like to do, and
that's known as a Level Order Traversal.
In the level order traversal here,
we do A, B, C, D, E, F, G.
And I wanna point out that this is
essentially a breadth first traversal.
In the previous ones we've been
looking at, the preorder and
the post order,
those are depth first traversals.
So let's explore how to do
this breadth first traversal.
And the first thing to note is that this
is gonna be a little more challenging.
The reason it's gonna be more
challenging is that I wanna
hone in on the scenario where
you're looking at node B.
So you visited A,
you visited B, and the next thing
you're supposed to visit is node C.
But you'll notice, B isn't connected to C.
B only has a connection to A, D, or E.
How is it gonna know to go to C next?
For doing this through recursion,
the ways that we just showed.
This is gonna be really hard.
We need essentially something to
keep track of the things we've seen.
The way we're gonna do
this is by keeping a list.
And if I keep a list I can essentially
add to it whenever I see new nodes, and
I can remove from the start.
That may not make to much sense just yet,
so
lets just walk through
what I mean by that.
So I've got my list and I'm gonna start
it just by putting A onto the list.
I'm not gonna count A as visited yet,
I'm just putting it on the list.
And then, I'm gonna look at my list and
remove the first element on my list.
As long as the list has elements,
I'm gonna keep removing.
So I'm gonna find it,
it has elements, I'm gonna remove A.
When I remove A, I mark it as visited.
And then, I'm gonna take all
the children of A, both B and C, and
I'm gonna put them onto the list.
I'm gonna pen them at
the back of the list.
My next step, is I'm gonna remove B.
And I'm gonna put B in my visited list.
The last thing I have to
do is add B's children,
which are D and E, to my main list.
Next step proceeding
just like the last one.
I'm gonna remove C from
the front of the list.
I'm gonna add C's children F and
G to the list.
I'm gonna do it all over again.
I'm gonna remove D.
I'm gonna add D as visited.
And then,
I wanna add these children to the list.
So I could actually add null here or I
could just check to see if they're null or
not and then choose not to add them.
You could do it either way.
I'll talk about it when we get
to the code here in a moment.
So then I'm gonna check E, again,
I don't have any children to
push on the list, so I won't.
Gonna check F and then we'll move to G.
Now, if I've done those steps,
I've done exactly what we wanted.
This is the level order traversal or
breath first traversal of this tree.
Nice, so
what I want you to realize is that we were
using this list kind of like a queue.
Or a line at a grocery store.
So if you think about it, a queue,
just like a line, works like this.
If you're at the very, if you come
up to a new line, if you're polite,
what you're gonna do is add
yourself to the end of the list.
Who gets to go next when the ATM is open?
Well, the person at the front of the line.
So you remove from the front.
This kind of data structure,
this interaction with
a list is known as a queue.
And it's also sometimes called first in,
first out, or FIFO.
So now that we have this notion
of a queue, queues exist in Java.
So you'll notice that there's an interface
called Queue that has Insert,
which is insert at the end and
that's called add.
It also has Remove,
which is remove from the front which
is exactly the behavior we want.
You can also look at the first
element by doing Examine.
Turns out that now we can
code this using this queue.
So what I'm gonna do is have
this in the BinaryTree class.
I'm gonna call this
a level order traversal.
And I'm gonna start by
creating one of these cubes.
I'm gonna create Queue of TreeNodes.
And it turns out I can actually
use LinkedList for this.
Because LinkedList implements Queue, nice.
So I'm gonna create a list of this
TreeNodes or Queue of these TreeNodes.
And I'm gonna add root at the start,
and that's gonna get things going.
Now, as long as the queue isn't empty,
I'm gonna keep removing elements
from the queue and
adding their children to the list.
So the first step within my loop is gonna
be to remove the front node in the list.
And then I'm going to check
to see if it's null or not.
If it's null, there was an empty tree,
I shouldn't do anything with it.
If it isn't null, then I'm gonna visit it,
and then I'm gonna add its LeftChild and
its RightChild to the list.
But I do wanna note, I don't necessarily
have to add the LeftChild, if it's null.
I could check if it's
null before I add it.
This is a choice you could make.
And the last thing, again,
is I'm gonna add that RightChild.
So at this point we have a good idea
of how to do a level order traversal.
And you're gonna actually use this idea in
this week's project, working with tries.