[MUSIC]
So when I was learning about trees,
I learned about the different
kind of tree traversals.
Level order, in order,
pre order, post order.
And you know,
I dutifully did the work, but
I never quite understood
what they were good for.
And so many,
many years later, well after the class I
had taken on trees, I was doing my thesis.
And at some point in that thesis
development, I realized suddenly,
this is a pattern recognition problem,
it's a problem in artificial intelligence.
That I was actually
working with a tree again.
And I was thinking about how to solve,
this one problem, that I had to solve for
my thesis.
And suddenly it hit me.
Oh my gosh,
I need a level order traversal here.
And it was of those moments, where I'm
like, oh, all that stuff I used back then.
It does have a point.
It is useful.
And it really kind of hit
the point home for me.