[MUSIC]
At this point we have a pretty good
idea of how to traverse trees.
What we're going to do next is dive
into the details of one of these trees.
The truth is, with most trees,
the data's organized in some way.
You're gonna have the highest
priority elements in your tree,
say the top maybe the shortest
words at the top.
You might have them sorted essentially
in terms of their ordering.
There's lots of ways you
can organize the tree.
So as we go forward it makes
sense to do an ordering.
In this case we're gonna look at
an ordering based on a binary search tree.
So by the end of this video' you should
be able to define a Binary Search Tree.
And be able to identify with trees that
are actually valid Binary Search Trees.
So as a quick review of binary search,
we introduced binary search back in course
one, but if you didn't take that
course with us that's totally okay,
I'm just gonna give you a really quick
highlight of what binary search is again.
What we're trying to do is if I
have an array of elements and
I wanna find an element, say Chicago.
In this array how would I do that?
Well if they're sorted,
I can do this really quickly.
I can search a sorted array much
faster than an unsorted array.
So what I can do here,
is essentially start at the middle.
Look at Essen and say what's the
relationship between Chicago and Essen?
Well first off, is Chicago Essen?
No, the words are the same.
But now I can just compare them, and
say well Chicago appears earlier
in the alphabet than Essen does.
So I can essentially now ignore Essen,
and everything to the right of Essen.
Because I know all of those are gonna be
words that start with letters greater
than E, E or greater.
And now I can just look at
the other half of the array.
So I've actually gotten rid of half
of the elements just with one check,
that's why this is so powerful.
So now I'm gonna look at Beijing, that's
the middle of the other half of the array.
And now I'm gonna ask it what's the
difference between Beijing and Chicago.
Well, they're not the same, so
I'm gonna do the same comparison,
Beijing is now less than Chicago,
so I can eliminate Beijing and
everything to the left of Beijing.
And now we can go to the middle
of the remaining array,
which at this point is just Chicago, and
check, and I've actually found Chicago.
So this is why Binary Search is so
powerful is that again,
we get rid of half of the elements
every time we do a comparison.
So we can find things in O(log n) time.
So sorted arrays are fantastic, then,
for search, because of that run time but
where sorted arrays are bad is in
terms of insertion and removal.
If I try to insert a city into this,
say San Diego, well that's gonna be not so
bad because I can just
insert it right at the end.
But if I want to insert another city,
say Pullman where I grew up,
now I'm gonna have to move some around
to be able to make room for that.
And we know that arrays cannot be
dynamically resized either, so
we're gonna have to always make
copies into bigger arrays.
It gets really messy.
What we want are all the nice features
of a linked list in terms of insertion,
but all the benefits in terms
of search of a sorted array.
And we're gonna get that
from a Binary Search Tree.
Say the idea behind a binary search tree
is take all these elements in this array
and just organize them as a tree, so all I
have to do is essentially pull these out,
make them tree nodes, connect them as a
tree, and now I have a Binary Search Tree.
So now I can do the same kind of searching
I did within an array, but I can also
get the benefit of a fast insert and
a fast removal that a tree provides.
So, what do I have to have to make
this a quote binary Search Tree.
So a Binary Search Tree has to,
first of all, be a binary tree.
So each node can have
at most two children.
On top of that, the left subtree has
to be strictly less than the parent.
So everything in the left
subtree must be lesser and
everything in the right subtree must
be greater than that parent element.
So now that we have an idea of
the definition of a Binary Search Tree,
what I wanted to do is give you a number
of trees and ask you which of these,
essentially are Binary Search Trees.
So what you do go into the in-video quiz,
answer the question and
we'll come back and
talk through all of them.
Welcome back.
I hope that the in-video quiz helped and
you're starting to get a better feel for
what is a Binary Search Tree.
So let's look at these one by one.
First off,
A is in fact a Binary Search Tree, right?
42 is greater than 32,
32 is greater than 12.
So the ordering is preserved, and
no node has more than two children.
So this is a Binary Search Tree.
B was not a binary search tree because if
you noticed, 42 is greater than 32 but
32 is part of the right sub tree of 42,
so it has to be greater.
So that's not allowed,
this isn't a binary search tree.
C is also not a binary search tree,
but for
a different reason,
42 here has 3 children.
Three children make it not a binary tree,
and hence not a binary search tree.
And lastly, you notice that in D,
this was actually the trickiest of them,
42 is less than 45.
You can't have this.
You can't have an element in the left sub
tree which is greater than the parent.
So this would not be allowed 45 should
actually be on the right side of 42 so
at this point we have a good feel for
what binary search trees are.
What we're gonna do next is find out how
do we perform a search within that binary
search tree.