[MUSIC]
Now that we have a good idea of
what a binary search tree is,
let's talk about how we do
a search in a binary search tree.
So by the end of this video,
you should be able to perform
searches within a binary search tree.
So the idea behind a binary search tree is
very similar to binary search of an array.
So what we're gonna do is I'm just going
to give you a few examples of this and
then we'll talk about how we
could solve this with code.
So first off, let's say I'm trying to find
element C, well how am I gonna get there?
Well I'm gonna start with the root and
we'll look and I'm gonna say is E C?
Are those the same things?
No they are not.
E is actually greater than C.
And because E is greater than C, it tells
me to look in the left sub tree of E.
So, my next step is to move my
current notion of tree node down to B.
I'm going to look at B and compare B to C.
Are they the same?
They're not.
B is less than C.
So I now need to look at
the right sub tree of B.
So now I'm gonna head and look at C.
So in other words in node C where
going to ask is C equal to C.
It is, yay, we found it!
We're done,
all we have to is return true or
return the node depending on what
we're doing with the search.
We found this binary search
tree contains the element C.
So, let's do one more example here.
Let's start searching for P.
So, what I'm gonna do is
again start at the root.
I'm going to look at E.
I'm gonna ask.
I'm gonna compare E and P, and
I'm gonna ask are they the same.
They're not.
E is less than P, so
I'm gonna go into the right sub tree of E.
So now I'm gonna look at M.
I'm gonna ask again,
what's the relationship between M and P?
Well, M is still less than P so
I need to go to the right sub-tree of M.
And now I'm gonna look at Q.
And I'm gonna see that,
do the same comparison, Q is not P.
I'm gonna see that Q is greater than P,
therefore I need to look
in the left sub tree of Q.
There is no left sub tree of Q.
P is not in this array, so
it's no here and I can return false.
Essentially that's not found.
So now that we have the idea
of how to do this search,
the question is how are we
gonna put this into code?
Well first off, you could solve this
fairly cleanly using recursion.
And the way I want you to think about this
is that if I'm thinking about what do I
wanna do at node E, so
the tree rooted at node E.
It's very similar to what I'm gonna want
to do when I'm looking at the sub tree
rooted at node B, which is very similar
to the comparisons I might make for
the sub tree rooted at C.
So because it's the same behavior at each
step, this lends itself well to recursion.
You can also solve this very
cleanly using iteration.
And here you would just have a loop where
you're essentially keeping track of your
current node.
So just like we did before, you'd have
your current node be E, then B, then C and
you can just essentially walk
through the tree that way.
Now at this point,
I want you to try this on your own.
So you're gonna be searching
in the project for an element.
And I'd like you to try that code
on your own before you look for
any support videos.
But if you want some more support, and
you're a little bit stuck on how to search
a tree, we have a more thorough
walk through of doing search
in one of our support videos, so
you can always look at that there.
Next, we're gonna start looking
at how to do insertion and
deletion from this binary search tree.