[APPLAUSE]
>> All right,
so in that last video,
Leo talked you through the algorithm for
finding an element in
a binary search tree.
And in this support video,
we're actually going to implement
that algorithm in Java code.
Now if you wanna work on this yourself and
you don't want to see the Java code,
you're welcome to do that.
Come back to the support video
only if you really get stuck.
Now looking ahead, you're not actually
ever going to be implementing the code for
binary search tree find in this course.
What you'll be doing is you'll be
implementing a find algorithm for
the tree structure that you're going to
be using as part of your project which is
not actually going to be
a binary search tree.
But going through the binary
search tree find algorithm
is going to help you with that process.
And in particular going through the code,
is going to reveal some subtleties
that you'll have to work with
when you implement the algorithm
that you implement on your project.
So, let's start with a task.
Our goal is to find whether or
not an element that's passed in as
a parameter is in our binary search tree.
So Leo walked you through the steps.
You basically are just gonna
search down through the tree
until you either fall of the end or you
find the element that you're looking for.
And at each step you always
know which way to go.
You go left if the element you
are looking for is smaller than
the one that you're at, and you go right
if the element that you are looking for
is greater than the one that you're at.
So simple enough, right?
So we've got our root pointer in our tree.
And let's just say that our first attempt
says, let's take that root pointer and
step it down the tree.
So I'm looking for
L, I take my root pointer, I go to
the right because L is greater than E.
And at this point you might
look at this diagram and
say, oh, that's kind of a problem.
We lost our root of our tree and
we'll never be able to get it back.
So, lesson number one,
don't change your root pointer.
That's what's holding the whole tree so
that you can get to it.
Your root pointer has to
stay pointed to the root.
So instead what we're going to
do is we're going to introduce
a second variable, curr.
And curr's job is going to be to step
down the tree as we're looking for
the element we're trying to find.
So we can change curr, that's no problem.
Curr starts at the root and
then it's gonna progress down the tree.
It's going to progress down the tree
by going left or right depending on
how the element we're looking for compares
to the element we're currently at.
So that's going to, in this first case for
example, L is greater than E so
we'd want to go to the right.
So you can see that there's
two things we need to do here.
We need to compare the element
that we're currently at,
curr, to the element that
we're trying to find.
And then based on the comparison
the second thing we need to do is we
need to update our current pointer.
So that's what these
if statements do here.
Now you can see that in these if
statements we are using the greater than
and less than symbols.
In general these symbols are not
going to work for our comparison, for
comparing objects.
So we're gonna come back to
that idea in just a moment
when I get to the end of this algorithm
I'll come back to that subtlety.
But for now let's finish this up
that if we decide that we are not
less than the thing that we're looking at,
and we're not greater than the thing that
we're looking at, well then we must be
equal to the thing that we're looking at.
So what should we do?
For example in this case,
we find that L is equal to L.
In that case, this else condition, we know
that we've found the thing we're looking
for and so we should just go ahead and
return true.
Okay so we're getting there.
Now we have our movement going left and
right and
returning true if we found
the element we're looking for.
But that's not quite enough.
We need to keep doing this over and
over and over again.
So that means we need a loop and
if we're going to have a loop,
we need a loop condition.
We need to know when should we stop
this process of moving down the tree or
conversely, when should we keep going?
So in the algorithm Leo walked you
through, you saw that you should keep
going as long as you have not
fallen off the end of the tree.
How do you know you have fallen
off of the end of the tree?
You've fallen off the end of
the tree when current equals null.
So we'll add that while loop in here as
a wrapper around our if statements that
while curr is not equal to null,
we should do these comparisons and
move curr down the tree.
If we ever find the thing we're
looking for, we'll return true.
Great, looks good right?
So are we done?
Think about that for a second.
All right, well hopefully you said no and
if you tried to compile this code,
you would find that it actually
gives you a compile error.
And the reason for this is we've figured
out what to if we find the element, but
right now we have no action that we're
taking if we don't find the element.
So how do we know that we
didn't find the element?
Well we didn't find the element if we fell
all the way off the bottom of the tree.
So if we fall all the way off the bottom
of the tree, that loop has ended,
and in that case will return false.
So that's almost the complete code for
find.
We just need to go back and address
this issue I mentioned at the beginning
of this greater than, less than symbol
not working for object comparisons.
So what we're going to do is
instead of using greater than and
less than operators, we're going
to use a method called compareTo.
So the compareTo method
does the following.
If the calling object is less than
the object you pass in as a parameter,
compareTo is going to return
a value that's less than zero.
So we'll assign the variable comp to
have the value that's returned by
taking toFind and
compareTo on the current data object.
And if that value is less than zero
then we know that toFind is less
than the data object we're currently
looking at and we should go to the left.
On the other hand, if the calling object
is greater than the object we passed in
as a parameter, then compareTo is going to
return a value that's greater than zero.
So in that case, in our code,
we'll go to the right.
And then finally,
if these two objects are equal,
if the calling object is equal to
the thing we pass in as a parameter,
then it returns zero and so
that's our else condition here.
If the comp is not less than zero,
and it's not greater than zero
then it must be equal to zero and
we found the thing we're looking for.
So that's how you can use compareTo to
make this a more general method to compare
any two objects.
Well, not quite.
compareTo doesn't work on just any object.
It only works on objects that implement
this interface called Comparable.
So you're going to have to put this magic
in your class header if you implement
a BST class, which says that you have
a BST that holds these type objects E,
but E has to be a very specific type.
It has to be a type that
actually implements or
extends in this nomenclature
the Comparable interface.
Don't worry too much about that
little magical statement there.
Basically what we are saying is that E
has to be the type that can have this
compareTo method called on it because it
is a very specific interface in Java.
But fortunately for you, things you
want to compare like strings, integers,
characters, they all implement
the Comparable interface, so
you can call this compare to
method on them without fear.
So that's it.
That's the full find method for
binary search trees.