[MUSIC]
In the last video we saw how to
search a binary search tree but
we didn't really see how to
add elements to it just yet.
So let's talk about how to insert
into a binary search tree.
And again, this is part of the motivation
for having a binary search tree.
Sorted arrays are great for search but
if you wanna do an insertion or
removal, linked lists or
trees are much better for performance.
So, by the end of this video
you should be able to insert
an item into the binary search tree.
So here's a binary search tree.
I have 20 as my root, and
then I've got children below those.
And the question is,
where should I insert 7 into this tree?
Now I have some options for you.
I could insert it in Option A,
Option B, Option C.
Is it okay to do either Option A or
Option B?
What I want you to do is answer this in
the in-video quiz and we'll come back and
talk about it.
I hope the in-video quiz helped you see
some of the limitations you have with
the binary search tree in where
you can place your nodes.
So lets talk through these one by one.
first off, option C isn't allowed.
7 is much less than 30, it can not
be part of the right sub-tree of 30.
Similarly though Option B
isn't allowed either, right?
7 is still less than ten, so
you can't have seven be part
of the right sub-tree of ten.
That eliminates Option D as well,
leaving us just with Option A.
In fact, this is the only place you can
place seven into this binary search tree.
With binary search trees,
there's only one place you can
insert a node when you do so.
So let's add in 7 into
this binary search tree.
Let's do a couple more of these.
Where should I add 27?
So what I'm gonna do, same idea as before,
is I'm gonna look at 20, 27 is greater
than 20, so I'm gonna go into the right
sub-tree of 20 and I'm gonna look at 30.
27 is less so
I have to go into 30's left sub-tree.
Then I'm going to do 25,
and 25 is less than 27.
So I go into 27's right sub-tree
only to find that 25 doesn't have
a right sub-tree.
Perfect, this is the place
I'm gonna put it.
I'm gonna insert right as
the right child of 25.
What am I gonna do then
if I'm want to insert 8?
Same algorithm applies.
You're gonna start at 20, you're gonna see
8 is less than 20, you're gonna go to 10,
8 is still less than 10.
So you're gonna go down to 5.
8 is greater than five so
you are going to 7.
8 is greater than 7 and here you find
your spot where you can insert that node.
Now what want to point out at
this point is that when you
commonly see Binary Search Trees
they're almost always full tress and
what I mean by that is all of
the levels are completely filled.
There is no constraint on insert or
binary search tree in itself that it
has to be full or essentially balanced.
You can have just a long string of
nodes in a binary search tree and
it's still a binary search tree.
Mia in the next lesson is actually going
to get into the details of how this
affects run times in asymptotic
run time Again, if you
want to go to code this, you can do this
either with recursion or with iteration.
So, if you want to do it recursively, you
again notice that at any given node you're
essentially solving the same problem as
you would have for the previous node.
So recursion applies here really cleanly,
but so does iteration.
With iteration you're just gonna
keep track of your current node and
essentially walk through
the tree that way.
We'll show you how to do that iterative
approach in our support video.
But again I wanna encourage you
to try this on your own first.
I think just knowing the details
of the algorithm is enough for
you to try to code this
on your own in a project.
And then if you get stuck, come back and
try watching the support video.
What we'll do lastly with binary
search trees is look at deletion and
we'll do that in the next video.