[APPLAUSE]
>> All right, so
now you've seen the algorithm for insert
and Leo walked you through some examples.
Let's implement it in Java code.
Again, this is going to be similar to
code that you're going to write for
this part of your project,
but not identical.
But doing this exercise will help you
write the code for your project as well.
So, the algorithm for insert is actually
pretty similar to the algorithm for find.
And in those examples that Leo walked you
through, you saw that essentially what
we're doing here is that we're finding
the element that we're trying to insert.
And if it's in the tree,
we don't do anything.
But if it's not in the tree, then what we
want to do is insert it where we ended
up with our search down through the tree.
Because we're always going to be
inserting as a leaf node in the tree.
So one idea that might occur to you
is well, we've already written find.
So let's just take that code for
find, here it is.
This is the exact same code
that we wrote last time.
Just put it there, and
then wherever we end up,
wherever curr ends up,
we'll just insert our new node there.
We might write a statement like this.
What I want you to do is
think about does this work?
Okay, so hopefully you said no,
that doesn't work, and here's why.
The key reason why this doesn't work
is because of this while loop condition
that we have here.
We're running that loop as long
as curr is not equal to null.
Meaning that once that loop stops and
breaks out, curr is equal to null.
It's actually fallen all the way off the
bottom of that tree, it points to nothing.
Well, that's no good because
now when we create a new node,
we end up creating it just
off the bottom of the tree.
So we can create it,
have curr point to it, but
it's not connected into the tree at all.
So it hasn't successfully been
inserted into the binary search tree.
In fact, what we have done here in this
statement is we've linked that node's
parent to curr, which was null, and so
it's just floating off there in space.
Once curr goes away, it'll go away too.
So that didn't quite work.
The key to this algorithm is,
and the implementation is,
we need to stop curr before it
falls off the bottom of the tree.
So, in order to do that,
we're gonna need to change the structure
of our while loop just a bit.
So here's what we're going to do.
In some cases, like this one here,
where curr is pointing to C,
which is a leaf node,
it might be pretty straightforward.
If the node curr is pointing to is a leaf,
it has no children at all, then it's
easy to tell that we should stop.
But other cases is
a little bit more subtle.
So what if curr is pointing to this node,
B?
B has one child.
How do we know if curr should stop?
Curr should stop if the node is supposed
to be inserted to the left, but
it shouldn't stop if the node is
supposed to be inserted to the right.
So we're gonna need to do something
a little more clever than just check to
see if the node is a leaf.
And I've alluded to
what we're going to do,
which is we need to check
the direction we're going to go first,
in order to determine whether
we wanna stop or keep going.
So what we're going to do here is we're
gonna create a while loop whose condition
checks first which direction
curr is trying to go, and
then verifies to see whether that
direction it's tried to go is not null.
So, if comp, as we saw before,
if comp < 0, curr wants to go left.
And as long as that left child
is not null, it can go left, so
the while loop should continue.
If comp > 0, curr wants to go right, and
as long as that right child is not null,
it can continue.
So there's our while condition.
Now, inside the loop, our goal is
just to walk curr down the tree.
Again, we need to check comp.
If comp < 0, curr goes to the left.
If comp > 0, curr goes to the right.
Now there's one more thing we need to do,
which is we need to update comp so
that it's ready to go for
the next while loop check.
Now you'll notice that this while
loop doesn't handle the case that
comp is actually equal to 0, and
we'll talk about that in just a moment.
So, what should we do next?
Well let's consider what might be
true when this while loop ends.
So when does this while loop
actually break out of its loop?
It breaks out if either of
these two conditions is true.
So, either curr is pointing to a node
that's about to fall off the end,
so it's ready to insert the new
thing that it's trying to insert.
Or, it's found the thing
it's trying to insert.
And the code that appears after this
while loop just has to distinguish
between those two different conditions and
do the right thing as appropriate.
So let's consider this first scenario
that we'd be in, that curr points to
the last node that it wants to search for
and it's ready to insert the new node.
In that case, again,
we just need to figure out,
should we insert it to the left, or
should we insert it to the right.
So again we check comp, if comp < 0,
we create a new node,
link it in as a left child of curr.
And if comp > 0, we create a new node
link it in as the right child of curr.
Finally, if the other scenario is true,
if we didn't break out because we'd found
the place to insert, but we broke out of
the while loop because we actually found
the element we were trying to insert.
Then we should just simply return false,
indicating that we didn't
do anything to the tree.
We didn't insert the value
because it was already there.
So that's just about it.
The last thing we have to do is we have to
indicate that if we didn't return false,
then we must have successfully
inserted that node.
So ultimately, if we ever get to the very
end of this method, will return true.
So that's it, it's just slightly
more complicated than find.
But you can see it has a little
bit of the same flavor
as that find method we wrote last time.
And here's the full code for
the insert method.