[MUSIC]
>> In the last video we saw how to
insert into a binary search tree.
In this video we're gonna
start looking at how to remove
an element from a binary search tree.
And you won't have to do removal for
your project, so
we're gonna look at this
really at just a high level.
So by the end of this video
you should be able to delete
an object from a binary search tree.
So let's think about deletion
in a couple of scenarios.
The first is what do I wanna do if I
have this binary search tree here and
I wanna delete seven?
That's actually gonna be really clean.
Right?
Seven is a leaf node.
I can essentially just remove the link
from five to seven and I'm done.
So by setting five's
right pointer to be null,
the garbage collector will
clean this up for us.
So this one's nice and clean.
Leaf nodes, easy to remove.
Let's look at another example.
So I've changed the tree
around a little bit.
And let's say now I wanna remove five.
So this one's little bit more difficult,
right?
Because I can't just cut
the link from ten to five,
because if I did that I'd lose seven.
And I want seven to remain in my tree.
But if I only have one element below me,
I can actually just hoist that element up.
And what I mean by that is
essentially just take the pointer
that's going from ten to five and
make it now point to seven.
And just by changing that reference, so
ten's left reference to seven, again,
the garbage collector will
clean up five for us.
So these two scenarios are fairly
clean and aren't too hard to coat.
There is gonna be one scenario that's
gonna be a little bit trickier.
So let's look at a whole other tree here.
I made some changes to the tree.
And the idea here is to delete ten.
And what I want you to do is just pause
for a few seconds, think about it, and
then we'll come back.
All right.
As you were working through that one,
you almost instantly saw
that this is tricky, right?
Trying to remove an element
that has two children?
There aren't really clean ways to do this.
I can't hoist up fifteen because then I've
got problems with both five and twelve,
are supposed to be children of fifteen.
And there's just, this gets really messy.
So I want to tell you is essentially
the algorithm to solve this in
the general case.
The way to do this is to essentially
realize that I could replace ten
with something else.
They way that I'm gonna do that is I'm
gonna look through, again this is tricky,
I'm gonna look through my right
subtree to find the smallest element.
The smallest element on my right
sub tree is gonna be twelve.
Now I wanna point out something really
important about finding the smallest
element in your right sub tree.
If it's the smallest element, you know
that it's left reference is null, right?
Twelve's left reference has to be null
because if it were anything else,
that thing would be smaller.
So we know that there's only,
at most, one child of twelve, and
that's going to be important
here in just a moment.
So let's find the smallest value in the
right sub tree, and then what I'm going to
do is hoist that value up, but
just the value, not the node.
So what I'm going to do is take ten,
remove the value ten,
and replace it with twelve.
And then you're gonna say,
well, wait a second.
Now you've got duplicates in your tree.
I absolutely do.
And the way that I'm gonna
handle this is I'm going to now
perform a delete on twelve on
the sub tree rooted at fifteen.
So I'm gonna delete this duplicate.
And you might say, well, wait a second,
that could be complex,
deleting this one, too.
But it won't be because we know that
at least, at most, it has one child.
And from the earlier examples we saw,
deleting a leaf node is easy and
deleting a node that has just
one child is actually easy.
So removing this duplicate
isn't going to be too bad.
The hard part, which is recognizing
where you can find the element and
how to bring that up in.
So, now that you have a good
idea of how to delete,
you could potentially
code this on your own.
I encourage you to do so.
So, in this lesson,
you've actually learned a great deal.
You've learned how to create trees and
what trees are in computer science.
And that trees play a large
role in a number of
things that we do as computer scientists.
We have explored different ways of
traversing these trees, and we have
looked really closely at binary search
trees doing search, insert, and delete.
There are a number of trees, again,
in the field of Computer Science and
I encourage you to look at more of
these for more details on your own.
Next what we will do is look
at the run time analysis for
binary search trees to see, really,
are these better than other approaches?