[SOUND] So in this lesson on trees,
you've seen a lot of jargon and
a lot of notation and terminology.
And so this concept challenge helps
you put all the concepts together and
really see how the different
pieces impact one another.
Now, you're used to the routine here.
You'll be presented with a question and
we'll invite you to solve
the problem yourself.
Then you'll discuss with other
learners either around you or
on the discussion forums, and
then you'll watch the UC San Diego
students video where they
discuss the question.
You'll be invited to answer the question
again and then we'll recap the solution.
So, in this problem, what you'll be doing
is thinking about how the insertion order
of elements into a binary search
tree impact the shape of the tree.
>> Hi I'm Alan.
>> I'm Melissa.
>> I'm Sarah.
>> So I think these are all
valid trees because each node,
everything less than the node
is less than the node, and
everything to the right of
the node is greater than the node.
>> Yeah.
So for A, the root always comes first,
and so there's two first,
and it could be either one or four, right?
>> Right.
>> Yeah.
>> So two, one and then two,
four and then eight on the end.
>> One could also come in the end, too.
>> Yeah, that's true, so
it could be two, four, eight and one.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, so
there's three possibilities for A.
>> So for B.
So if the rest come first,
then it has to be two, and then
one can still come at the end since it's
on its own, it doesn't have any children.
>> Yes.
>> So it doesn't have children,
it can come at the end right?
>> Yeah, if it doesn't,
that makes sense, yeah.
>> All right, so, and
then four has to be after eight.
>> Yes.
>> So it'd be two, eight, four, and
then one could come over.
And then C, it is one long one so
they have to be in order.
>> Yeah.
>> Efficient though.
>> Yeah true.
>> I think D's a little weird
with the two at the end.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah that confused me a bit.
I thought that was
an invalid tree at first.
>> Yeah.
>> I thought it was an invalid tree.
>> But I think it's a valid tree since
two can come after four since it's
smaller than four on the left.
>> Yeah, that's true.
So, the root, which is one,
comes first, and then-
>> And then it would have to be four,
cuz it's the one's only child.
And then I guess two and
eight come in either order.
>> Yeah, so
there's two possibilities for D.
>> So as you saw when the U C San Diego
students discussed this problem,
all the four options are valid trees.
You can think about the root
node of each of these trees,
you can think about the leaf
nodes of each of these trees, and
you notice that they're all satisfying the
properties that are required for trees,
and not only that,
they're all binary search trees.
And so notice that every node has at most
two children and that when we look at
the elements or the values stored in
each of these nodes, we always have that
nodes on the left have smaller values
than the nodes to the right of them.
So we have four valid options
of binary search trees.
But, then, the question is, in what order
might we have inserted the elements
in order to get to these very, very
different shaped trees that we have here.
So let's start with the first option,
option A and
we notice that the root of the tree will
have to come first when we insert it.
And that's because when we insert
nodes into a binary search tree,
we always insert nodes as leaf nodes,
so they don't have any children.
And so if we start out with nothing,
our very first element is
going to be the root node because the root
is not a child of any other node.
So we know that our first element to go
in is going to have to be the number two.
But then the question
is what happens next?
And whether there are any constraints
that are imposed on us by the shape that
we see already.
And what the learners discussed, and
what you might be observing as well,
is that the eight had to have been
inserted after the four because it shows
up here as a child of the node four.
And so
that means that in our possible orderings,
eight is always going to come after four.
But that means that it could go at the end
so then it could have two and then one and
then four and eight.
Or we could have had four and eight be
inserted immediately after two and then
the one at the end, or we could have had
four inserted and then one and then eight.
And that's okay because the node for
one and the nodes for
four and eight really don't interact
very much with one another,
and so they could have been inserted
in any order into this tree.
All right, so these are the three
options that we have for
insertion orders that lead into
this shaped binary search tree.
But now let's look at option B and
we notice that we have
a slightly similar shaped tree.
As before the root comes first, and
as before, we noticed that when
we have a child node, that it had to
have been inserted after its parent.
And so that means that we have
a constraint of four had to be inserted
after eight.
But as before, there's still some
freedom in terms of how we insert one
relative to the nodes four and eight.
And so again, we have the three options
that mirrored the collection of
options that we had for option A.
But now we get to something quite
different when we look at option C, and
in option C we notice that the shape that
we're thinking about is a linear shape.
And so we start at the bottom with the
root and the root had to come first, but
then we have other constraints as well.
So we see that the node two
had to be inserted after one,
because that's a child of one, but then
also four needed to be inserted after two
because it's a child of two, and then also
eight needed to be inserted after four,
and so all of a sudden we have completely
constrained the insertion order into this
binary search tree because every single
node has already been determined.
It's position in the insertion order
completely determined, and so the order
in which we inserted elements is exactly
one, then two, then four, then eight.
And that's the only way to have
inserted them, in order and
in that order,
in order to get that path-like tree.
All right.
Last but not least,
we've got this tree and
it looks quite different from the other
ones that we've thought about.
Still, the root will have to come first
when we insert into this tree, but now
notice that the dependencies are that both
leaf nodes are children of that node four.
And so both two and eight needed to be
inserted after four, which meant that four
had to come right after one, right
after the root, in the insertion order,
because we had to have space for
two other elements behind it.
But those two other elements, well they
could go in whatever order they want
because neither is a child of the other.
And so we have two options for
the insertion order,
either two before eight or
eight before two.
And now we've gone through all of
the options that we were considering and
the take home message of this concept
challenge is that the order in which
we put elements into a binary
search tree impact the shape, and
what you'll see is that the shape of
the binary search tree will have a huge
impact on the performance of operations
with that binary search tree.
And so you want to keep that in mind when
you're working with this data structure.