[MUSIC]
In this video, we're gonna dive
into the details of something
called abstract data types and how they're
implemented as interfaces in Java.
So by the end of this video, you'll be
able to explain the idea of abstraction
both in Java and in the real world,
and describe why it is important.
And you'll also be able to describe the
difference between an Abstract Data Type
as well as a Data Structure,
which does the implementation.
We're getting into this really
key idea in computer science, and
really in the whole world,
in our lives, called abstraction.
Abstraction is the idea of hiding away
the details of how something works
in order to focus on the key features
you need to interact with that thing.
And it's really how we
function with the world.
And it's certainly the key behind
implementing large scale software systems.
So let me give you an example
of abstraction that
you should be familiar with.
So here's the example of a car.
And in particular, your car brakes.
Let me ask you a question.
Do you know how your car brakes work?
Now you might say, mm, no, not really.
I'm not a mechanic.
I don't really know how they work.
But if you ask me this question I say,
sure I do.
Here's how they work.
I put my foot on the brake pedal and
my car stops.
That's all I need to know.
So the difference between this first
thought with thinking about what's
under the hood and the details of
the brakes, and the way I described it,
which is step on the pedal and my car
stops, is the difference between being on
either side of something
called an abstraction barrier.
When I'm on the user side of
the abstraction barrier, I only care
about the behavior that happens when
I interact with my car's brakes.
Like I said,
I put my foot on the pedal and
it stops, that's all I need to
know in order to drive a car.
I don't have to know how things
are implemented under the hood.
But in order for
my car to have functioning brakes,
somebody has to be on the other
side of the abstraction barrier.
Somebody has to know how my
brakes are actually implemented.
The person who designed my car,
the manufacturer of my car,
a mechanic who's gonna fix my brakes,
they're on the other side of
the abstraction barrier, concerned with
the specific implementation of my brakes.
As long as they fulfill the contract,
that I put my foot on the brake pedal and
my car stops, I don't particularly
care how my brakes are implemented.
And that's what allows majority of us to
drive our cars without being a mechanic
who knows about every single detail.
The same idea exists in software systems,
in particular,
in something we're gonna look
at called data abstraction.
In order to work with
large quantities of data,
it's not important that you understand
exactly how that data is organized if
you're simply a user of
a particular data repository.
So what you care about is how
you can interact with that data.
So let's take the example of a list.
A list is kind of an abstract notion.
It's a set of elements arranged
to some particular order.
And you can do things with those elements.
You can add elements to your list.
You can give the size of your list.
You can get an element at
a particular index in your list.
You can iterate over the list
in a particular order.
All of this is specified in something
called the Abstract Data Type.
And these Abstract Data Types often
manifest themselves as either interfaces
or as abstract classes in Java.
In Java, there's an interface that's
called the list that embodies this
abstract notion of a collection of
elements organized in a sequential order.
But really the abstract notion of a list
goes beyond a specific
programming language.
You can think of a grocery list,
or a list of students in a class.
These things are not
directly related to code.
So this idea of
an Abstract Data Type is broader
than just a particular implementation
in a particular programming language.
It's really just this abstract concept
of how we interact with this data.
It's a promise.
On the other side of
the abstraction barrier,
we have our specific implementation of the
list functionality, in this case, in Java.
You're probably already familiar
with the array list class.
You've used it several times.
And what that class does is it implements
the list interface, it fulfills all
of the functionality of a list, using an
array to store the elements in the list.
So it can use the array to put
the elements in a particular order.
As you know, an array organizes elements
in order with indices to access
the different elements in the array.
So that's one particular
implementation of this list interface.
And this specific implementation
using a data structure, or
particular organization of data
under the hood called an array.
But the array is not the only
way we can implement
the list interface in this
abstract data type list.
So throughout the rest of this module,
we're actually gonna be looking at
a different implementation of the list
interface called a link list,
which we'll get into
starting in the next video.
Before we move on to the next video,
I just want to go back to this idea that
there are always two sides
of an abstraction barrier.
On the one hand there's the user side, and
you'll be on this side whenever you're
using built-in libraries in Java.
You'll be using the defined interfaces,
and
you care mostly about the behavior,
not so much about the implementation.
On the other side of things, when you're
a library developer, which you'll
also be in this class, you care a lot
about the specific implementation.
And the specific implementation
must fulfill the contract, but
it's also going to have impacts of
how fast it fulfills the contract.
What's the performance of a particular
choice of underlying data structure
to fulfill an abstract data type contract?
So we'll start to make all these ideas
much more concrete when we dive into
the implementation of the Linked List
data structure in the next video.