[MUSIC]
So, a few years ago, I was one of a very
small team of engineers trying to get
Google's Shopping Express
project off the ground.
Now, Shopping Express is a service that
Google provides, which allows customers to
place orders across a variety of different
merchants, through a single website.
And when they place their order, we send
couriers to go pick the orders up, and
then deliver them to
the customers within a few hours.
So these days, Shopping Express is a
successful service with dozens of merchant
partners, and
it operates in 89 different U.S. cities.
But back in the beginning,
we had no idea if it'd work.
How many orders would we
be able to deliver per day?
How long would it take?
How much would it cost?
We had no idea.
So what could we do?
Building something like
Shopping Express requires a lot of
investments and infrastructure.
And you really don't wanna do that, unless
you have some idea about whether it's
gonna work, so
what you could do is build a fake version.
In other words, build some software to
simulate what the real thing might do.
You might say, tell it how many couriers
you have available, how many orders you
think you're gonna get, and then have
the simulator figure out how to route
the couriers around the city, and
deliver the packages from A to B.
So that's what we did,
over a period of several weeks,
we built a simulator, and
it was pretty simple to start with.
And it got gradually more sophisticated,
the very first version had the couriers
just moving in straight lines,
as if they were birds.
But the final version had them following
roads correctly, and it even took traffic
into account when it was trying figure
out the optimal routes to send them on.
And the simulator had a map,
which showed the couriers traveling
around the city delivering things.
Now, not only was this really cool,
it was actually useful for
debugging the simulator, and also for
getting some insights into how
we could improve the algorithms
we used to round them.
So a simulator like this is actually
a great way to illustrate Polymorphism.
If you can imagine the part of the code
that was used to render the map.
Now what sort of things do
we wanna see on the map?
We wanna see a picture of the city.
We wanna see the roads.
But we're, particularly, interested in
the objects that are interesting to
the simulator, like the couriers, like the
stores, where they're picking things up,
like the customers where
they're going to deliver.
Now, these three kinds of objects
are all pretty different, but
they do have something in common,
they all need to be drawn on the map.
So one way you can approach this
is by coming with an interface.
Let's call it drawable,
so things can be drawn.
And it might have a single method
which is something like draw me.
So the courier's draw me method,
would maybe draw a picture of a van.
The store's draw me method would draw
a picture of a building, for example.
Now as far as a map
rendering code is concerned,
it doesn't need to care about any of
these objects, and what they are.
All it knows Is that it has
a bunch of drawable object, and
it calls draw me on all of them, and
they all draw themselves correctly.
Now, the nice thing about this is that,
down the line, if you need to introduce
a new object, let's say a warehouse,
you can make that implement the drawable
interface, implement the draw me method,
which draws presumably a bigger building.
And you pass that along to
the rendering code, and
the rendering code is none the wiser.
It just draws these objects.
It's just a drawable.
And it draws the warehouse
correctly on the map.
So, that's really, really helpful.
Now Polymorphism isn't only for
small objects like these icons.
Now one of the things about writing
a simulator is that we wanted to try out
lots of different strategies for
routing the couriers, and
these strategies were pretty big tweaks
of code, very sophisticated in the end.
But a lot of this simulator, like the map
rendering code or the input code,
and so on, could be the same for
all of them you need to change.
So one thing you can do,
one thing we did do, was to create a name,
an interface called,
I think it was called routing engine.
So all these different strategies for
routing couriers would
implement that interface.
And then, we could swap different ones in,
and see how they compare very easily,
because the rest of the code didn't care.
It just had a routing engine.
It didn't need to know about
the insides about how it worked.
They were all just routing engines.
They were all the same.
As far as it was concerned.
Now, of course, they weren't the same.
Some of the initial ones
were really simple.
For example, the first one we did,
every order that was placed,
a single courier went to the store,
picked it up and
took it back, just to that one customer,
so, not particularly efficient.
Later, routing engine implementations
were much more sophisticated than that.
But again, the point is that, as far as,
most of the code was concerned,
you didn't have to change anything,
you could just change the algorithm,
make it an implement routing engine,
plug it in, and Polymorphism did the rest.