[MUSIC]
So this video, we're going to dive
into some implementations of that list
interface that we introduced
in the last video.
We're gonna look at two implementations,
the Array List and the Linked List, and
we'll get into the Linked List in some
detail, since that's a new data structure.
So by the end of this video,
you'll be able to describe and draw
the structure of a LinkedList, and you'll
be able to give at least one advantage of
using a LinkedList over an ArrayList for
implementing the list interface.
So, as we mentioned in the last video, the
idea of an abstract data type is that it
specifies behavior but
doesn't specify implementation.
So it's up to the developer of
the library to specify the implementation
of a particular behavior.
So in Java,
if I wanna implement an interface,
I promise to fulfil all the functionality,
but I can do it however I wanna do it,
as long as the functionality is fulfilled.
Java provides two built-in
implementations, at least two,
more than two built-in implementations
of the list interface.
One of which, you're very familiar
with called the ArrayList,
uses an array to implement
the functionality of the list.
And the other is called the LinkedList,
which uses as you probably guessed,
a linked list to implement
the functionality of the list.
Now I'm taking some
liberties with this diagram.
The inheritance hierarchy doesn't
exactly look like this in Java.
But it's close enough.
Basically, the ArrayList and
the LinkedList are both data structures
that implement that list implementation.
So, let's first look at the ArrayList.
As I mentioned, we've got an array
underlying that structure.
And you know about an array,
it's just a sequence of elements,
all look at contiguously in memory and
each position has an index, so
you can go directly to any
particular location in that array.
So if I wanna get the element
at index position 2,
I can just go directly to the element at
index position 2 and I can see there's 15,
and that's instantly,
you can just do that in constant time.
However, I wanna ask you a question.
Let's say, as part of a list interface,
it says, I can add an element
at the beginning of the list.
So, let's say I wanna add a new
element to the beginning of the list.
In other words, at index position zero.
The question I have for you is,
how long is that going to take
relative to the number of elements
that are already in that list?
Okay, so
this is actually going to take order and
time to insert that
element at the beginning.
And the reason for that is that,
I can't just drop in the element
in the index position zero.
If I try to put an element in the index
position 0, I'll overwrite the 42.
So before I can put an element
in the index position 0,
I need to move the 42 to position 1.
But to move the 42 to position one,
I need to move the 95 to position two.
And so on and so forth.
So I basically need to move every
single element out of the way,
all the way down the list, before I
can put an element at position zero.
The problem is, there's no way for me to
expand my array to like negative one and
negative two.
It doesn't work that way.
I'm stuck at index position zero.
So its gonna take relatively long time
to put an element at the beginning
of the array.
So if I have a task that involves
constantly putting elements
in the beginning of my list.
An ArrayList might not be my best choice.
So, in other words, the Abstra data
type here is specifying behavior, so
the ArrayList is fulfilling
all the behavior, but
it doesn't specify any
bounds on efficiency, so
the ArrayList is not very efficient for
this particular task.
Let's look at a data structure
that's more efficient for
inserting elements at the beginning, or
arbitrarily anywhere in the middle
of the list, called the Linked List.
So here's a picture of
my new data structure.
And what you see here is the data
organized into these boxes called nodes.
So I have three nodes in my Linked List,
storing the elements 42, 55, and 23.
And inside each node,
I have the following fields.
I have some data,
that's stored inside the node.
And then,
these nodes aren't necessarily arranged.
Anywhere near each other in memory.
So, how to link them together somehow?
So, each node also has a reference
to the next node in the list, and
a reference to the previous
node in the list.
Now, in order to know where this whole
list is, I need to store a reference to
the head of the list or in other words,
the first node in the list.
And, typically, in what's called a Doubly
Linked List, because I have two pointers,
one to the next and one to the previous,
I also store a pointer to the tail of
the list, the last node in the list.
So in this way, I still got my elements
arranged in a particular order, but
instead of being contiguous in memory,
these nodes could be scattered all over
the place and they're linked together.
I have direct access to the first node in
the list, and the last node in the list.
But if I want any of the nodes
in the middle of the list,
I have to follow those pointers through
the list to get access to them.
So it's a little bit
different from an array.
Now what I've shown you here
is a Doubly Linked List.
You'll also hear people talk
about a Singly Linked List.
A Singly Linked List is very similar,
only instead of having a next pointer and
a previous pointer, the nodes only have
a data field and a next pointer but
no previous pointer.
And typically,
in a Singly Linked List, you only store
a pointer into the head of the list.
These are pretty much the same, sometimes,
somethings are slightly
harder to implement.
Some functionality is slightly
harder to implement with the singly
linked list than with a doubly linked
list, but you can pretty much do all of
the same stuff you can do with a singly
linked list and doubly linked list.
We're going to be focusing on the doubly
linked list, but we will ask you some
concept questions about singly
linked list, and their performance
in the end of module quiz, so make sure
you kind of know what they're about.
So let's go back to that
doubly LinkedList and look at,
in more detail, how we're going
to implement this data structure.
This data structure's
already built into Java.
So in general, you wouldn't need to
implement it, but we are going to ask you
to implement it as part of a programming
assignment, just so that you get
a really good sense of how this data
structure works and what it's all about.
So you'll be implementing functionality
that's already built into Java but
that's okay.
It's kind of a rite of passage
to implement a LinkedList,
as part of your computer
science education.
So to implement a LinkedList,
you're going to need to
implement two different classes.
So the first class you'll need to
implement is called ListNode, and
that stores the data in one particular
node in the list, as well as
the pointers to the next node in the list
and the previous node in the list.
So I want you to stop for
just a minute, and
think about the types of that
field next and that field prev.
What is going to be the type
that you wanna use for
those two fields in the ListNode class?
All right.
We'll get back to that when we actually
start writing Java code, but for
now let's talk about the other class
that you'll need to implement.
This other class is the class that
represents the LinkedList itself,
we'll call it MyLinkedList,
because LinkedList is already taken.
It's already built into Java.
And what my list is going to store is,
some overall properties of the list,
perhaps its size.
But most importantly,
a reference to the first node in the list.
And the last node in the list.
So it's gonna store those head and
tail pointers,
to give you access to
the whole list itself.
But it's the node class that really
comprises the structure of the list
itself.
So this diagram now is just
a slightly more detailed diagram of
what you'll actually be implementing in
Java, showing you all of the fields and
their values for this particular example
that has three nodes in the list.
I'm going to use it to add one more
subtlety to our LinkedList implementation.
So those are the ListNode objects.
Here's the MyLinkedList object.
And I'm now gonna talk about a slight
variation on this implementation.
So what we've been doing so far,
is we've been linking the head and
the tail references directly to to
ListNode objects that store data.
So 42 and 23 are the head and the tail,
respectively, in our LinkedList, and
they actually store real pieces of data.
So those pieces of data
are actually in the list.
But sometimes that can
be kind of problematic.
Because you might accidentally
run off the end of a list or
accidentally run off the beginning of
the list, when you're traversing the list.
So it's handy to introduce these
things called sentinel or dummy nodes.
So what are sentinel or dummy nodes?
Basically, what we're gonna do is,
we're is we're gonna take
the nodes that store data.
Shift them over slightly,
then we're gonna insert these dummy nodes
at the beginning and
at the end of the list.
These dummy nodes don't store any data.
They're always gonna be there,
even when the list is empty.
And they're going to be pointed
to by the head pointer and
the tail pointer in the list.
So they're essentially just buffers,
that keep you from running off one end or
the other of the list.
They make implementation of the LinkedList
functionality, slightly easier.
Do you need them?
No, you don't need them.
You can implement LinkedList perfectly
well, without these sentinel nodes.
But we're gonna use them in our
implementation because like I said,
they make this implementation
slightly easier.
All right.
So
that's kind of an overview of where
we're going with our implementation.
These are just pictures showing
you the Java classes that we
are going to implement.
But let me now return to some
of these efficiency questions,
that I asked you at the beginning.
Let's go back to our
ArrayList implementation.
So the question I have for you now is, if
I want to get an element at a particular
index in my list, how long is that going
to take in the ArrayList implementation?
All right good.
So, hopefully you now
understand why it's order 1.
Because these elements in the array
are organized contiguously in memory, and
we can just go directly to any
index in the array that we want to.
That's one of the main benefits of arrays.
Let me ask you, now, the same question for
a LinkedList implementation
of the List interface.
It may seem a little strange, but
LinkedList can actually associate indices
with the elements in the list,
and that's up to you,
the designer of the LinkedList
class to do that association and
you'll be doing that in your
implementation of your LinkedList.
And the question I have for you is, if we
associate the index 0 with 42, the first
element in the list, 1 with 55, and 2 with
23, how long does it take me to access
an arbitrary element in my LInkedList
implementation, in the worst case?
All right, so it's order n.
It's much slower than an ArrayList.
Because we only have access to the head
of the list and the tail of the list.
So we can actually do it in n over two,
in the worst case.
But of course, you know,
that's just order n.
So, we saw an example where
ArrayList were worse,
when we were constantly inserting
at the beginning of the list.
We don't have that problem in LinkedList,
because we can just put elements at
the head in constant time, but if we wanna
access an arbitrary location on the list,
that's relatively slow using a LinkedList.
So the underlying implementation is gonna
determine the speed of these operations.
And it's all about trade offs.
Choosing your data structure, to do your
implementation is gonna depend on what
operations you're gonna need to
use with that data container.