[MUSIC]
Why would you want to use
a list rather than an array?
The big advantage of
an array is random access.
You can look at any element of
the array in the same amount of time.
So reading an array is constant time.
It's o over one.
In a list,
you have to walk down the list step by
step to get to the element you want.
So reading in a list is linear time.
It's o of n.
On the other hand, inserting or
deleting an item in a list, just requires
fiddling some object references.
So, it's constant time.
But inserting or deleting into an array
usually means you have to copy all
of the following items in the array.
Sometimes you have to copy the whole array
if you don't have enough space in memory
so that's o of n.
In general, arrays are faster to read,
and lists are faster to write.
So you have to pick your data
structure carefully depending on what
algorithm you're planning
on using with it.
For example, there was a time
when I needed to do a merge sort
on a collection of very large objects.
Merging two arrays means
allocating a third array
as big as the original two combined,
and then copying each object into it.
So it's really slow.
Merging two lists means
walking down the two lists and
just fiddling the references as you go.
And when you're done
you have one big list.
So that's really fast.
In this case the algorithmic
complexity is the same.
They're both n log n, like any merge sort.
But in practice, the difference in
performance was something like 10 or
20 times, because copying
the objects took such a long time.
So using a list was a big win.