So we're working towards our
implementation of our link list.
And in this video, we're gonna talk about
a couple of concepts that are gonna
be really handy for the implementation.
They're not specific for link lists in
particular, they're more general concepts
in Java, but you're going to use them
in your link list implementation and
they're the ideas of generics and
exceptions.
So going back to our diagram,
we had these two different
classes that we had to implement.
The ListNode class and
the MyLinkedList class.
The ListNode class is really the backbone
of that link list structure,
while the MyLinkedList class provided us
access to that backbone structure via
the head and the tail nodes and
stored the size of the list in general.
So let's start by looking at
the implementation at that ListNode class.
So here's a ListNode and
we can make it just class.
It's not gonna be public or private, it's
going to be sort of package level, because
we're designing this class specifically
to be used with our MyLinkedList class.
This is not really a public class in that
the world shouldn't be able to use it.
We'll just need to be able to access it
within the package that we're working in,
so we just declare it class
rather than public or private.
It has three data members.
It has the pointers to the next and
the previous nodes.
And again, going back to that quiz,
that in video quiz from the last video,
you know now that those should be
pointers to ListNode objects and
it also stores data inside that node.
But at this point,
you might be seeing that E and
be wondering what in the world
is this E all about?
I don't know of a type called E,
that's what we're gonna talk about next.
What this E stands for is?
It's called a type parameter.
So this list class, this ListNode
class works with a parameterized type.
Meaning that type can be passed in where
we create one of these ListNodes and
what it allows us to do is it allows us
to make our list structure be generic.
In other words, it can hold any
kind of data we want it to hold.
You've probably worked
with generics before,
because you've worked
with ArrayList in Java.
You know that they take as
an argument to the constructor and
of the type, some type of thing
that the ArrayList is gonna store.
Now you're gonna see how you can
implement classes that make use
of the type parameters, so they can accept
a type when that class is created and
here's how you do it.
On the first line, you put that parameter,
which is typically a single capital letter
like E or T in those angle brackets.
And then any time you
wanna refer to that type,
you just use it throughout
your class declaration.
So let me give you an example of
how to create a class using these
parametrized types.
Here's an example of a very simple class.
It simulates a collection of elements
only when you add elements in,
it can only give you back the most
recent thing that you added.
It's called RememberLast.
It can be instantiated to take any kind
of element through that type parameter
called T.
So when I instantiate this class
as you'll see in a moment,
I'll have to pass in a type and that
type goes in for the type parameter T.
Anywhere I want to refer to the type
of things that's stored inside this,
RememberLast object,
I just use the capital letter T and
that will stand in for the type.
It's just like any other
sort of parameter.
It's like a variable, but for a type.
So what you can see here is
that down in the add method,
you can see that the parameters
of the add method is of type T.
It returns a type T and
inside that method,
I created a local variable of type T.
All of that is just fine.
It's just a parameter for
a particular type and
that type will get a value
when I instantiate this class.
We instantiate the class just like
you'd instantiate any other generic
class like ArrayList,
which you've worked with before
by putting the actual type that
you wanna use in angled brackets.
So I can create a member of object type
integer, which can store integers or
one of type string,
which can store strings or
any other kind of object
that I want to instantiate.
It has to be an object type though,
I can't instantiate a generic
class with primitive types.
But that's okay,
because as you can see in this example,
if I instantiate it with the integer
class, Java has this autoboxing
functionality of integers, so I can just
pass in little ints like that three.
Java will autobox it into an integer
to store it in my generic class.
So that's the example of
how to use generics and
you'll be using these parameterized types
in your linked list implementation.
Now let's look at ways
to handle bad input.
Let's say that I want my RememberLast
class not to remember null elements,
so I don't wanna be able to
add null elements to my class.
And my question for
you is what should happen if my input
to the add method happens to be null?
I'll need an if statement to check for
it, but
what should I do if I discover that,
that parameter is null?
Let's consider the options
that I gave you.
The first option that I gave
was to return negative 1,
like a flag to indicate
that this was bad input.
Now that's a nice thought.
Sometimes, it is appropriate to return
sort of a sentinel value to indicate that
something went wrong in the method.
But in this case, it's not going to
work and the main reason it's not
going to work is because this method
is declared to return type T.
Type T may not be an int and so
we can't just go ahead and return an int,
it has to return something of type T.
Now you might think, okay, well,
maybe I'll return null, but
there's something kind of unsatisfying
about just returning normally
when this input was so bad that we want
to kind of just not allow it at all.
So what we're going to do instead is we're
going to throw an exception to indicate
that something went wrong and
we don't know how to handle it.
This is Java's mechanism of breaking
the regular flow of the code to say, help,
help, I've got a problem.
I don't know how to deal with it.
Here, you deal with it.
So you can think of an exception as
a method literally panicking and saying,
help, I don't know what to do.
And taking that point of the code and
throwing it up to who ever
called the method and saying,
you deal with this, I can't.
So in this case, we're throwing a type of
exception called a NullPointerException.
Saying that we got a null pointer,
we don't know what to do with it,
then the method that called this method
is going to have to deal with it somehow.
Sometimes code methods,
like this one would declare that they
throw exceptions and that has to be
the case when your exception is
something called a checked exception.
In this case, however,
a NullPointerException is
not a checked exception.
It's an unchecked exception.
So we don't have to declare in the method
header that this method could potentially
throw an exception, but
it's okay to do so, if you want to.
So you can go online to the Java
documentation to understand
which exceptions are checked,
which exceptions are unchecked.
But pretty much the common exceptions
like NullPointerException,
index out of bounds exception,
those are all unchecked exceptions.
Because it would be really annoying
to have to declare those everywhere,
cuz they might happen really
anywhere in your code.
So you're gonna be doing a lot of
exception throwing to handle bad input
when you implement your
LinkedList class and
now we pretty much have all the mechanisms
that we need to do that implementation.
We'll look at the Java code to start you
off on that implementation of your doubly
LinkedList in the next video.