All right, we've looked at quite a bit
of the linked list implementation, and
now it's time to take it all the way to
Java code, which is what you're going
to do in the first part of this
programming assignment in this module.
So by the end of this video,
you'll be able to implement
a doubly linked list in Java.
And if you don't quite get there we've got
some support videos and concept challenges
that will help you a little beyond
what I cover in this particular video.
So let's go back to our diagram.
You can see here the two classes
that we're going to implement.
The list node class and
the my linked list class.
So let's start by looking
at the ListNode class.
And we looked at some of the details
of this class in the last video,
the generics, how we're gonna
throw exceptions on bad input.
Let's dive in now to what
the class actually looks like.
It's actually a fairly simple class.
It's got three fields,
there's the previous reference,
the next reference, and the data field.
And then we've got a simple constructor
here that just sets the data field to
an argument that we pass
into the constructor.
Now, a couple things to
notice about this class.
The first one that might seem a little
weird, or a little uncomfortable,
is that this is actually what's
called a recursive class.
It's a recursive definition.
What that means is that we're using
references of the class itself
inside the class we're defining.
So we're defining the ListNode class, and
inside that ListNode class, we have
two references to ListNode objects.
Now this might seem a little weird.
Like how can we use a class when
we're not even done defining it, but
this is what recursion is all about.
We're not gonna talk too
much about recursion.
Mia will talk about it a little bit in
the next module when she talks about merge
sort, but just be comfortable with
the idea that this is totally okay.
Because by the time Java actually
creates any of these ListNode objects,
the class definition will be finished,
and so it'll be totally okay to do this.
Feels weird, but it's totally okay.
The next thing I wanna point out is that
we're using this generic type parameter
E to indicate the type of the thing
that the list node stores.
Notice that we've got it in
the type of the previous and
next pointers, but
it doesn't appear here in the constructor.
And that's just the way you
define generic classes,
you don't need to put the type
parameter In the constructor.
And if you do,
if you accidentally forget and
put it there ,you're gonna get
a really weird compile error.
So it's not supposed to be there.
So that's basically it.
This is our entire list node class we've
got the forward, the previous pointer,
the next pointer, the data that we're
trying to store and the constructor which
sets the data element to be whatever
we pass in to the constructor.
One thing to note about this
is that the constructor will
by default set the previous and
next pointers to null.
So we don't have to do that explicitly,
though we could if we wanted to.
So with that under our belt,
let's go ahead and
look at how we define
the my linked list class.
This is gonna be the class that
actually does all the operations on
the linked list.
So what we need first is our data fields,
and
looking at that diagram you can see that
there's going to be three data fields.
There's the head pointer, the tail
pointer, and the size of the length list.
So I've got a couple blanks
in my Java code there, and
I want you to tell me what are the types
that should go in those blanks for
the head pointer and the tail pointer.
Okay, hopefully you figured that out
that they should be ListNodes, and
they should be ListNode of type E.
So the same type of data we wanna store in
the LinkList has to be the type of data
that we store in each individual node, and
that makes sense,
because the nodes actually are the list.
So now we've got our data fields set up.
Let's look at the constructor.
What we want the constructor
to do is create an empty list
as you can see in this diagram here.
An empty list is not
actually devoid of nodes.
We still need those sentinel head and
tail nodes.
So the constructor is going to have to
create those two nodes that you see in
the diagram.
So here's our first attempt
at writing this constructor.
We're gonna set the size
of the list to zero.
There are no elements in it.
And then we'll create a new node for the
head and create a new node for the tail.
And link the member variable head
to that first node we created, and
link the member variable tail to
the the second node that we create.
So now my question for
you is, is this code correct?
Does this correctly set up this empty
link list, as you see in the diagram?
You found out that the answer is no, it
doesn't correctly set up this link list.
Why not?
Well it's missing the links that will
link together this dummy head node
to the dummy tail node, and
those links are shown there in red.
Remember, the ListNode constructor
just sets the previous and
next pointers to null.
So, when we first create those nodes,
those previous and
next pointers in both the nodes are null,
they don't point to each other.
So, we need to explicitly set the next
pointer of the head node to point
to the tail, and the previous pointer
of the tail node to point to the head.
And we can do that using
these two lines of code here.
So we say head.next, which is that
next pointer in the head node,
is going to get the value of
the reference to the tail node.
And tail.prev is going to get the value
of the reference to the head node.
Then our linked list, our empty linked
list, we correctly set up those head and
tail dummy nodes will be
properly linked together.
All right, so now you've really got
all you need to go ahead and dive in,
and do your first part of your homework
assignment which is to implement
the methods size, get, set, add, and
remove in the MyLinkedList class.
So if you're feeling ready,
we've got a concept challenge for
you just to really solidify
your understanding, and
then feel free to dive into
that programming assignment,
but I'll warn you that implementing these
linked list methods is pretty tricky.
So if you are having any doubts,
or you're at all uncomfortable, or
you try to start implementing these
methods, and find yourself getting stuck.
We've got a support video for you that's
gonna walk you through in a little bit
more detail some of the subtleties of
implementing these linkless methods.
So good luck and have fun.