So you've been hearing from
Christine about linked lists.
And as a data structure, it's not
such a complicated data structure.
It's just got these nodes that
are linked together one after the other.
But it turns out that implementing
linked lists is really quite tricky.
And so
this concept challenge that we have for
you will help you think through some
of the details of the implementation,
so you're ready to do it when you
get your programming assignment.
So as you know, with a concept challenge,
we'll be posing a question and
you'll pause and think through
the answer and solve it yourself.
Then you have the opportunity to discuss
your solution with people around you or
in the discussion forums.
We'll show you some UC San Diego learners
thinking through the same ideas.
You'll answer the question again.
Hopefully with a little bit more
confidence behind your answer now.
And then confirm your understanding
as we come together and
walk through the solution.
So let's get started
setting off the problem.
In this problem,
we're going to tweak the data structure
that Christine talked about a little bit.
We'll be implementing
a singly linked list.
In the core videos, the linked list data
structure that you saw was doubly linked.
And we're modifying just a little bit so
we have a cleaner example for
this concept challenge, and also so
that we don't take all the fun out of
the implementation when you go ahead and
do the programming assignment.
So just to point out the differences
in the singly linked list,
we only have a sentinel object
at the head of the list.
And we don't have a tail sentinel.
And then when we think about what's
contained inside each of the object,
we have next references,
we don't have previous references.
All right, so we have a head object and
then we point forward
choosing next pointers.
So this is our abstract representation
of the singly linked list.
And what this concept challenge really
is about is going from the code to these
pictures of the nodes linked together and
seeing how the code
relates to those objects.
So the code that we've written is for
defining a class SSLNode, which is
a single node in a singly linked list.
And in this particular implementation,
we're gonna have three different
constructors that can be
used to create a node.
And what I'd like you to think
about is what happens when
we use these constructors to create some
nodes and try to link them together.
>> Hi, my name is Paul
>> I'm Nancy.
>> My name is Raymond.
>> So I think we can eliminate
sort of E as an answer choice.
>> Can probably also eliminate D,
which is also
saying that all the nodes
are individually assigned and
they're not actually
pointing to anything else.
I think after you add more nodes
they actually point to something.
So I don't think D should be the answer.
>> Yeah.
I think Nancy is definitely correct, and
I'm seeing her theory
also applies to layer C,
cuz it also does not has the next
reference to node 1 from node 2.
So I mean just for letter a,
I mean it's obviously
incorrect that the only
reference has two values.
The next reference of node 0
has one reference to node 1,
another reference to node 2, but
yeah, do you think it's correct?
>> Well just by looking at
the constructors, we can see that
you can't have two references
coming out of the same node.
So I think we can
eliminate that answer also.
>> So let's think through what the
learners talked about in their discussion
and walk through the solution by
drawing the diagram one line at a time.
And so we start off our diagram
by thinking about what happens
when we declare the variable n0.
It's of type SLLNode and
remember that those
angle brackets say that our nodes
data will be of type integer.
Now, when we wanna create the object
we use the new operator and
we say we're creating an object when
we're using the No-arg constructor.
So with the No-arg constructor,
we're saying that the default values for
our instance variables are null.
And so in our memory model, we wanna draw
our object that's being pointed to by n0,
and we fill in those instance
variables with null.
That's all we have to do for
this first line.
Now we go ahead to our second line,
where we're declaring a new variable, n1.
And notice that the constructor that
we're using the build the object
that's going to be pointed to
by n1 now has some arguments.
And so we're going to include
those in our memory model.
We're going to include an argument for
n0, which is the previous node.
Now, the first line of
the two argument constructor
calls the one argument constructor.
All right, so
we're gonna follow through this carefully.
The first thing we need to do
is call the constructor for
an SLL node with input the data.
And the data was that argument one,
which is the integer that we want to be
stored in our object, the node object.
And so the first thing that the object
that's being created right now does is,
it fills in the data value 1, for
the instance variable of this object.
Now notice that as we're constructing
this object we also get a variable,
this, that's pointing to the object
that's being constructed.
And that's gonna be useful for tracing
through the execution as we go ahead and
go to the next line.
Now these next two lines of code
are the trickiest part of the constructor.
And so we're gonna go through
them in a fair amount of detail.
What we're doing here is we want to
connect the objects that we've created,
and so we need to move some arrows around,
we need to move some references around,
and so it's a little bit tricky.
So in the first part, what we're going
to do is we're going to set the value of
this current object's next object or
next node.
And the way that we wanna do
that is we wanna read off what
the previous object pointed to before.
And so we look at the value
that's stored in prevNode.next.
And so we follow the area, we see that
we have a box in our memory model for
prevNode and we follow that to
look at what's its next value.
And that's null and so
we need to copy that over to this.next.
And so we follow the arrow for this,
go into the box for next and so
we've copied over null.
But now what we'd like to do
is say the previous object,
the previous node,
it used to point somewhere, but
now we wanna point it to us, because we
want to link the previous node to us.
And so we need to update
the value of prevNode.next with
the current object that we're building.
And so that means we wanna update it with
the arrow that's being pointed to by this,
namely the object that
we're currently building.
All right, we did it.
Now we've got yet
another object to create.
So let's move our work up above and
think about what happens
when we execute the constructor
SLLNode on new input parameters and
we're going to point to the newly
created object with the variable n2.
All right, so as before, we start off
by using the one argument constructor
to build an object of type SLLNode and
fill in the data field in that object.
And then, we do the tricky
part with the arrows, and so
walking through it we look up
what the prevNodes next value is.
And notice that in this call for
the constructor, we're using n0 or
the object pointed to by n0 as the same
object as pointed to by prevNode.
And so when we read off prevNode.next,
we need that yellow box up above.
And what we wanna do is copy the arrow
that was in there to be the new
value of this .next, all right.
And so now this.next is going to
point to the object that's pointed
to by n1 as well.
All right, so what we've done there,
is we've said that the next value
after the object that we're creating
is what used to be the next value
after the prevNode's object.
And now what we're going to do is say
the prevNode should point to me to
the new object.
And so what I need to do is say
update the value of prevNode.next
with a pointer to the object
that I'm building.
And so that variable prevNode.next now
points to the object that I just built,
namely the point that object
that was pointed to by this.
All right, so we've gone through
all of the lines in the main
method and now let's clean up our
picture just a little bit and
see what it would look like with
the abstract representation that we had.
Okay, so
that's a little bit easier to follow.
And so let's pick out the elements of the
linked list that we have in this picture.
So the head of the list is
that object pointed to by n0.
Also notice that it's
a sentinel object over here.
Even though it's a linked list node,
it's got null data.
So it doesn't really contain any
important information that's going to be
part of our list.
It doesn't store any data
that's used in our list but
it tells us where to start, so
our sentinel node is that n0.
The first node that has real data is n2,
so the node after the sentinel node,
and then notice that n2 then points to n1.
Now I'm using n2 and n1 as shorthands for
the objects pointed to by, but
basically what we see is we have a linked
list that starts with a sentinel node.
And then goes to a node that stores 2,
and then goes to a node that stores 1.
And that is our list.
So in the next concept challenge,
we'll take this concept just a little
bit further, and see if we really
understand those two lines of code that
played with the arrows, and make sure that
the implementation is perfectly clear.