[NOISE] So, now we're ready for
a second concept challenge.
And in the previous one, remember how we
talked about how tricky it was to get
the arrows right,
to get the references right.
And so we're really gonna hammer home that
point, with a second concept challenge.
And so, as usual, you're going to pause
and try to solve the problem yourself.
Then discuss you solution, watch the UC
San Diego learners, discuss it as well,
then answer the question again and
confirm your understanding
when we come back together.
So, we're looking at really similar code
to what we talked about in the previous
concept challenge but
we're just swapping two lines, okay?
The two lines that gave us
the most trouble before.
And so let's just see what
happens if we switch the order.
And what I'd like you to think about
is what does the list of notes that
we create in that main method look like
if we've done this like little swap,
this just tiny, tiny little swap,
and then run the code.
>> Hi, I'm Paul.
>> I'm Nancy.
>> I'm Millie.
Okay, so if we look at the last
two lines of the code,
we noticed that the order
of them has switched,
and then I think by noticing that point
we can firstly eliminate answer A.
Because if we look at
the last line of function,
we noticed that it
connects node n0 with n2,
which makes the next pointer of n0
should be pointing to n2 instead of n1.
And we noticed that answer A is the only
one that connects node n0 with n1,
which cannot be correct.
So, we can just eliminate this one.
And what else can we do?
>> Well, I think we can also,
like in the previous question,
we can also eliminate
the null pointer exception.
Since if you look at the constructors
we do notice that after you add
more nodes you're actually
pointing to something, so
it's not actually referencing a null data.
On the very last line of
the of the last constructor,
I was kinda confused because it seemed
that the node was pointing to itself.
And I'm not actually sure
if it's allowed to do that.
But, that's what it seemed
like it was doing so
I think answer D would be the best answer,
if it's actually possible.
>> I agree.
I think that's, it looks like that's
what's happening in the last two lines of
code, since the previous
node's next gets set to this.
>> All right, let's do a step-by-step
walk-through to really
get at what causes the problem when
we switch those two lines of code.
And let's think together about how
the list of nodes will be generated and
what it will look like at the end.
Now, the very first line of code, because
we used the no argument constructor
is exactly the same as in
the previous concept challenge, so
we're not going to go through the details,
but let's think about what happens when we
use the constructor with two
parameters to create a new object,
a new SSL, sorry, SLL node object,
this time pointed to by n1.
So when we call that two
argument constructor,
we now have prevNode pointing
to the object that is
pointed to by n0 that we created before,
and this points to the object
that's being constructed at
the moment by this constructor.
And so the first thing we do is we fill
in the data value with the number 1,
the integer 1, and now we go ahead and
think about the references and
the points, the arrows.
So, at this line of code,
what we'd like to do is assign
the value this to prevNode.next.
So we follow the arrows.
We look at prevNode.next and
its current value is null.
But what we'd like to do is
set its new value to be this,
namely to point to the object
that we're building.
And now we're ready to go ahead and
assign prevNode.next's value to
also be the value of this.next.
So that means that when
we look at this .next,
it should get a new value,
whatever value prevNode.next had.
And so that means copying that arrow into
also being the arrow
that's within this .next.
And so notice that both prevNode.next and
this .next are now going to point to
the object that's being constructed.
Okay.
That's a little bit different from
before and it might not be what we want.
So let's just keep with
it a little bit more and
see what happens with
the next node as well.
We now call the two argument constructor
and build a new object of type SLLNode.
We fill in the data, so
we've got the integer 2 now and
now we're ready to play with the reference
next so the variable next and
what we'd like to do is
set prevNode.next to this.
Now prevNode, just as before,
is the object pointed to by n0, and
we'd like to update it's value to point to
the current object that we're building.
And so that means that instead of the
arrow that we had to the object pointed to
by n1, we now point to the object
that's being created to
that's also being pointed to by n2.
And now we'd like to update the current
object's next value to prevNode.next.
But that means, well, we'd need to copy
the value that we just did because we just
updated prevNode.next and so
we'd look at that arrow that
points to the current object.
And we copy it into this .next as well.
So, the picture of the three
nodes that we've created,
well it starts the same as before,
we still have a head of the list,
we've got a sentinel node,
a node that has its data being null.
But now, what it points to or
what it links to is the object
that's pointed to by n2.
But notice what happened to
the object that's pointed to by n1,
it's all lonely over there, it's not
linked to the other two nodes at all.
And so what we have are three nodes that
don't really form a linked list anymore,
and so by swapping just those two lines of
code, we've broken our implementation and
we no longer get a linked list.
So the point of this little exercise
was just to caution you about
the care that you need to take when you're
implementing linked list data structures.
And especially when you're thinking
about dealing with those references and
being really careful about the order
in which we copy the references around.
And not losing any of the information and
any of the links that we've already built.
So now you're ready to implement
your own doubly linked list
when you go ahead into the project.