[MUSIC]
When I first started computer science,
I was cruising the first few months
because the practice that I did
was just taking a function and
just giving it what it needed.
Just giving it the right
answer straight on.
And I didn't think too much
about the data structure.
I didn't know anything about
data structures back then.
And then I got into data structures,
and that was when my whole happy CS
world turned upside down and
I was struggling with it.
I pulled so many all-nighters
trying to finish projects that
just involved data structures,
just randomly implementing them.
And I was really frustrated, and
really wondering if CS was
something I would like to continue.
Or if that was my route, or
if I was even fit for it.
But, then I got involved
into this project that
needed to implement Dijkstra's algorithm.
And it was to determine the shortest
path from one place to another.
And then, that's when I realized,
that data structures are like
paintbrushes and paint.
And, your computer is like the canvas.
And with those data structures,
you can create masterpieces.
And the moral of the story
is that in computer science,
if you come across anything really
difficult or really hard, in the end,
they're usually the things that help you
the most, they're usually the things that
help you understand the beauty
behind computer science.