Now, you're going to write some programs
and analyze web server log files.
Most major web servers log
each access to a file,
which records who made the request,
when the request was made, what their
request was, and how the server responded.
So why would you want to
analyze web server logs?
A web sever's log file lets
you understand a lot about
how your website is being used.
You might want to know,
how many people are visiting your site?
Is it popular or not?
If you have many different pages, are they
all getting traffic or only a few?
Understanding how your site is being
used is particularly important
if you're trying to make money off of it.
Popular pages bring in revenue,
while pages that nobody looks at
are not helping your business.
The log file can also be
useful in diagnosing problems,
as it will tell you when your
server is experiencing errors.
If one of the pages isn't getting
traffic because a link to it is broken,
you want to know, so you can fix it.
In the rest of this lesson,
you're going to work on code to
read the contents of a log file.
Being able to read the contents of a log
file will set you up to solve a variety of
problems, such as figuring out how many
different visitors have come to a website
or how many times each
visitor has visited the site.