Welcome back.
Now that you know the importance
of web server logs, it's time for
you to start thinking about
writing code that deals with them.
The first thing you're going to
want to do is to be able to rename
a web server log file and represent
the information in it in Java objects.
To do this,
you need to think about two things.
The first is what does all of the
information in the web server log mean?
And the second is how do you
represent it in a Java class?
Here, you can see one entry
from a web server log file.
It has a lot of information and it's not
readily apparent what each piece means.
To find out what it means,
you would want to read documentation
about this web server.
This particular data came from the web
server log for an Apache 2.4 web server.
So to find out more,
you could go to Google and search for
Apache 2.4 web server log file format.
If you do that,
you'll end up with a lot of hits.
And this first one here, gives you
a link to the Apache documentation site.
If you scroll down a bit, you'll find
the information on the access log.
That is the log of accesses to the web
server, which is what this web log is and
you will see that it has information
about each of the pieces of this entry.
The first is the IP address, that is
the address of the device on the internet,
which made the web request
that is logged here.
The next two pieces are both dashes that
indicates they are missing information.
The first dash is for some information
about who made this request,
which you'll see the documentation
says is unreliable.
The users computer could
lie about who they are.
This second dash is for
the user name if they're logged in
with HTTPF authentication, if they typed
in a username and password on the website.
The next piece of information is the date
and time when the request was made.
Next, you have the request itself
including what type of request it was.
In this case, get, where they're
asking for a particular web page and
then what page they asked for.
Next is the status.
Here it says, 200,
which indicates success.
There are many other statuses,
which indicate success or failures.
You may be familiar with 404,
which is the very well-known status code
that indicates that the requested
page was not found.
Finally, is the number of bytes
that the server replied with.
How much data it sent back
to fulfill this request?
Now that you've read the documentation and
understand what each of these pieces of
information mean, it's time to think about
how to represent them in a java class.
The first thing you need to think about is
what type of information each of these is.
For the IP address,
you could use a string since you're
interested in just the text of that field.
Java does have a built-in class for IP
addresses, which would give us some more
features if we wanted to actually
connect to that address, for example.
But we don't need that functionality and
we don't need to worry about the
complexity that would introduce right now.
We don't need to represent
the two fields that we've omitted
that have no useful information.
We do, however,
want to represent the date.
You could use a string for that in which
case, you would just have its text or
you could use the built-in Java Date
class, which understands what dates and
times are and
how they relate to each other.
So you could check if one time
is before or after another time.
For the request,
you can just use a string.
And for the status and number of bytes,
those are both numbers, so
you can use an int.
Now that we've gotten through these types,
it's time to turn this
into some Java code.
Here you can see the start of
a Java class for a LogEntry,
we've declared a public class LogEntry and
written fields based on the types
that we just discussed.
You should now think, should each of
these fields be public or private?
Remember that if a field is public,
any piece of code can access it.
If a field is private, only code within
this particular class can access it.
In this particular case, it makes sense
to have each of these be private and
to design your class to be immutable.
Remember, from earlier when we learned
about strings that immutable means,
you cannot modify an object
once you create it.
So you're going to write this class, so
that each of these fields will be set in
its constructor, but can only be read.
To make anything able to read these
fields, you'll write a public getter or
accesser method such as these, which will
just return the value of that field, but
there will be no way to set the value
of the field once its constructed.
Speaking of constructing, you need to
write a constructor for this class.
There are two ways you could do it.
The first is to take in
this entire string and
then I have the constructor pull it apart
into each of these individual pieces and
fill in the fields or
instance variables of the class.
The other is to have the constructor take
each piece of information separately and
simply initialize
the fields of the object.
We're going to have you do the second one,
just making a constructor that looks like
this, which is going to fill in the fields
based on the information passed down
with each piece being passed separately.
Why would you do it this way?
Well, this gives you a little more
flexibility if you wanted to create one of
these objects from some other source
of information you could do so.
It turns out that pulling this line apart
is actually a little bit tricky, so
we're gonna give you the code for that.
It's a little bit ugly and we'll package
it up into a nice method for you, so
you can just use it to read the file.
Here is the final log entry class with
all of the things you just learned about.
You would use this to represent one of
these log entries as you work with it.
So your next task is going
to be to use this class,
the code we give you to split this
up into each separate piece and
put them together to make code that's
going to read the entire log file.