Hi, now that you've made your LogEntry
class, you need to parse the lines
of the web server log to be able to
create instances of the LogEntry class.
You'll do this by splitting the string
into the appropriate fields
to pass values to the constructor for
the LogEntry class.
You could accomplish this task with
many indexOf and substring calls.
Although this task is not algorithmically
hard, the code for it is very cumbersome.
For example, for
the time portion of this entry,
you would need to turn
the string in to a Date object.
The built in Java class from the Java.util
package which represents a date and time.
Even though both the date and time class,
as well as methods which parse strings,
are part of Java, the interface to
the Date class is complex, especially
since the date format in the server
logs is not the default format in Java.
For these reasons, we've provided code for
you which will take a string from the web
server logs, parse it into appropriate
fields, and return a log entry record.
To use this call WebLogParser.parseEntry
and pass the string you want to parse.
The method returns a LogEntry object.
With that in mind, its time for you to
starting the write the LogAnalyzer class.
For right now, you're gonna write code in
the constructor to initialize the object,
and then write the read file method.
In later lessons,
you'll write additional methods
that will perform that actually analysis
of the log file that you've read in.
The first thing you would do to fill
in the code for the constructor.
The constructor should initialize that
the record fields to an empty ArrayList.
You've created ArrayLists in the past so
what you need to accomplish
this task should be familiar.
The second thing you should do is
fill in code for the readFile method.
This method will determine the file
name to read from and then add log
entries to the records field to reflect
the information from the file you opened.
To accomplish this task,
you will want to make a FileResource for
the requested file.
You will then want to iterate
over the FileResource's lines.
And for each line, you will use
the WebLogParser.parseEntry method
to convert the line of
text into a LogEntry.
Then you'll add that LogEntry to the
records field, which as you may recall,
is an ArrayList.
When you've written a constructor and
the readFile method,
you'll want to test out your code.
We've provided a convenient method
called printAll, which will print
all the log entries you've stored
in the instance variable records.
Remember the .toString
method that we taught about?
System.out.println will make
use of that .toString method to
represent the log entry as a string.
Once all this works, it will be time to
start analyzing the data you've read in.
Happy coding.