In this lesson you learned
a bit about web server logs,
which can give you a lot of
information about your website.
You learned what is in them,
how those records are formatted,
as we looked at the Apache web
server documentation together.
And then you learned how
to make a LogEntry class
based on the information in that file.
As part of that,
you learned about toString,
which is an important Java concept,
as you will want to write a toString
method in many of the classes you create.
Finally, you wrote code
to read in the log file
using the parsing code that we provided.
Now, you are ready to write some code
to analyze the data you've read in.