[MUSIC]
All right,
as you know in this part of the project,
you'll be adding code to respond
to mouse clicks and mouse hovers.
So let's take a look at what you
need to do to make that happen.
So here's the project write up and
I'll walk you through it a little bit and
talk about the starter code.
So what you're gonna do is of course you
want your documentation pages open for
the unfoldingmaps javadoc and
the processing reference.
And the first thing to do is to just
find the starter code that's in module5.
And again,
we provide you with code that essentially
implements the module4 functionality.
Then you're actually going to, the first
thing you're going to do is you're going
to be changing the class hierarchy.
And so in order to do that,
do the step 2 here.
You're gonna modify
the header in CityMarker so
that it extends this new class called
CommonMarker instead of SimplePointMarker.
And then we're gonna ask you to draw the
UML diagram for the new class hierarchy.
And part of your reflection and
what we'll ask you about
is why we made those changes and what
changes we made to the class hierarchy.
So spend some time really understanding
the new code and a new class hierarchy.
And when you do this change,
you're going to get a compile error.
So right here you'll see
a compile error in CityMarker and
we ask you to figure out why that compile
error occurred and how you can fix it.
And we've got some hints here and
then a little description
of what's really going on.
All right so
then your ready to start coding.
And in order to add this interaction
you're going to be implementing
two methods in EarthquakeCityMap.
One is mouse moved and
the other is mouse clicked and
both of those have a little
bit of starter code in them.
And you'll be implementing
them to some degree.
So the first thing you're gonna do is
implement this selectifHover helper method
and that's called from
the mouseMoved() method.
So let's go over here to the starter code
to understand what's really going on here.
So in EarthquakeCityMap
that's where you'll find that
selectMarkerIfHover method.
So it's down here.
And as I mentioned it's called up
here from this mouseMoved() method.
And really the goal of selectMarkerIfHover
is to set the if selected to true on
that marker that's under the cursor, and
to only do it for one marker at a time.
So the goal of the selectMarkerIfHover is
to iterate through all the markers and
see if they are under the mouse cursor
at the moment that mouse X and mouse Y.
And if they are then for
the first one you find,
you will set that marker to be selected.
So how does that result in
displaying the title that you see
next to the marker when
you hover over a marker?
Well to understand that we need to go
over here to the ColumnMarker class and
look at its draw method.
So if we go down here to the draw method.
You can see that there is some
logic here that basically says
if that marker is selected,
then you're gonna show the title.
The showTitle is a method
you're going to write as well
to display that text next to the method.
So that's how this all comes together.
In EarthquakeCityMap we have this
mouseMoved() method that basically
clears the last selection and then finds
if another marker has been selected.
And again, just be careful to only ever
have one marker be selected at a time.
That's a little bit tricky.
There are some hints in
the project write-up.
So that's what you have to do to get
the hover functionality working.
Going back to the project description,
the next thing you'll wanna do is
to implement that showTitle method.
That's what, as we saw,
is going to actually be drawing
the text next to the earthquake marker.
And you will have to look into that
text method in the processing library.
Using the processing documentation that
you've seen in some of the support videos
to understand how to display
text next to each marker.
You'll just be using those
processing drawing methods.
All right, then once you have
your showTitle method working,
you should see your mouse actually
causing those titles to appear if
your selectMarkerIfHover method and
your showTitle method are both working.
So you'll wanna test that out.
The next piece is to implement
the mouseClicked method in
the EarthquakeCityMap so
that your EarthquakeMarkers and
your CityMarkers respond to clicks.
And you can read the text here about
what that's supposed to do, and
then there are some hints
about how to implement that.
But to show you where
this all is in the code,
we can go down right here
to the second TODO item.
And just look at where you're gonna put
your code that handles mouse clicks.
This is not a totally trivial method and
you'll want some helper methods
to keep mouse click from getting
too long or disorganized.
But essentially, you need to iterate
through the EarthquakeMarkers and
the CityMarkers,
see if any have been clicked.
And then if they have, you'll need to do
some additional iteration to hide what
markers that aren't supposed
to be displayed, or
to show the markers that are supposed
to be displayed at any given point.
Again, one thing to note
about the CommonMarker,
since all of these are CommonMarkers, is
that they have this property, getClicked.
But also because they inherit from
SimplePointMarker which inherits
from this abstract marker class
they have a hidden property.
So you can set them to be hidden or
not and
that's how you're actually
gonna do the hiding.
Because you'll note here in draw,
if this marker is not hidden,
then you're going to draw it but if it
is hidden, then it will not be drawn.
And that's something that's set
through the super classes, and
you can check out the documentation.
And we also give you some hints
here in the hints for step 7.
So that's it.
You have an option of adding
some additional functionality
to your responsiveness,
to your GUI if you like.
But other than that once you get through
step 7 you will finish the project
for this module.