[MUSIC]
All right, in this lesson we're
gonna learn some core algorithms for
searching for data.
Searching for data you probably
do every day, many times a day.
And so we're gonna focus on some of the
fundamentals of how to search for data and
how to do that quickly.
So by the end of this video,
you're going to be able to motivate
why we want to search for data.
As well as to be able to write
code to perform linear search, and
then we'll build on this
in subsequent videos.
So let's start off with
a motivating example.
Say I'm going on a trip, which I am.
I'm going on a trip and I wanna plan my
airline travel, and in order to do so,
if you've booked airline tickets online,
you probably know that those
airline ticket booking sites
use a three letter code for the airport
that you're trying to book from.
So I'm coming from my
hometown of San Diego and
I wanna figure out what is the three
letter code for the airport in San Diego.
So there's a lot of ways I
can find this information.
And probably one of the most popular ways
is I can go to my favorite search engine
like Google and
type in this query into Google and
Google will go off and
search the information that's on the web
to find me a page that will
hopefully answer my question.
Now, this is an example of search.
In fact an Internet search
is a fairly complex search.
So there's a lot going on here in
order to organize all the data and
return me results quickly.
Results that I find useful and
so on and so forth.
So this kind of search is a little
bit beyond the scope of this course.
But the idea is the same.
We have a big repository of data and
I wanna find some information
in that data in order to answer
some questions about it.
This is kind of fundamental to almost
everything that we do in Computer Science.
So, let's simplify the problem slightly.
Instead of searching the entire Internet,
I'm gonna take a subset of the data
on the Internet, a very small subset.
That I can find in a file
called airports.dat,
which is on the website,
whose url that you see here.
And, this file has information about,
almost, 7,000 different
airports around the world.
And it's represented in terms
of a number of different fields.
So each line in the file has a number
of different comma separated fields.
Those fields include a unique ID inside
this database, the name of the airport,
the name of the city that the airport is
located in, the name of the country, and
that three letter airport code.
And a bunch of other information
as well which you can find out by
going to that URL.
So I'm gonna be searching within
this lesson in only this data,
not on the whole Internet.
So, what I'm going to do is, I'm going
to read in all of this data into my Java
program, and then I'll search for
a particular city that I care about, in
order to find out some information about
its airport, like its three letter code.
So here's the first step that I
need in order to read in this data
into my program.
I need some way to represent this data.
So we know how to do that.
We know how to write classes and
create instances of those classes, so
let's do that.
Let's write a class called Airport.
And it's going to have a field for
each piece of information we wanna
represent about a particular airport.
In this case, we'll represent a city,
a country, and that three-letter code,
as well as whatever information we
want to keep about our airport.
Each of these fields is
going to be private.
As I mentioned, a rule of thumb is
to keep all of our data private, but
we'll provide getters, so we can access
each of those pieces of information.
They'll get set in the constructor when
I read in the data from this file.
And then I have access to all of
these pieces of information for
each airport that's stored in my program.
So let's imagine that I've done that.
I've written some code that reads in this
file that has all this information about
these airports into my
Java program by creating
one instance of this airport class for
each airport in that file.
I'm gonna simplify things a lot.
And I'm gonna imagine that my entire
file only had eight airports in it.
So I'll read those all into,
each into an individual airport object
which I'm going to store in an array.
So my array is going
to be called airports.
It's an array of references
to airport objects.
So one object for each airport.
And what's stored in the array again,
is a reference to this object which you
see depicted here in the blue boxes.
And those objects exist somewhere in your
computers memory, somewhere in the heap.
And again, what could store in the array
is the references to those objects.
But this diagram is a little bit too
complicated for my needs for this lesson.
So I'm gonna simplify things a little bit
by writing all of the information from
each object directly in the box for
the array itself.
So this is going to be my representation
of the data that I've now read
into my computers memory from
that big airports.dat file.
And again, there's a very simplified
version for the purpose of illustration.
So now, I've got all the data about all
my airports right into my array and now,
I can write a program to answer questions
about the airports in that array.
And in order to answer a question
about a particular city's airport,
I have to find that airport object first.
So, let's look at how to do that.
So let's say I'm looking for
information about the Beijing airport.
And I wanna find out what is the three
letter city code of that airport Beijing.
So, how am I gonna do this?
Well, first I need to find it.
One way I can do that is just basically by
starting at the beginning of my array and
looking at each element in my array,
one after the next until I come
across the airport I'm looking for.
Or I get to the end of my array and
I haven't found it.
And that's an algorithm
called Linear Search,
which we're going to look at right now.
The way it works, is I start at
the beginning of my array, so
I start at index position zero,
which is the fist index in my array.
And then I'm gonna look at
the element in that index.
And I'm gonna ask is this a match for
the thing that I'm looking for?
In this case I'll ask is the string to
find which is the name of the city I'm
trying to find,
equal to the city field in the objects
that's located in that array position?
And in this case I'll see that Montreal is
city in the object at position zero and
Beijing is the city I'm looking for,
those two strings are not the same, so
there's no match.
I'll go on to the next element in my
array by incrementing index by one, so
now I look at the element in position one,
is that a match?
Compare the cities, again I find
that's not a match, so I'll continue.
Here's the index position two.
Match?
Nope.
Still not a match.
Index position three.
Still not match.
Index position four.
Finally, I look index position four and
I see that its city is Beijing,
which exactly matches the city
that I'm looking for.
So now I've found the airport
object in question.
And I can use it to answer the question of
what is a three letter code for Beijing?
So I read that out of the entry and
I can return it to my user.
So this is a match and we're done.
That in a nutshell is
the algorithm called LinearSearch.
And here's how it looks
like in Pseudocode.
So in the beginning we initialize the
index variable to the start of our array,
and then we're gonna have a loop that
keeps going as long as we haven't found
what we're looking for,
in which case we'd just return it.
Or we get to the end of the array in which
case we conclude that the element is not
in our array.
So while our index is not equal
to the length of our array,
while it's less than
the length of our array.
We'll look at the element in
the particular position where index is
referencing, where index
says we should look,
see if the city in that element
matches the city we're trying to find.
If it does, we'll return the three-letter
code, thus breaking the loop and
breaking the whole method,
basically returning out of that method.
Otherwise we'll keep going by incrementing
our index variable by one and
going back to the top of the loop.
When the loop ends we can conclude that
the city we were looking for was not in
the array at all and we return some value
to indicate that we didn't find it.
Okay.
So now it's your turn.
This is an interactive piece of the video.
I want you to pause the video.
And I want you to get out either
a piece of paper and a pencil, or
better yet, just open up a clips and
go ahead and write the code for
LinearSearch before you unpause the video.
Once you unpause the video,
we'll go back over it.
But I really do want you to take a shot
at going back to the algorithm that
you just saw, going back to
the example and writing out this code.
See if you can do it.
I bet you can.