All right, welcome back.
I hope you had a good time writing
this program, writing this method.
And I'm now gonna write it out,
step by step on my tablet PC.
If you really think you've gotten no
problems, just go ahead and zoom ahead.
You can see my solution,
just check it against yours.
But I encourage you to also follow
me through the thought process,
as I write this code.
So thinking back to that algorithm,
the first thing that we need
to do is we need to declare
a new variable called index.
Which is going to be the variable
that steps us through the array.
So I'm gonna do that,
I'm gonna declare a new variable.
It's type integer, called index and
its initial value is 0.
So now I'm ready for my loop.
And my loop is gonna be a while loop.
And it's going to run as
long as that variable index
is less than the length of my array.
So airports.length, okay.
So now inside the loop, remember what we
wanna do is we wanna look at the Airport
object that's in the cell
indicated by that index variable.
So we're going to get that
Airport object out first and
store it in its own separate variable just
to make the code a little bit cleaner.
So I'll declare new variable Airport
a = airports at position index.
Now I'm ready to work with that Airport
object and I can compare the string that
I'm trying to find,
the name of the city I'm trying to find.
To the name of the Airport that's in that
object, pointed to by the variable a.
So I do that with an if statement, because
if they're equal, I wanna do something.
So if my toFind
equals a.getCity.
Now notice that I've used the .equals
method here instead of the == operator and
that's pretty important.
Because what .equals is saying to Java is,
I want to compare
the string representations in these two
objects by essentially their characters.
I wanna know, are they the same string?.
I don't care if their the exact same
object in memory, I just wanna know,
is it the same string of characters?
And the .equals method will do that.
On the other hand,
the == operator, that's just gonna
compare the references that are stored
in two particular variables.
And so that will only be true
if those are actually the same
literal object in Java's memory.
So in this case, and almost always
when you're working with objects,
the .equals method is the appropriate way
to compare those two different objects.
So if I find that the string that I'm
looking for is equal to the object's
City that's stored in a,
then I'm going to return the AirportCode.
So return a.getCode.
Otherwise, I need to keep looking.
So there's nothing really more to do
except to go on to the next location, so
I can say index++.
Notice I don't need
an else statement here,
because if the if statement was true,
then I just return out of the function and
there's nothing more to be done.
But if that if statement is not true,
then I increment my index and
I'll go back to the top of my
while loop and repeat the process.
Now if my while loop completes, that means
my index has gotten all the way to the end
of my array and I still haven't
found the city that I'm looking for.
So now I need to return some value that
indicates that the city is not there.
And in this case,
I'll just return the value null.
And that's appropriate, because my
method is suppose to return a string.
So null is a good value to indicate hey,
we couldn't find it.
It wasn't there.
So that's it.
That's it for the code.
I wanna leave you, oh, there's the code
a little bit more cleaned up for you.
But I do, after you're done sort of
looking at and digesting the code.
What I wanna leave you with
is a thought question.
Actually, two thought questions.
I wanna ask the question of,
if we're really unlucky.
So if we're looking for some airport and
it's very unluckily way at the end of the
list or it's not even in the list at all.
How many Airport objects are we
going to have to look at
to figure out either the AirportCode
of this particular airport.
Or to figure out that airport
is not in the list at all?
So try to think of how you would
answer that question in terms
of some number of airports in the list.
And then, the more important question is,
can we do better than that?
Is there a way to answer
this question faster?
And that's what we're
going to look at next.