[MUSIC]
All right.
In this video, we are going to improve
on that linear searching algorithm
that we looked at in the last video,
and we are going to talk about
an algorithm called binary search.
So by the end of this video, you will be
able to explain what binary search is.
You will be able to write code
to implement binary search.
And you'll also be able to explain
what conditions need to be true for
binary search,
as well as explain why binary search is so
much better than linear search.
All right, to motivate the need for
binary search, let's go back to
our linear search algorithm.
We were looking for airport objects
that had particular city names so
we could answer questions
about those airports,
like what are their three digit airport
codes, three letter airport codes.
And what we did was we started at the
beginning of our array at index position
zero and we just marched through
this array element by element,
until we either found the city we were
looking for or didn't find it, but reached
the end of the array, in which case we
concluded that the city wasn't there.
And it worked, but I asked you this
thought question at the end of the video.
I said, if we're very unlucky,
how many elements do we have to
look at in order to, either find the city
or conclude that it's not there?
And then the second part of that
thought question is, can we do better?
So, to answer this question, I'm going
to step over into the real world.
So, I'm gonna use a dictionary for
this example.
And this is a physical dictionary,
which some of you maybe have
never used in your lives.
But this is what it looks like.
It's an enormous book.
It has basically every word in,
in this case, the English language in it.
And I can find definitions of the word,
I can find their origins,
the spelling, so on and so forth.
And so if I was gonna find
a word in this dictionary,
here's an example of how I might use
linear search to find that word.
Let's say I'm looking for the word, shark.
So I open up my dictionary
to the beginning.
Let's see, okay.
Acrobatics, let's see.
All right, not on this page.
And over here, not here, not there.
Acupuncture, nope, still not there.
I'm looking, I'm looking,
I'm looking, I'm looking.
Are you getting bored yet?
I'm getting very bored.
I'm not gonna make you watch me page
through this dictionary page after page
to find the work shark.
It's way back here at the Ss.
This is gonna take a really long time.
But this is effectively what we
were doing with linear search.
We are starting the beginning, looking
all the way through in a row, our array.
So what's a better approach
to approach this problem?
Well, it's an intuitive parse that we all
use when we're opening a dictionary and
trying to find a particular word.
I don't open to the beginning,
because I know us is sort of in the middle
towards the end of the alphabet.
So I'm going to open to about sort
of halfway, maybe a little bit more.
And I found myself in the Rs.
Okay.
R S, S comes after R.
So I need to go a little bit further, so
I'll take another chunk of
the dictionary and flip it over.
Oh, I've gone way too far,
I'm now in the Ys.
So let me flip back a little bit, okay.
Now I find myself in the Ts,
keep going back.
Great, I'm in the Ss, S O,
I need to go back a little bit more.
So on and so forth until I
find the word I'm looking for.
And already, after only about three or
four flips, I'm much closer to shark.
The word I'm currently looking at is
shirt, Than I was when I started the As
and was just flipping through
one page after another.
So this is an example of
the binary search algorithm.
What I'm doing is is I'm starting with
my entire pool of data, in this case,
it's the dictionary, and
then I'm going to go half way and
I'm going to reassess where I am to see
if I've found the thing I'm looking at.
And if I haven't found
the thing I'm looking at,
I'm going to use some information to
decide whether I should go to the second
half or go back to the first half,
and then I just have a smaller
version of the same problem, where I'll
again flip the book open about halfway.
So notice each time I flip,
my pages are getting smaller and
smaller and smaller,
the number of pages that I flip.
And that's the exact same
intuition behind binary search.
So lets step back over now into the code,
so
we can figure out how to write
this algorithm on the computer.
So we're going to need to implement this
algorithm by taking our data in our array
and what we want to do is to
cut the list in half each time.
But if you look at the list
as it stands right now,
you'll notice a really important
difference between the data that's
in this list currently and the data
that we had over here in our dictionary.
So think about it for a second,
maybe pause the video,
see if you can identify the issue
that we have right now.
All right hopefully you saw it.
The list has to be sorted.
The reason that we can eliminate half the
data in the dictionary is that the list
of words is in sorted order, so if I'm
looking for a word that starts with S.
I know that nothing that starts with P or
before matters to me and
I can just get rid of it.
So the same has to be true in order to do
binary search of the data in an array.
It has to be sorted on the element
that you're looking for.
So in this case,
it's sorted now by city name.
And here's how the binary search
algorithm is going to work.
I'm going to start by identifying
the string I'm looking for.
Let's look for Beijing again.
Notice Beijing is now at the beginning,
towards the beginning of the list
because it starts with B.
What I want to do now,
is I want to keep track of what
range of the array is currently
active to be searched.
Versus the part of the array
that's kind of been ruled out.
So, I'll keep track of the active
range of the array with two variables.
A low index and a high index.
And these are just gonna indicate where in
my array I'm allowed to look for my data.
Outside of this range,
I've already eliminated all
the possible data outside of the range.
So my range starts with the whole array.
So, low starts at 0 and
high is length minus 1, in this case 7.
And now I want to go to
that middle element,
just like I did in the dictionary.
So I calculate the midpoint.
I calculate the midpoint by taking the low
plus the high and then dividing by 2.
In this case, it's 0 plus 7 divided by 2.
Now, you might be thinking okay,
the midpoint is 3.5.
But the problem is that there's
no position 3.5 in my array.
Luckily, we're doing
integer division here.
And so we don't need to worry
about decimal points or
anything like that because Java will
automatically truncate that 0.5 and
give me the value 3 as my middle position.
So (0 + 7) / 2 is 3,
and that'll be my mid.
Now I am going to look at the element
that's at that mid point .in
this case it's the element Essen,
representing the city Essen in Germany.
And I am going to compare it to
the string that I'm looking for.
I am going to say, does it match?
Because maybe I've found
the thing I am looking for.
In this case, no it doesn't match.
But instead of just giving up,
now I need to get some more
information out of this element.
Now I want to know which half
of my array can I discard?
Should I discard the lower half?
Or should I discard the greater half?
So I'm going to compare
Beijing to Essen and
see whether Beijing is smaller or
larger than Essen, and
I'm doing this alphabetically, so Beijing
comes before Essen in the alphabet.
So Beijing is alphabetically
smaller than Essen.
Which means that everything that's
larger than Essen in my array
couldn't possibly be the string I'm
looking for, so I can eliminate it.
And the way I eliminate it
is by adjusting my range
to no longer include those elements.
So I'm gonna move the high
point in my range
to be one less than that middle
element that I've just ruled out.
So this is what it looks like.
I will change my high to be mid- 1,
which in this case is 2,
and that effectively rules out
everything that's either 3 or greater.
So now I have another version
of the exact same problem.
I have a low value, which is still 0, and
a high value of my range, which is now 2.
So I only need to look in
this range of the array,
and I'll do it the exact
same way I did it before.
I calculate a mid value so (0 + 2)/2,
which is 1, and then I'll look at
the element that's at that position,
in which in this case it's Beijing.
I compare the city I'm looking for,
Beijing, to the city that I see.
Which is also Beijing.
And I see that I found a match.
So that's great.
I'm done.
I can just return that three letter
city code.
And you can see that this was a lot faster
than my algorithm before which had to look
through about five different
cities before it found Beijing.
Now I recognize that Beijing moved now,
so it's further towards the beginning.
But in general, this is going to be a lot
faster than our linear search algorithm,
and we'll look at just how much faster
a little bit later in this lesson.
So here's our algorithm in that
same pseudocode we used before to
look at the linear search algorithm.
We're going to now need to initialize
two variables, which are the low and
high end of our range.
And again we initialize low to be zero and
high to be the length of the array minus
one, which is the last
position in our array.
So we've got the whole array in our range.
Now we're gonna enter a loop.
And it's a little bit unclear yet
when our loop is gonna stop.
So let's leave that as a question mark for
the future.
That'll be for
you to think about in just a second.
But inside the loop here's
what we're gonna do.
We're gonna calculate that
midpoint of the array and
then look at the element that's
in that midpoint of the array.
If that element matches the city
that we're looking for,
then we're done we just return
that three letter city code.
Otherwise, if the city
that we're looking for
is alphabetically less than
the city element that we found,
we want to update our range so
that we're only looking at the small
half of the array by moving
high to be equal to mid- 1.
Otherwise, we know the city
that we're looking for
is in the larger half of the array.
In which case we update our low
value to be equal to mid + 1.
That's what the loop does.
Again, we don't quite know when it stops.
But if it stops, what that means is we
haven't found the thing we're looking for.
In which case we can
conclude it's not there, and
we'll just return that value that
indicates that it's not there.
For example, the value null.
So that's pretty much it and
the only thing that we have to figure
out is when do we stop that while loop.
This is a question I'm
going to give to you.
So I want you to spend some time thinking
about what should the while loop
condition be?
And there's gonna be a quiz that is
gonna ask you a bunch of choices and
you're gonna wanna select
the correct choice.
And in order to do that what I recommend
is that you work through on your own
several examples of cities
that aren't in this list.
So trace through that algorithm
using the loop that never ends, yet.
To figure out what the algorithm does and
figure out when it makes
sense to stop that loop.