[MUSIC]
So let's trace through an example of
a city that's not actually in this list
to see when we should
stop the while loop and
conclude that the city is not
actually in the list at all.
And the city I'm going to use is Istanbul.
So let's go ahead and run the algorithm
looking for that city, Istanbul.
I start with a low of zero, high of seven,
and that midpoint is three.
So I look in position three.
I see the city Essen, not Istanbul.
Istanbul comes alphabetically after Essen.
So I look in the greater half of the list,
by moving my low up to be mid plus one.
I'm gonna calculate a new mid value,
look in the middle of that list.
I see Montreal.
Montreal is not equal to Istanbul.
Istanbul is alphabetically
less than Montreal.
So I will again adjust
my range appropriately.
Now I am down to just one element.
I have a range that includes only one
element so high and low are the same.
But that's okay, that's no problem.
This is still a valid
element that we can look at.
This element is Lagos.
And it is not equal to Istanbul, so
I again conclude that I
need to move my range.
And in this case Istanbul is
alphabetically before Lagos, so
I'll change my high value to be one less
than mid, in this case making it three.
But now I'm kind of stuck.
If you look at the array,
all the elements are grayed out, so
I've effectively ruled out every
single element in this array.
So how can the computer know this?
Well, let's look down at our low and
our high values.
And something kind of funny has happened.
Low is four, but high is three.
So our low has actually gotten to
be greater than our high value,
which indicates to our algorithm,
essentially,
that we've exhausted all of
the range that we can look at.
So we've squeezed our range so
tightly, the high and
low have actually switched places and
we're out of places to look.
So at that point, we can conclude that
the element that we're looking for
is not actually in the array and
we can simply return this null value,
indicating we didn't find it.
Now it's your turn again.
Go ahead and finish off this code.
I'm showing you a skeleton code here for
that binary search algorithm,
and you can go back to the algorithm and
compare it to this code.
One thing I'll point out is this method,
compareTo, that you might
not have seen before.
What compareTo does is, it compares
a parameter object to a calling object.
In this case, it will compare
the city name that we're looking
at in that airport object
to the toFind city name.
And it will return negative
one if the calling object,
so in this case toFind or
Istanbul is less than,
alphabetically less than the city object
in the airport, so the parameter object.
And we'll return zero if
they're the same string and
it will return positive one if the city
we're looking for, the toFind is
alphabetically greater than the city
that we passed in as the parameter.
So we can use that to make our
choice about whether we should go
look at the smaller end of the array or
the larger end of the array, or
If in fact were actually done.
So use that information
to complete this code,
pause the video and I'll pick up
with you again in just a minute.
All right, welcome back.
Let's fill in this code.
There's not too much you have to write,
just have to write what happens in those
three conditions, depending on where
the thing you're trying to find is,
relative to that mid location
that you're looking at.
So, in the first case there,
that if compares less then zero.
What that's saying is that the element
we're trying to find, the city name we're
trying to find is alphabetically less then
the element we're looking at in our array.
So we need to adjust our range, so
it's in the lower half of the range
we were previously looking at.
That means we need to bring high down.
So let's change our variable high so
that it's down at mid.
But not just at mid,
it actually needs to be one less than
mid because we already looked at mid.
So we'll subtract one from mid and
that's our new value of high,
and then the loop's ready to start again.
But if compare is greater than zero, that
means the thing we're trying to find is
alphabetically greater than
the thing we're looking at at mid.
So we need to adjust our range up.
In that case,
we need to change our low variable.
So we'll change it to be equal to mid + 1.
And if neither those things are true that
means that compare is equal to zero.
Which means we've found th
element that we're looking for.
In which case, we can just return
that three letter airport code.
That's all we need to do here
in the else statement is
return airports[mid].getcode().
And that's it.
That's the complete code, and there you
can see it a little bit cleaned up.
Now I just want to make one
small comment about this code.
Most people if you show them this code
if they're sophisticated programmers,
they kind of cringe.
They'd say, ooh,
there's kind of a problem here.
It's not really a functional problem.
It's going to work correctly most of
the time except when your data is very,
very large and your numbers for
high and low get very,
very large if your array is really,
really big.
What's gonna happen is
when you add high and
low together,
it's gonna do something called overflow.
You're gonna get a number that's so big
that you can't represent it, essentially,
in Java in an integer value.
So we can help guard against that
situation by instead of adding high and
low together and then dividing by two,
what we really should be doing instead
is subtracting low from high to get the
range we're talking about, dividing that
value by two and then adding it to our low
to get it back into the correct range.
So that's a better way to write this code.
The other way will work as long as
your numbers don't get too big but,
to be a sophisticated programmer
start getting in the habit of
thinking about things like this.
You don't ever want your integer values
to get too big, when you can help it.
So let's end going back to
these same thought questions.
So, we said before,
in a linear search if we get unlucky
we're gonna have to look through
every single element in our array and
if there are a lot of elements in
our array, like there are a lot of
words in the dictionary, that can be
a very, very slow, cumbersome process.
So, binary search is going
to improve on that a lot.
So, you notice when we were
tracing through the algorithm, and
when I was looking through the dictionary,
that I could eliminate essentially half of
the remaining choices,
without even looking at them.
Every step through the loop,
that was great.
And if I do this process repeatedly, what
I'm doing is I'm dividing the number of
things I have to look
at in half every time.
So I divide my original numbers in half,
I have half as many.
I divide that in half, half as many again.
And half and half and
half and half until I get down to just
a single element that I'm looking at.
And, it turns that the way
the function that expresses,
that half-half-half-half
function is the logarithm.
It's the logarithm base two.
So, if I compare the function that
represents the number of elements that I
have to look at in linear search
which is just equal to n,
the number of elements that I have in
my ray to that log base to n function.
I can see that these two
functions behave very differently.
So when my n is fairly small, say two,
32, 1024 my log is also quite small.
But you know the two values
aren't horribly different.
But as n gets very, very large,
you can see that a huge difference
emerges between these two values.
N grows, and it can get pretty darn big.
So it can get into the billions.
There are about 7.2, 7.4,
depending on when you're watching this
video, billion people on the planet.
So, if you think about that in terms of N,
7.2 billion.
And log N, which really isn't that much
more than 30, that's a huge difference.
And so, these numbers are really gonna
make a difference when we're talking
about extremely large data.
So that's our first taste of comparing
basically how long these algorithms
take to run, and
you're gonna see much more of that in
the next couple lessons on sorting.