[MUSIC]
Welcome back.
In this lesson we're gonna learn about
benchmarking which means this video
I get to have a little bit of fun.
The reason I get to have some fun is
that my PhD is actually in computer
architecture.
Computer architecture is the high
level of design of processors.
And when you start talking
about designing processors,
you're talking about making things fast.
If you wanna be able to say one processor
is faster than another processor
you have to have some programs
to run on the processors.
And those are essentially
called benchmarks.
So in this video we're going to dive
in beneath the hood a little bit.
And look at some of these details in
terms of how long does it take for
a program to run.
And what are the different things
that affect program execution time.
So big goals for this video is for
you to be able to explain the role
of benchmarking in computer science, and
for you to be able to identify components
in real systems that can
impact execution time.
Now you may have already used some
kind of benchmarking software before.
For example, the website on the left,
www.speedtest.net has software
designed to test your internet service
provider's ability to transfer data, so
essentially how fast is
your internet connection.
The website on the right is
benchmarking software for video gamers.
So if you're a video gamer and
you wanna see how well your video
games are gonna play on your system,
this software is designed to essentially
test all that hardware your graphics card,
your processor, etcetera.
So if you want to see how well does your
system do given a piece of software,
that's the classic case of benchmarking.
Now the other way that you may have
used benchmarking before is if you ran
a program that was a little slow.
So may want to use benchmarking to
essentially compare one piece of software
against another.
So you may have had your old code, which
took awhile to run, say like ten seconds.
Then you improve your code, and
it ran in say four seconds.
You've essentially done benchmarking.
You compared your old version of your code
against your new version of the code and
you say your new version
of your code is better.
Now if you've ever done this before you
may have noticed that the execution times
weren't very consistent.
It may have ran four seconds one time,
six seconds the next, three the next.
Why is there a variance there?
Well those details are what
we're gonna dive into now.
When Mia first introduced
run time analysis, she said,
you know, when you're trying to work on
a real system, there's a lot of different
variables that play into how
long it takes something to run.
So it's really useful to be able to
analyze an algorithm in itself and
we've been doing a great deal
of that in the last lesson.
And that's an incredibly useful
way to analyze an algorithm.
But at some point or another, you actually
wanna run your software on a system,
and you wanna be able to
measure how long it takes.
There are a number of
components that go into that.
Now I'm gonna dive into some details here
that you don't need to know going forward.
We're not gonna test you on it.
But I just want you to see that there's
a lot of components that all play into
how long it takes for
something to run on a real system.
Now one area that you're probably
very familiar with is the Compiler.
So, when you take your code that you've
written it goes through a Java Compiler,
it produces Byte Code which then
runs on Java Virtual Machine.
And there's two things I
want you to focus on here.
The first is that the Java Virtual Machine
is actually an abstraction,
it's an abstraction for computers.
You don't need all the details
behind to essentially write
the byte code to run on it.
The second piece I want you to focus
on is that the compiler makes choices.
The choices it makes affects
the performance of your program.
Now there are companies that
compete in other languages,
like C++, to essentially produce the best
compilers the fastest running compilers.
So what your compiler does
impacts your performance.
But let's dive into the details
of the Java Virtual Machine,
let's go one level of extraction lower.
Your Java Virtual Machine is actually
executing on top of an operating system.
An operating system makes choices too.
An operating system is
essentially an obstraction for
all your hardware components.
And it makes decisions like how many
resources should your program get?
How often should it get to run?
How long does it run for?
All these decisions are made
by your operating system and
that affects performance too.
But again, it's an abstraction for
the hardware.
So let's look at the hardware.
When you actually start running your
program it's gonna run on real devices.
Your program exists and
data exists on hard disk.
Your memory is essentially your working
set that you're working with right now.
And your CPU is actually what
does all your computations.
You have other components
in your computer.
You may have a graphics card which
does again graphics rendering.
You may have a monitor, a keyboard,
a mouse, an internet port,
a wireless adapter.
All of these things can
impact performance.
At this point you're almost certainly
saying, whoa, that's a lot of details.
And in fact I'm kinda breaking
some rules right now.
These systems have been designed so
these details are hidden away from you.
That's the whole purpose of abstraction.
In fact we should be really
happy about abstraction.
Because when you wrote your first
program you didn't deal with,
how am I gonna pull the program from
disc and then get that into memory and
then put that through my processor and
then get that to the screen.
You just wrote it in Java.
And it ran on the Java virtual machine.
So why then am I pulling back the curtains
here and looking at the details?
And this would be for two reasons.
The first is because when we thing
about the running time of a program on
a real system, it's influenced by
all these things, by the compiler,
by the operating system,
by the processor design.
The other reason I'm talking about these,
is because these are really
interesting topics in themselves.
After you've finished the specialization I
encourage to look more into any of these
topics you may be interested in.
Again compiler design is
interesting in itself.
Operating systems is
incredibly interesting.
And of course I love computer architecture
which is the design of processors.
So, let's get back to performance.
So how then,
given how complex these real systems are,
can we reason about how long it takes
to run our program on a real system?
You might right now be thinking,
well, wait, I have the program, and
I have the system,
couldn't I just run it and time it?
Well yeah, that's what benchmarking is.
So benchmarking is just running
a program on a real machine and
measuring its performance.
And for right now we're gonna define
performance to be essentially how long it
takes for a program to execute.
But I do wanna say there
are other metrics in performance.
For example, you might care
about how much power is consumed
in running that program if you're
talking about a laptop or smartphone.
But for right now, again, let's just focus
on how long it takes for something to run.
And we'll use benchmarking in two ways.
The first is it allows us to
compare different machines
by running the same program
on each of those machines.
And the other way we use it,
is comparing two different programs
on the same machine, and that's what
we're going to do in our next video.