[MUSIC]
In the last video we started looking how
to measure the time of program running
on a real system.
What we're gonna do here is start talking
about how we actually measure time
specifically measure time in Java.
And to do that we're going to look
at how Java timing libraries work.
So let's think about
some code we might have.
Let's say we're trying to measure how
long it takes to execute selectionSort,
which we learned in the previous course.
What I wanna do to measure this is I wanna
say, create an array of values, I wanna
fill those values with random contents,
and then I'd wanna run selectionSort.
But how long did selectionSort run there?
I can't just measure the time of
the program because I've got time to
create the array and I've got time to
fill the contents with random values.
I wanna measure just selectionSort.
I mean, I guess what I could do is I could
say, put a print statement right before
and right after and
take out a stopwatch and like go, click.
Right when it starts, and then click when
it stops and try to measure it that way,
but that doesn't seem like
it's going to work very well.
So Java does have something that
we could use to help do this.
How can we just get
the time of selection sort.
Well it turns out Java does,
it has within the system class it
has something called nanoTime.
Which you can call and
essentially give you the current time,
which you can then use to
compare against some other time.
So we're gonna use that in our code
here to evaluate the execution time
of that selection sort.
And we're gonna do that by putting
first a call to system time
right before selectionSort.
And I'm gonna put another call
to it right after selectionSort.
And then all I have to do is essentially
subtract that startTime from that endTime,
divide it by one billion because
it's in nanoseconds, and
I get how long it took for it to run,
and then I can print that out.
And now, why might I wanna do this?
Well, I might wanna measure how long it
takes for a selectionSort to execute.
And I may wanna compare
selectionSort execution time
with growing the size of the array.
So the idea for
this would be something like let's
take increasing sizes of n,
let's then print n.
We'll then create a randomized
array of size n,
and then we'll time selection sort and
print out the outcome.
Then, let's compare this to quick sort.
Let's say, you get a randomized
array of size n again, and
time quick sort, and
print out its outcome.
If I write the real code for
this and ran it on a real system,
I could get times back like this.
So essentially I have on the left
hand side the value of n and
or the size of the array.
And then I have a column for
all the selection sort
outcomes in terms of seconds.
And I have a column for the Quicksort
And you see immediately that
Quicksort's way faster, even for
only 10,000 elements in the array.
And selectionSort keeps growing and
growing, and Quicksort still really fast.
This is great data, and
we can use this in some additional ways to
essentially analyze how did that program
run, and we'll do that in the next video.