[MUSIC]
All right, welcome back.
In the last video,
we started to see real system times.
In this next video,
we're going to go into more depth.
We're gonna look at those
real system times and
we're gonna use them to make decisions
about the performance of our algorithms,
the performance of our programs.
So by the end of this video,
you should be able to use runtimes for
a real system to reason about performance.
So in the last video,
we had just seen the idea that we're
gonna try to measure the sort times.
Both for selection sort and
for quick sort.
Again, on a real system.
So the idea behind this is to
go with increasing sizes of n,
print the value of n.
Create a randomized array of size n and
then time selection sort and
print how long it took.
We'll so the same thing again for
quick sorts.
We'll create a randomized array,
time it and then print the outcome.
What we got from that was essentially this
set of data and we can see really quickly
from the data that quick sort did better,
but we couldn't really reason much about
the performance yet,
unless we do a more in-depth analysis.
So what we're going to do next is
throw this into Google Sheets and
essentially, do some analysis
of the graphs of this.
So this is the initial graph of
selection sort against quick sort.
The y-axis here is how much time
it took for them to run and
the x-axis is essentially size n.
And again, this confirms our original view
of this that quick sort is just much,
much faster than selection sort,
even for fairly small values of n, but
let's look at each of these
algorithms in some depth.
So starting with selection sort.
What we see is essentially these
are the runtimes as n goes forward.
And if you look at this,
it kinda looks like an n squared growth,
but how do we know for sure?
What we can do is essentially do a best
fit on the data against say, an n squared.
And the way to do that is essentially
figure out a reasonable value,
the constant that goes in
front of that n squared term.
So by best fit here, all I'm saying is I
found a reasonably good constant value for
k and then I plotted that.
And you can see here that the actual
runtimes for section sort,
match an n squared growth quite well for
this constant that I found.
Now what you might be saying is well,
wait a second,
you said this is the best fit and
you found a really good constant for it.
Wouldn't it look really good whether
it's n squared or n cubed or n?
Well, let's do the same thing.
I mean, try to find a good constant value
for n cubed and a good concept value for
n and see how it works.
So here's the three different fits,
we having blue is still the actual.
In yellow, we still have the best fit for
an n squared.
And then in green,
I have this best fit for n cubed.
And immediately, you see that that
n cubed grows way too quickly.
So, either I pick a constant that has
the values way too low early on or
I have it essentially go off
this chart fairly quickly.
So n cubed just won't fit,
no matter what constant value I use.
Likewise, if we look at red,
that's the best fit of n growth.
And essentially here,
we see that it's not fitting either.
No matter what constant value I do for
linear growth, it won't fit.
It's gonna be too high at
the beginning and too low later on.
So really, this n squared is the right way
to look at this in terms of the growth.
And that's exactly what we would expect
for selection sort, so we're happy to see
that runtimes on our real system actually
match our high-level analysis beforehand.
So let's then focus in on quick sort.
So in our initial view, we saw quick
sort was essentially just this line on
the bottom, because the values were so
low, essentially just at the axis.
So if I zoom in on it, what we're gonna
get is a little bit more refined data or
better view and the first thing I want
you to notice is that this is real data.
So we have two of these points that are
essentially outliers and there is a number
of reasons why these could be outliers,
but I'll focus on two of those reasons.
The first is that you know that
the quick sort is n log(n),
essentially an average case.
But depending on the input set,
it could run longer than that.
So these could just be
essentially to randomized inputs
that didn't perform that well for
a quick sort.
What I think is actually is more likely
is that this is on a real system.
There could be other things scheduling,
other programs running at the same time.
And if you look at these values
in the hundredths of seconds.
So if something else got scheduled at
the same time, so are conflicting for
resources on the same system, you can see
aberrations in data like this very easily.
The second thing I wanna point
out about this graph is that this
kind of looks linear.
Looks like linear growth, not the n log
n that we talked about, the high-level
analysis and how can you really tell the
difference between linear versus n log(n)?
Well, to do that, first thing
is that we kinda need more data.
These are really small sizes of n,
especially for
quick sort when quick sort is so quick.
Now we have a great deal more data for
quick sort and
we're gonna all the way out to 10
million elements for size of n.
And you can essentially see that we've
still got the same kind of graph and
we still have these some of these
points are going up and down the chart,
but this is really a clean,
almost linear growth.
But again, how do I tell the difference
between when you're an log(n),
especially in this granularity?
What I can do is essentially that
same best fit analysis that we just
talked about.
So what I'll do is I'll do a best fit,
both for
linear growth, as well as n log(n) growth.
And if you zoom in on this,
I know this is a little hard to see.
If you zoom in on it,
in yellow we have that n log(n) growth and
it's matching the actual blue really well.
Whereas in red,
we've got our linear growth and
you see that it essentially falls off.
As you get to larger sizes of n,
you started getting a bigger gap in terms
of the actual versus the predicted data.
So this really is n logging growth, which
is exactly what we expect for quick sort.
So that's great to see, but why were
we seeing it look so much like linear?
Well, the question is how big is log(n)?
So let's say, my n is 10 million,
how big is log(n)?
Take a second to think about it.
If you're answering a really small number
in the 20s to 30s, you're spot on.
In fact, 2 to the 23 is about 8 million.
So this is roughly 23.
Now 23 is really small
relative to 10 million and
that's the problem when you are trying
to do a linear analysis versus n
log(n) is that login is just so
small relative to n.
The n tends to dominate.
So in summary, now that we've looked
at all of these different data points,
I want to bring up the fact that we can
really just use real runtimes to reason
about performance.
But whenever you do so, be careful,
because real system data can be noisy.
But ultimately, if you want to know
how well does your program behave
on a real system,
you have to do this kind of analysis.