[NOISE] So, we've talked about some
algorithms and we've talked about using
benchmarking and timing to try to analyze
the performance of those algorithms.
And so now we're ready for a concept
challenge to bring those ideas together.
And so as you know, for
a concept challenge,
what we ask you to do is to pause and
try to solve the problem yourself.
Then try to find and opportunity to
discuss your solution with other learners,
either on the forum or
with people learning with you.
Then you'll have an opportunity to
watch the UC San Diego Learners
discuss the problem, and then you'll
be able to answer the question again.
And then confirm your understanding as
we go through the solution together.
So, for this particular question, what
we'd like to do is look at some real data
for a sorting algorithm that we ran on
bigger and bigger and bigger collections.
And so, in particular,
could these be the timings,
the real timings for insertion sort?
So, take a look, answer the question,
and then we'll come back later.
>> Hi, I'm Tina.
>> Hi, my name is Gev.
>> Hi, I'm Mia.
>> All right, so
looking at the visual data on this graph,
it seems to fall along
a linear one mostly.
So, I would think it'd be like say,
of and for the run time.
I don't know if it would be for
insertion sort.
>> Cuz we learned about
a lot of different sorts and
insertion sort wasn't really
the most efficient, you know?
>> Yeah.
You're right.
I remember talking about merge sort and
quick sort and
there are n log n and that's one of
the best possible times you can get.
And what this looks like,
it looks like all then and
that kind of sounds too good
to be true for insertion sort.
>> If it's too good to be true,
then maybe we can probably rule out
that this wouldn't be a worst case time.
>> Yeah.
>> Maybe it could be, best case then?
>> So you've seen the UC San Diego
learners discuss these timings that we
were seeing and think really
about whether an actual machine
running insertion sort on bigger and
bigger data could produce these timings.
So, let's tie back the timings
that we got from running the code
to the analysis that we did earlier
in the course trying to think about
the asymptotic behavior of various
sorting algorithms and procedures.
And, in particular we're
thinking about insertion sort.
And when we analyze insertion
sort using big O notation,
we saw that on average, and in the worst
case, big O behaves like, I'm sorry,
insertion sort has a quadratic behavior.
It's got big O of n squared.
But when we look at this graph,
that doesn't seem to jive, right?
The graph looks very linear,
it's going up at a constant rate.
It appears linear and not quadratic.
It doesn't look like a parabola.
And so we're trying to
understand how is this possible.
And one clue comes from looking at
that other cell in the table and
seeing that there is a case when insertion
sort can behave like a linear algorithm.
And so let's think back to when we
might be in that best case performance,
that best case scenario.
And to think about that,
we have to go back to the code of how we
go ahead and implement insertionSort.
And we realize that
the variations in performance,
the variations in timing for the insertion
sort algorithm come from this while loop.
And this while loop executes
a different number of times
based on how organized or
unorganized the data is to begin with.
So, if we start with really almost
sorted or fully sorted data,
then this while loop just checks
whether our current element that
we care about is in it's correct location
relative to the other elements and
if it is, we don't need to do anything.
And, so, if all of the tests that
we did to create that timing chart
that we saw before.
If all of those tests were on really,
really big, but sorted data,
then we could very well have gotten that
linear behavior that we saw, because that
insertion sort algorithm is super
fast on sorted or nearly sorted data.
So indeed, that timing chart that we saw
could be the result of running just basic
old insertion sort on really big data as
long as we know something about that data.
And so the moral of this story is that
when we look at timing data we have to be
aware of drawing conclusions
from that timing data.
And, we wanna be cautious about trying
to deduce the big O complexity and
classes of an algorithm
just based on the timing.
That's not enough.
Usually we need to understand what the
data that we were testing on looks like
and whether there's other
factors at play as well.