[MUSIC]
In this lesson,
we're going to start dealing with testing.
And I really enjoy testing,
because testing influences
your confidence in your code.
And let me tell you just a quick
story here before we get started.
So, I've worked with students for
a long time and I've also worked for
professional programmers a long time.
And there's a surprising difference
in terms of the confidence
about code correctness
between those two groups.
And the surprising difference here is
that students actually tend to be more
confident than
the experienced programmers.
So I'll talk to students, they'll come in,
they'll show me their code.
They'll say, hey I've written all my code,
I haven't compiled it yet, but
I'm sure it's close to being finished.
And this is terrifying, because you
haven't compiled your code yet.
You haven't run any test cases.
How can you be sure that
it's working correctly?
In turn though,
I've also seen professional programmers
who've written and tested even
parts of their code, and they still don't
have much confidence about whether or
not it's correct or not until they've
seen extensive testing done on that code.
So there's a big difference in terms
of confidence, I think comes from
the misunderstanding about, how do you
know if your code works, or if it doesn't?
And a lot of that has to do with testing.
So by the end of this video, I hope you'll
be able to explain the value of having
confidence in your code, and also be able
to identify some ways to build confidence
about your code's correctness.
So when we start talking
about code correctness,
let's start thinking about code
that runs in important systems.
So there's code that runs say,
a pacemaker in someone's heart.
And there's code that's going to be
running the next self-driving car.
And there's code the runs the landing
program on the space shuttle.
You have to be incredibly confident
about the correctness of this code
before you'd ever let it
impact people's lives.
So how do you gain this confidence?
Well, it's hard to gain the confidence
especially given there's lots of different
people who are gonna use your code.
There are users who are gonna
try to use your code, and
users do a lot of unexpected things
with code when they work with it.
You also have hackers who are
intentionally trying to misuse your code
in order to break it to gain some
kind of privileged access to it.
You have other software
developers in your own company,
who might use your code in a way
different than it was intended.
And then, you also have yourself.
I'm working with code these days
that I wrote ten years ago.
I want to be sure that my code is actually
correct that I use in the future, too.
So let's focus on one scenario here.
Let's just look at programmers.
And talk about how confident
our code needs to be.
How confident we have to be in our code
to be able to say it's working correctly.
So let's say you're working at a company
and there's 30 programmers there.
And each programmer writes say,
only ten methods.
Well, right there you've
already got 300 methods.
Well, let's say you got some really
good software engineers, and
they're 99% sure that each of
those methods works correctly.
Well, what are your chances that
one of those methods is broken?
95% chance one of those is broken.
That's pretty scary.
And this is ignoring interactions
that may occur between the methods or
highly level design mistakes
that may have happened.
This is just looking at
the individual methods themselves.
The other way you can look at
this as a software engineer,
is to essentially say that
this is risk assessment.
If you talk to CTOs of companies,
this is essentially what they'll say.
Well, depends on the domain.
If we're working with pacemaker code,
you have to be sure it's gonna work right
before you ever release it to the wild.
On the other hand, if you're writing code
for a website that provides cute cats,
it's still fun, it's still important, but
you can have some bugs in there
without any real loss of life, right?
So it really just depends on the domain.
You have to have different degrees
of confidence depending on how it's
gonna be used.
So, how do we gain confidence for our code
and how do we reason about the confidence?
What I wanna do is give you some ideas,
essentially,
about how I feel about my code.
This is just my personal opinion.
But essentially,
when I have written code and
I haven't compiled it yet, I have almost
no confidence that that code is correct.
I've been writing code for a long time.
I just assume that it's gonna have
problems until shown differently.
Even after I've compiled the code,
I still have no confidence in it because I
could have many kinds of bugs at run time.
Maybe I've tested against a basic input.
The inputs, maybe a couple of inputs that
I used to essentially device my algorithm.
I'm still gonna have a low degree of
confidence because I haven't tested corner
cases yet.
After I test corner cases, like giving a
null input as a reference or say, an empty
list, then I start feeling a little more
confident about my code working properly.
But it's not until
a whole bunch of users or
other software engineers of the company
start pounding on down my code,
before you're gonna start
feeling really good about it.
And this is why companies do beta testing.
They want users to essentially pound on
the code to essentially
find potential mistakes.
You might say, wait a second, couldn't we
just test it against all possible inputs,
and then we know for
sure it's gonna work no matter what.
Well, maybe.
If your method only depends on say,
a boolean, so it has different behaviors,
whether or
not a true value is given to it or
false value, sure,
you can try both true or false.
But even if your method takes
just three integer inputs,
this is gonna be essentially impossible.
Using int has essentially four
billion different values.
And if you wanna look at all possible
combinations of three integers,
you're looking at this number here, and
I have no idea what this number is.
It's just huge.
There's no way you could possibly
test all these combinations.
Which means if your method
takes an array as an input, or
depends on information being
fed to you from a database,
there's just no way you could
try it on all possible inputs.
This is just scary.
So we can't test on all possible inputs,
we just try to test it on as much as we
possibly can, in real life situations.
So how then can we
increase our confidence?
Well first off, at an algorithmic level,
be critical of your code.
Be critical of your idea.
You wanna make sure,
first devise your algorithm, and
then essentially put on your
skeptic hat and try to break it.
Trying breaking it in many
ways as you possibly can.
In the process of trying to break it,
you're essentially gonna try all these
different corner cases to see whether or
not it's gonna work.
Is is gonna go off the end of the array?
Is it gonna again, deal with that
null reference being fed to it?
The other thing you can do
is usually attempt to reason
about its correctness formally.
There's an area of programming languages
that's essentially focused on this.
And that could essentially
be a course within itself.
The last thing you could do, is
essentially create automated test cases,
that are gonna try and test the code in
a whole bunch of different situations, so
you can feel more confident
in its performance.
And that's, in fact,
what we're gonna do next.