[SOUND] We've heard how
important it is to test but
let's talk now about testing practices.
So the goal at the end of this video is
to be able to describe different testing
methodologies and
be able to compare and contrast them.
So first off, let's start by looking
at the development cycle of code.
Kind of standard cycle is to write code
then write tests to test whether or
not the code's working right, run those
tests and then iterate through there.
But there's an entire design development
practice which puts testing front and
center.
And what it essentially asks is how
are you writing that code if you don't
know how it's gonna be tested?
And there's usually some specifications
about how the code's supposed to work but
you don't know for sure until you
see how it's gonna be tested.
And with this development practice
called test driven development,
what we're gonna do is just essentially
flip those first two steps.
So we're gonna write the tests
before we actually write the code.
Now, there are a number of
companies that use this approach.
But I wanna say, before we start to
argue the merits of each of these,
this is a very contentious area.
So when the right tests,
which tests are best to run?
This is open area for debate.
Now there's debate within the software
engineering community about how to do this
but there is some general consensus.
And the general consensus is you shouldn't
wait till the end to test your code.
Test early and test often.
How are we gonna run these tests?
Well, there's two testing styles.
The first is called black box testing.
Now, with black box testing,
you're only testing the interface or
through the interface.
The other style known as clear box or
white box testing or
tests that know actually about how
the implementation was set up.
We can think about this going back
to Christine's earlier example of
the abstraction barrier.
So we have the car where you're thinking
about how does the brake pedal work from
a driver perspective.
And then on the other side of
the abstraction barrier you've
got the mechanics and the engineers who
actually understand how brakes work.
So if you think about black box testing
you're thinking about essentially just
that driver trying to use the interface,
trying to press the brake to
make sure it stops and
press the gas to make sure it goes.
On the hand though,
if you're a mechanic you know a lot
more about the implementation.
You may know these are disc brakes,
so these should be tested this way or
these are drum brakes, so
these should be tested this other way.
So it just depends on which side of
this abstraction barrier you're on.
And there are pros and
cons to each of these.
So what I want you to do is look
through these potential advantages for
black box testing and
see which ones you think are correct.
Welcome back.
So I hope you were able to look through
these examples and by doing so,
start getting a better feel for
when black box testing is appropriate and
when clear box testing is appropriate.
Let's just walk through these one by one.
So it's black box testing is it gonna be
more representative how users are actually
going to use the code?
To some degree, yes, it is.
You think back to that driving example,
if you're thinking from
the clear box testing view.
You're the mechanic,
you're not going to be worried so
much about will the user ever press
the brake and the gas at the same time.
But if you're actually user of the car
it's more apt that your going home with
the scenario of well,
I can actually press both these at once.
What should happen?
So if you're thinking
from the interface or
the driver side you'll have a better
view of what users really do?
Second one is it easier to write
by someone who's unfamiliar
with the implementation?
This is absolutely correct.
So you don't need to know how
that code piece was implemented
to be able to test it.
You just have to know what
the interface looks like.
So it's easier in a sense to
write those black box tests.
The last option are you more
knowledgeable of potential corner cases
which might cause incorrect behavior
if you're doing black box testing.
The answer's probably not.
This really is an advantage
to clear box testing.
But it also just depends on
how you define corner cases.
If you're thinking corner cases as those
weird scenarios that the users might do
like in option a.
Then yeah, this kind of is true for
black box testing.
But what we really mean for this option
here is if you know the details how brakes
works, if you know this
implementation is a disk brake and
disk brakes often fail when these two
components aren't aligned properly.
You can do a much more rigorous test on
that component of the brakes which you
wouldn't be able to do if
you did black box testing.
So option c is really an advantage for
clear box testing not black box testing.
So now that we have an idea of these
tests, what should we actually do for
the testing?
So should I be testing
each individual statement?
So should I say, assign a to be 5 and
then test if a is not 5, abort?
Well no, this would be silly.
This is way too fine grain.
This is way too within the weeds.
That's too small of
a piece of code to test.
So you're saying, well wait a second.
So if it's too small, should I be testing
at the whole code level of alpha testing?
Well, this isn't the right place to start.
Alpha testing is incredibly important but
you don't want wait until then.
That is way too late.
So we need to find some
kind of middle ground.
And the middle ground that is gonna
work for us is essentially methods.
We need to find a small unit of code,
small section of code to test and
methods that actually match
that description quite well.
In fact, this is what people mean
when they're saying unit testing.
Just testing really small pieces
of code or units of code.
So how are we gonna be
performing these tests?
We're actually gonna be
doing these using JUnit,
which is a built in suite
essentially to help test Java code.
Now it's actually built in and
allows us to write and
run tests for exactly unit testing.
It's fantastic.
It's actually built into Eclipse, so if
you want to know more details about how to
use JUnit with Eclipse we're gonna
have a support video on that next.
If your more interested in just diving
in to how do you write tests for
linked lists,
that's gonna be the next core video.
Coming up next.