[MUSIC]
Then the other important bit about
testing your code is actually testing
the behavior.
So there are different ways
that you can test the behavior.
One of them is unit testing.
So with unit testing you basically just
want to test a particular piece of code.
So you want to make sure that you are only
testing an isolated piece of method,
rather than testing the whole software.
>> And then once you're pretty sure that
that little piece of code is working
properly, you can use
integration tests which will
check the connection between that piece
of code and other pieces of code.
So if you're writing a service that say,
like relies on a database,
you can actually check the connection
between your code and the database.
Make sure it's pulling information out of
it properly, storing stuff in it properly,
that kind of thing.