[MUSIC]
Hey everyone.
In this support video what we're
gonna do is look at JUnit in detail.
So, first off we're going
to look at our code.
In the package that was provided you'll
find there's a MyLinkedListTester
which is already set up to do JUnit.
To make sure that you're
able to run JUnit,
you want to make sure that you've
done the setup instructions properly.
To set up JUnit,
you go to project, properties.
Go to the Java build path.
And then add in add library.
You'll select JUnit.
JUnit four.
And then finish, and that'll essentially
add in the JUnit four libraries.
And that's essentially what
you need to be able to JUnit.
Okay, so now that Eclipse is set up,
let's talk about JUnit overall.
So JUnit is a lightweight test platform.
And what you do is you're gonna
write methods that are going to run
before the tests occur and
then you're going to write methods which
are essentially just testing the behavior
of methods in some other class.
In this case we're trying to
test The MyLinkedListClass,
specifically this class right here.
Let me give you a preview of some of
the methods you might want to write.
One method that's incredibly
useful is called setup.
And for
setup what you do is put an @before and
that means this would be run
before a test, and you run setup.
And what it's gonna do is essentially
set up the state of your variables so
that you're able to perform tests.
In this case, we're setting up a short
list, an empty list, a longer list, and
we're gonna use these for
a number of tests.
It's worth noting that there is another
method called setupClass, which,
if you wanna run something just once
not before every single test case,
you'd use setupClass.
But if you wanna have setup done
before each individual test,
that's where you use setup.
In terms of writing tests, the syntax for
this, lets just say @Test, and
then this is one of the test
cases that'll be executed.
In this case I have the method testGet,
so this is supposed to test the get
method in a MyLinkedList class.
Let me point out the two things that
are probably the most useful to you
in terms of seeing whether or
not your code is working properly.
The first is actually down here,
which is called assertEquals.
With assertEquals, what it says is,
I want you to verify that "A",
in fact, matches shortlist.get(0).
If those two are not equal,
I want you to throw an error.
If they're the same, just keep going.
So since they're the same,
assert that this logic is true.
And assert exists in a number
of programming languages to help
with debugging and catching any errors.
The other method that I think is
going to be quite useful is fail.
And the,
where fail comes in is emptyList.get(0) is
supposed to throw an exception.
I have an empty list, there's nothing in
there, if I try to get an element out of
that that should throw an index
out of bounds exception.
But how am I gonna test that in place?
If I just call the method
emptyList.get(0),
it's gonna throw an exception which
could be treated like an improper
activity via inceptions being strung.
So the way we do this is to actually throw
your operation within a tri catch block
where the proper behavior is
actually gonna be caught.
So it's gonna catch an index out of
bounds, exception if it catches it,
it's just gonna keep going
to the very next task.
But if this codes succeeds and
doesn't throw an index out of bounds
exception, what you call is a method fail.
And fail is gonna say,
this did not work, we need to quit and
it will print out you need
to check your out of bounds.
We could have more of a verbose print
messages here, something like in test get,
empty the list if I get 0 fails
you should check out of bounds and
those are going to be the main
methods used for this.
There are other methods that allow you
to tear down anything you've built in
the process of this test.
You're not going to need this for
this case.
But if you'd say, create a large
database before you began the test,
when all the tests are done
you'd want to tear that down.
And the way that you'd do that is
you'd make a method teardown and
you use an @ after to denote I want this
method to be performed after
all the testing is complete.
So what does this look
like when you run it?
So if we go to MyLinkedListTester and
we try to run this code what
it's going to give me is a whole new
window over here on the left called JUnit.
And what it will give you
is a number of things.
It will tell you how many different
tests it ran, in this case there's six.
Now we've put code within testGet and
within testRemove.
All the others are just
empty stubs at this point.
So I ran all six of those tests.
Because I haven't written
the MyLinkedList class yet, testGet and
testRemove are both gonna fail because
it's not gonna behave properly.
What you will also is that there is
actually times associated with this.
This is how much time was spent
running these tests to figure
out that there was a failure here and
within test remove there is an error.
If you ever see these times start becoming
large in the second range or even ten
second range, you might want to think
more about how you are doing your tests.
But again as we said in
the original videos,
it's more important to make sure
that you're testing your codes and
getting it right and then afterwards
think about the performance implications.
I hope this helps you get started with
JUnit and good luck on your project.