[MUSIC]
In the last few videos, we started looking
at more details about how to do testing.
And so
far we've looked at a really high level.
We've been talking about
why testing's important,
how you can do it in
the development cycle, and
we kinda ended at this point of saying,
well, we need to be able to test methods.
For me, testing didn't quite make sense
until I saw it in a clear example.
So what we're gonna do
here is do exactly that.
We're gonna walk through a single
example of testing a single method
from your linked list.
So the goal by the end of this video is to
be able to write tests for linked lists,
which is what you're being asked to do for
the project.
So let's start with a doubly linked
list like we been working with before.
We've still got a head pointer
pointing to the sentinel node.
You got tail pointer pointing to the tail
sentinel and we've got both next and
previous pointers all the way throughout.
We're gonna be testing the method get.
This is a quick reminder, get takes and
is an index, and it's gonna return back
the value of that element at that index.
So it's gonna walk through the link list,
find index say 1 and return back 42 here.
Now if you ask for something that's
invalid like I asked for index 10 for
a list that only has two elements
it should throw an index out of
bounds exception.
So we need to be able to
test that behavior too.
We'll get to that in just a bit.
So I have the idea now to
essentially test this git method.
But what test should I run?
Now here are the scenarios.
These are all different tests
I could potentially run.
And I want you to select which
ones you think apply, and
try to avoid ones that might be redundant,
compared to previous ones.
So if you think it's already been tested,
you can essentially say
that this is redundant.
I don't need to test this anymore.
Go ahead and
take a few minutes to work on this quiz.
I'll see you back in a moment.
Welcome back.
I hope that working through this
helped you understand better
what kind of tests we should run and
which ones we shouldn't.
So let's walk through each
of these in more detail.
So first off should I test
get (0) on an empty list?
Where would this be important?
Well this is a very good example of
a corner case where you have empty lists,
you better be sure that you're testing
that it's gonna throw an out of bounds
exception if you're trying
to get an element from it.
So this is a perfect
test of a corner case.
How do I do this test?
Well if we're working in JUnit,
like we talked about in the last video,
what you're gonna do is
simply write this test.
You're gonna say try.
You're gonna put, because
emptList.get can throw an exception,
you're gonna put this in a try block.
And the correct behavior is for
it to throw an exception.
So you want it to throw
an IndexOutOfBoundsException, and
you want that to get caught.
That is actually the right behavior here.
The wrong behavior is for it to just
get without throwing that exception, or
to throw some other kind of exception.
So if you do emptyList.get and
you get something back instead
of throwing exception,
you'll then execute the code fail
which is essentially, you failed here.
This should have thrown an exception.
Next test.
Should we be testing get
on a negative value?
Well there's a lot of scenarios you
can think about in code where you
might accidentally ask for negative index.
It's important if you're asking for
negative index, for that to fail as well.
This is another great
example of a corner case.
The way you'd test this is very
similar to the test we just saw.
And we have a short list.
This is a list I have instantiated to have
the elements that you see up at the top.
It's got just that one element 65 and
we're gonna try get -1 on it.
And that should fail.
That should throw
an IndexOutOfBoundsException.
If it fails to do that,
we should essentially fail a test.
That's exactly what this code does.
Next one, should a test get 0
from a list with 1 element.
Is this worth running?
Absolutely.
This is a standard use case.
I definitely wanna be able to get
the first element from a list that
has one element.
How would I write that in JUnit?
I would essentially say assertEquals and
that means these two better be equal,
or this test fails.
That's what assertEquals means.
And then what I do is I put
a string in there first to say,
check to make sure
the first element's there.
And then I'm gonna test,
I'm gonna give the value that I expect,
which is the (Interger) value for 65.
And then I'm gonna call the shortlist,
which has just this one element, .get(0).
And that should return back 65,
these two should match.
If the assertEquals succeeds, we're fine.
If those two don't match,
it'll fail, and my test will fail.
All right.
Do we wanna try,
get one from a list with two elements, or
do we think this is potentially redundant?
Well this one's a bit debatable.
If you're thinking of black box testing,
you might say this is redundant.
But if we know just a little
bit about the implementation,
it's completely reasonable
to run this test,
because we want to be able to know that we
can get more than just the first element.
For example,
your code could work just to say
essentially head.next to
get the first element
without ever running any loops to get to
the most appropriate element on the list.
So because I know that my code
is gonna have loops in it,
I kind of know a bit of the details
about the implementation, and
I want to test to make sure I can get
any element, not just the first one.
So this is a completely
reasonable test to run, but
again I'm kind of knowing a bit of
the details about the implementation.
All right.
The way I would do this is
just like the last one.
I'm gonna say assertEquals, I wanna
make sure that if I call shortlist2,
this is the one that has these
two elements, that get(1)),
it should return back
to me the value of 42.
I'm just gonna make sure
those two values are equal.
If they are, the test passes.
If they're not, my test will fail.
All right, last one.
Should I test to get 2 from
a list that has 3 elements, and
that's the 3 elements we see up above.
Well, now we're being redundant.
I already know that I can test,
I can find more than the first
element because of the last test d.
What you could argue is,
maybe this is a better test than d,
than option d which is just find
the second elements in the list.
One of these tests is required to
essentially find, to test whether or
not can find more than the first element,
but only one of them.
At a certain point if you just
keep running this over and
over, it's gonna get a bit redundant.
In summary, the most important thing
is to consider both the corner cases we
are testing as well as the common case.
Again this is the most important piece.
Make sure you test these components and
test them well.
Less important there is a cost
associated with testing.
Most companies run unit
tests overnight and
this is gonna take some number of hours.
When you're running code overnight, you're
running code usually on your servers
which means you're paying power costs
associated with running these tests.
So if you have a lot of extra redundant
tests that could be problematic.
But in general,
the rule is just err on the safe side.
Test the things that you
think should be tested and
then worry about those redundant
cases eventually later.