[CROSSTALK].
This concept challenge
is about testing and
in particular how to write code to
verify that your test actually worked.
This is a subtle skill and one that you'll
need to get good at in order to make sure
that you're writing correct code.
So same format as before.
Try to answer the question yourself first,
discuss it and
watch the UC San Diego
learners discussing it.
Then answer the question again and confirm
your understanding with our explanation.
So we're gonna be writing a tester for
the remove method in the link list class.
So you've perhaps gotten this link
list setup in your setup method
in your tester and
you wanna test the remove method.
Now just a remind what the remove
method is supposed to do.
It's supposed to take
an index position and
then remove the element
at that index position,
returning the element that was there and
getting rid of the element from the list.
So, let's say you're now
writing your test code.
And, again, you've got this list
already set up in the setup method.
So, you can now work with this list.
It's called list one.
And, the first thing you're going to
do is you're going to test removing
the element at position zero.
Now again, this is just one of the tests
that you're going to write to test remove.
There are other things you might want to
test, like testing trying to remove off
the ends of the list, testing removal of
a element in the middle of the list, but
you're focused right now on testing
removal of the element at position zero.
Now you can write this line
of code in your tester.
And if it doesn't crash,
that's a good sign.
But it's not enough to verify
that this code actually worked,
that you correctly removed
the element at index permission zero.
So the question for you to work on on this
concept challenge is, what code to you
need to write to verify that this
remove call worked correctly?
>> The first thing that you always need
to do is verify that the actual number
you're removing is the correct one
because you might think that you're
removing the one at position zero,
but then if something goes wrong
you actually remove another one.
So you want to, do actually want to
verify that the value that you're
returning actually matches with
which one you want to remove.
>> And I think the next thing we
need to do is check the next node
which goes after the first one.
And since we remove the node
which contents value 65.
And then the other node,
which contains 21,
would become the first node,
which has index zero.
So I think we do need to check
if it has value of 21, and
then we can know that we
did the correct remove.
>> Yeah.
Yeah, I think both of you are correct.
And I think that the option two and
option five both talking about
the null pointer exceptions.
I think we need to check them, cause the
remove does nothing modification to them.
So I think we can just
do not handle those.
>> Yeah, I think that, well, part of
the reason is because when you check
get negative one, negative one will
return a null pointer exception
no matter what you do to the rest of them,
so I don't think it's really necessary,
and then also to add to that I also don't
think it's necessary to check that.
Get one has a value of 42.
Because you're not actually modifying, so
when you remove 65 all you're doing is
modifying the reference of 21 but you're
not modifying the one that goes after.
>> Yeah, definitely.
Right.
>> You're only modifying
the ones that goes before.
So it's not necessary to check.
It's just I guess you can check but
it's [CROSSTALK],
it would be an unnecessary step.
>> Yeah.
>> Do you think there's anything
else we need to check besides that?
>> Yeah, I think we need to keep track
of the size because size of the list is
stored as a separate reference.
So we want to check whether it's two or
not.
>> Yeah, to make sure that we actually
remember to update the size whenever
we remove an element.
>> All right, so now that you've worked on
the problem yourself, let's go over each
of these possible pieces of code that
you could include in order to verify.
That this line of code worked correctly.
And in essence what we
really need to do is test
the essential pieces
of that remove method.
So what are the essential pieces?
The essential pieces are to actually
return the element that was removed,
to remove it from the list, and
to make sure the list is now
one smaller than it was before.
So those are the verification
steps that we're going to include.
And let's go through the list of all
those verification steps that we gave you
as possibilities,
to see which of those matches those
essential pieces of the remove method.
This first statement here says that
we should verify that the variable
a contains the value 65.
Absolutely.
That's definitely something you should do.
Because that's one of
the things remove has to do,
it has to return the value that was at
position zero, which in this case is 65,
which would now be in the variable a.
So definitely need to check that.
The next possibility
said we should call get
negative one to make sure that causes
an index out of bounds exception.
Well that's not really essential.
It's not an essential piece
of the remove operation.
You absolutely should test this but
it would be more appropriately tested
when your testing the get method.
That's not part of testing whether
removing the element at an exposition zero
actually worked.
So don't bother with that right here.
The next thing said we should call
list one dot get in its position zero
to make sure it now has the value 21.
This is what another piece
that's essential for
the remove method, so yes,
definitely include this test.
When 65 is removed, 21 better have
shifted over to take its place.
So include that test.
What about this next one?
Should we call get at index
permission one to make
sure that 42 has also shifted over?
And the answer to that one is, that's not
an essential test that we need to run
here, that's not an essential
verification step.
Because we're not testing add,
we're not testing get.
We're testing remove and
if we've tested these other methods well,
we can be pretty sure that the integrity
of the list is such that if 21 got moved
over correctly,
then 42 also got moved over correctly.
So that's not an essential
verification step here.
Next question, should we test off
the other end of the list to see if
that throws a null pointer exception.
And again, going back to what we said
about the essential pieces of testing
remove, that's probably
not necessary here.
We're not trying to test the get method.
We're just trying to test remove.
However, there is one more
thing we need to test
to make sure this remove zero worked.
And that's whether or not the size
of the list was actually reduced.
So this last step here,
calling list at size to check to
make sure that it's equal to two is
definitely something you need to do.
So in summary,
we have three essential verification steps
to make sure remove at position
zero worked correctly.
We need to make sure it
return the correct value.
We need to make sure that the element
that was at position zero moved up,
sorry position one moved
up to position zero and
we need to check to make sure that the
size of the list has been reduced by one,
so those are the three essential
verification steps, now before
we go let me just ask you a question,
what about this bug?
So, this bug is where we've updated
the head pointer correctly,
head dot next, but
we've failed to update that node 21,
we haven't updated its previous pointer so
that it connects back to the head.
And, this is definitely a bug,
that red arrow there is not correct.
But my question is will our verifications
steps, those three steps we laid
out over this concept challenge,
will they correctly detect this bug?
And the answer, of course,
is no they won't.
So we're kind of stuck here because
we've actually tested the verification.
We've verified all of the essential
behavior of the remove method and
it seems like it's working correctly.
The problem here is to really test
that this pointer is correct,
we need to get into the structure of this
list because we don't have a great way
of figuring out, when you're going in
the opposite direction, whether or
not all those pointers
are correctly positioned.
So what we'll recommend for
you to do is we'll recommend for
you to actually break the boundaries
of black box testing just a bit.
And, go in and put in a test to
make sure that list get zero,
which should get back that
node that contains 21,
make sure its previous pointer actually
points to that sentinel head element.
Now, again, this does break
the spirit of black box testing,
because you're no longer testing the list
from outside its abstraction barrier.
But for your sanity and
to make sure that you don't
have any of these nasty bugs that are very
hard to discover with black box testing,
given me a methods that you have access
to, we are going to allow you and even
encourage you to break that barrier, and
go in and test these pointers directly.
So good luck with your link list and
its testing.