[MUSIC]
So one philosophy that people use and
actually apply testing to their projects,
is called test driven development.
And the purpose of test driven
development is to actually
make sure that you
are testing the right thing.
A lot of times people will write
the code that they mean to, and
then they'll write the test, and
when the tests pass, they're happy and
they think they did the right thing.
But there's always the chance that the
test actually would have passed before you
made your changes, which means
you're not testing the right thing.
>> Yeah, so you wanna make sure
that you first write a test for
the soft piece of code
that you're writing.
So, first you write the test,
make sure that it fails, and
then go through and write your code.
>> Seems a little backwards, but
>> [LAUGH]
>> It's a good principle to follow,
because that way you make sure that
you're never actually fixing a totally
different bug.
>> Exactly