[MUSIC]
In this video I'll walk you through
the module four assignment, so
you know what you have to do and
how you have to do it.
As you saw at the beginning of the week,
you are gonna add the spell checking and
autocomplete functionality to your text
editor, which is going to be a lot of fun.
So, the first piece you're going to do,
we're also gonna have you do some more
benchmarking, cuz benchmarking is great.
And the whole focus on of this course is
on running time and making things fast.
So, what we'll be doing is implementing
two dictionary implementations.
So, you'll find all of
the code you need for
this assignment in the spelling package.
So, you'll want to go ahead and
open up the spelling package,
you'll see a lot of files in here.
You won't need all of these files for
this assignment.
They'll be used for this assignment and
for next weeks assignment.
So, pay attention a little bit to which
files you'll need to be working with.
In this first piece of the assignment,
you'll be working with the dictionary
ll file and the dictionary bst file.
So, here's dictionary ll,
here's dictionary bst,
and you'll see that these both implement
this interface called Dictionary, so
here's this dictionary interface.
It just has two methods, one is called
add word, add a word to the dictionary.
And the other's called is word.
And actually, sorry, it has three methods.
The other is called is word that
checks to see if a particular strain
has been added to the dictionary,
is it in the dictionary.
And then the third method is called size.
So, both of your implementations.
Oh and size by the way returns
the number of words in the dictionary.
Both of your implementations,
dictionary BST and dictionary LL, will
implement each of these three methods.
The difference between them is
the dictionary LL will use a link list
to implement the dictionary.
To hold all the words in the dictionary.
And DictionaryBST will
use a binary search tree,
which in Java is implemented as a TreeSet.
So, you'll see that we've
set you up to use a TreeSet
as the data structure that's going to
store the words in your dictionary.
So these shouldn't take you long at all to
implement, these are very straightforward.
You're just gonna use the built-in
Java classes to do this.
Once you've got those implemented,
we've provided some testers for you.
So, you'll see over here we've
got dictionary ll tester,
dictionary bst tester.
You can use our testers
to make sure you've
implemented your dictionary correctly.
So, we're trying to make this
as easy as possible for you so
that you can get to the interesting
piece of this assignment
which is that we want you to
think about What the running time
is going to be to find words in each
of the dictionary implementations.
So, put the link list implementation and
the BST implementation.
So, we want you to do that
prediction first, and
then, we've written a dictionary
benchmark class for you.
And again, you'll see it over here.
It's called DictionaryBenchmarking.java.
And if you just run that program it'll
do something similar to what you
did back in week two, comparing
the running time of the Dictionary LL,
to the Dictionary BST class this time.
So you'll see that it's
basically all written for you.
The only thing that you will want
to play around with is these
variable values up here at the top.
So, the number of trials you run,
the increment step,
the number of steps, where you start.
Play around with these What
these control is how many
words you load from the dictionary each
iteration, how many iterations you have,
what the increment between iterations is,
how many times you look for words.
Trials is the number of times you look for
the word each time, each iteration.
Playing with these numbers to
try to get some smooth data.
I'll tell you right now that
the data is going to be noisy.
It's tough to get clean data here.
And don't worry about getting it too
incredibly smooth, as long as what your
seeing is more or less matching
what you expect to see your okay.
We'll ask you about some
of that in the in the quiz
that follows this programming assignment.
So, we'll ask you what you saw, and
we'll ask you to explain what you saw.
Finally, when you're ready,
when you've got this working,
you can modify your GUI application,
that text editor.
So, you'll need to go into
our code just a little bit.
Just go into the launch class.java
files up here in application
You'll see this file launch class.
And all you're going to need to do is
go down here to get dictionary and
change it from using a hash set to
using your dictionary bst class and
then that will get things working.
All right.
So, then to submit part one
you just zip up your files,
dictionaryll.java and dictionarybst.java
and submit the zip file for grading.
And remember that the grader
takes a few minutes and
you'll see a zero out of six as your
score while the grader is working.
Now, what you can do after that, and
you can see that I'm filming this video
before the instructions are totally done,
so you'll see more instructions here,
is after you run your code,
if you have any problems at all,
we will be providing you, With a class
that actually runs all of the tests
that we ran when we graded your file.
So you can run those tests,
see what they do, and
then reason about what they did
versus what they should have done.
And we'll give you some grader feedback
that'll tell you What test was being run,
which tests passed, which tests failed.
In particular we'll tell you as
much information as possible
why those tests failed.
So, you'll be able to go to those
particular tests in the file that we give
you, see what that test is running, see
what output your program is giving, and
try to change your program so
it's giving the proper output.
And that should help you with debugging.
If you have any problems
passing our grading tests.
So, that's all there is for part one.
Oh and by the way, after part one you'll
be able to see the misspelled words
flagged in the interface once you turn
on that spelling suggestions option.
Part two, you're going to appoint
the autocomplete functionality.
And you're going to do this
by implementing a trie.
And the class you're going to implement
uses a trie as it's data structure.
And it implements two interfaces.
The autocomplete interface,
and the dictionary interface.
You're already familiar with
the dictionary interface.
But you might want to take just a minute
to look at the autocomplete interface,
which is right here.
So, you can see that it
just has one method.
It's called predictCompletions.
It takes a prefix and
the number of completions that you want.
And it returns a list
of those completions.
And there are some specifics about
what completions you need to return.
Those are given over here in
the assignment instructions.
So, then your goal is simply to implement
the methods in the auto complete
dictionary trie class.
So, going over here, here's the starter
code for the auto complete dictionary trie,
and you'll notice that several methods
are missing, so add what is missing.
To implement addword,
you need to add a new word to the trie, so
you'll be implementing a trie
data structure Structure here.
Now, you're not gonna implement
this completely from scratch,
because if you go over here to TrieNode,
you will
see that we've given you an implementation
of a node in the trie structure.
And that's described a little
bit in the videos for
this week, and you can look at it here.
But basically, the idea is that each
link to the next level is a hash map.
That links the character that takes
you to the next level's node, and
then the node that is there.
Each node is also gonna keep track
of the text up to that point, and
as I mentioned in the video,
you could omit this for
space, but you don't have to and it makes
it a lot easier if you keep it in there.
So, we suggest keeping it in Been there.
And then you have this Boolean flag
whether or not this node is a word or not.
So, this is just the implementation that
I talked to you about in the video and
we're providing this for you.
And you can look at some of the methods
that we provide, they're gonna be really
useful in doing your auto complete
dictionary trie-implementation.
So, using these methods,
you will go ahead and
implement all of the missing method That's
here in the auto complete dictionary trie.
So, there's the add word method,
that has to build out the trie just a bit.
And we noticed this other thing that we're
converting all the strings are lower case,
as you insert them.
And that's just to make this
implementation slightly easier.
So everything in the dictionary,
everything you're going
to compare it against,
it's always lower case,
you have to do that conversion.
Here's the method that
returns the size of the trie.
Now, notice this isn't the same as
the number of nodes in the trie,
this is the number of
words in the dictionary.
So it's not actually the size of the trie
at all, it's the size of the dictionary.
In terms of the number of words.
That's from the dictionary interface.
And then we have the isword
method down here.
And that returns whether a string
is a word that's in this And so
you'll need to use the algorithm that I
explained in the video for tracing down
the trie as character by character
in the string and making sure that
the last node that you land on is actually
in the trie, and it's marked as a word.
Finally, the last thing that
you're gonna implement for
this part is the predict
completions method.
The predict completions method,
you've got, we've got the algorithm right
here, but basically it's two pieces.
First, you use a similar
methodology that you used for
is word to trace down and find the stem,
or the prefix in the trie.
So, you're going to find that stem or
prefix in the trie, and
if the prefix does not appear in the trie
then you just return an empty list because
there's no way to predict completions
from this non-existent prefix.
But once you find the stem or
the prefix then you're gonna
perform a breath first search.
As Leo described in his videos this week.
To generate all the completions.
And here we're giving you
the algorithm for the spec for search,
to make things a little bit earlier.
So you create a que, and
a que is really just a link list.
It's a link list where you add notes
on one end and take them off the other.
So, you add things to the back and
take things off from the front.
And link list already, by default,
will Give you this behavior.
Then you'll create a list
of completions to return,
that list of completions is initially
empty, and while your queue is not empty
and you don't have enough completions you
will remove the first node from the queue.
If it's a word,
you add it's completions list and
then you'll add all of its child
nodes to the back of the queue.
And you'll just keep doing this until
you've generated enough completions or
you run out of completions.
[INAUDIBLE] In the dictionary,
and that's it.
So that's all you need to do for
the implementation.
And it's described in a lot of detail,
here.
So, I encourage you to read
this assignment carefully.
Because it gives you some.
Specific instructions about how
you need to return words in
increasing length order.
So, if I ask for four completions,
I need the four shortest
completions from a particular prefix or
stem, and not a longer completion.
We have a tester for you, we have this
class called AutoCompleteDictionaryTrie
tester, you're welcome to run that to test
your methods, you may need to add to it to
make sure that it's complete, and
when you're ready, you just upload your
AutoCompleteDictionaryTrie.java file and
again.
You can run, again I'm doing this before
this file is completely finalized,
before the instructions are completely
finalized, but again you'll be able to see
the exact tests that we run
in a file that we provide and
we'll have the name of that file in these
instructions by the time we launch.
Part 3 is purely optional.
So, we've got a note to our beta testers
that we want them to do it, but for you,
it’s up to you.
And what part three is basically,
is you’ll notice that in
part two we ignored case.
So we put everything in
the dictionary in lower case.
Everything in the autocomplete
dictionary in lower case.
But for part three it would be
more interesting if we could
Do spelling correction and spelling
suggestion based on case, as well.
So, if a proper noun has a lower case
letter to begin with, it's not allowed.
But if it's an upper case
letter then it's okay.
And it turns out that our dictionary text
file already has all the proper case
incorporated into it.
So, words appear in the dictionary
text file in their proper case.
So, the challenge in Part 3 is to
expand on your implementation for
Part 2 in a new file.
Don't mess up your implementation from
Part 2 because we're gonna grade it
as it is.
But make a new file that implements
a dictionary autocomplete
that actually takes case into account.
So, if you're working on this part,
we assume that you're really well on your
way, you don't need much guidance, so
we're leaving it fairly open-ended.
And we hope that you have a lot of fun,
and we you encourage to discuss your
implementation with other
learners in the forums.