If you think back to the start of
this course, you learned a little bit
about cryptography and
implemented the Caesar cipher.
Now you're going to learn a bit about
the Vigenere Cipher, which historically
is quite important, as it was thought to
be unbreakable for hundreds of years.
However, as you're going to see and
do, the cipher is quite easy
to break with the computer.
Now, let's see how this cipher works.
The key in Vigenere was
classically a word.
For example,
here we picked dice as our key.
You write down the word repeatedly
to match the message length.
Each letter represents a number for
how much to shift by, so
dice means shift by 3,
8, 2, and 4, repeatedly.
In a Java program,
it would be quite convenient to
represent the key as an array of ints.
Now to encrypt, you shift each letter
by the amount written under it,
much like you in a Caesar cipher, but each
letter gets shifted by a different amount.
The first letter is M,
which has 3 added to it, so you get P.
The second letter is E,
which has 8 added to it, so you get M.
Then you repeat this process
across the entire message.
As we did for Cesar, we'll have to
skip anything that's not a letter.
Notice that conceptually, this cipher
is like four different Cesar cyphers.
One with a shift of three, shown in blue.
One with a shift of eight, shown in red.
Another with a shift of two,
shown in green.
And a fourth with a shift of four,
shown in purple.
This similarity means that a programmer
who has already written an implementation
of Caesar cipher could make use of it
to help implement a Vigenere Cipher.
In fact, you could make an array
of Caesar cipher objects,
one with each shift specified in the key
and use them for your encryption.
If you did something like this,
you could use the mod operator to wrap
a count into the pattern,
0,1,2,3, 0,1,2,3.
For this mini-project,
we're going to give you the code for
a Vigenere cipher and you are going
to write the code to break it.
Your goal is to take messages that
we have encrypted with Vigenere and
find the decrypted message
without knowing the key we used.
You will start with breaking a message
that you know is in English,
and then expand your program so
that you can try to break encryption
in a variety of languages.