Hi.
The first step of your Vigenere breaker
is gonna be to write code which
only handles the case when
you know the key length and
are working with a single
language like English.
Whenever you're developing software,
it's a great idea to implement one feature
first to test it thoroughly before you
build more features into your program and
that's exactly what we're
gonna be doing here.
Remember that the vigenere cypher
acts like several Caesar cyphers for
different slices of the message.
Here you see a message which was encrypted
with a vigenere cypher whose key length
is four.
We've colored the letters based on
the part of the key that was used.
If you take only the blue letters,
you can use the Caesar cipher
cracker that you wrote previously
to find that part of the key.
These letters are basically just a message
encrypted with a Caesar cipher but
they're spread out through
the total message.
Then you can do the same thing with the
red letters to crack that part of the key
and similarly for the green and
the purple letters.
This is the conceptual idea
of how to break Vigenere.
If you know the key length,
you slice the string up, and
you break each slice
using a Caesar cipher.
So, what should you
write to implement this?
The first method you'd want
to write is slice string.
Which takes three parameters,
the message to slice up,
which slice you want and
the total number of slices.
For example, if you call this method with
four total slices and which slice equals
zero, you would get the blue letters
put together into a string like this.
Similarly, whichSlice = 1 would get
the red letters as you see here.
The new line character counts
as a string and whichSlice = 2,
you'll get the green letters
in the string and finally,
whichSlice = 3 would give
you the purple letters.
Again, you see the new line character.
We have some advice for
you to help you write sliceString.
First, remember the StringBuilder
class you learned about earlier.
It would be useful as you build up
the resulting string to return.
You'll want to append characters
to a StringBuilder object.
Second, you will likely want to
make use of counting for loops.
In ways that are slightly
different than you've seen before.
You've typically had four loops start at
zero but they can start at any number.
Here you see an example of a counting
four loop that starts at four.
Of course, you could use a variable or
a parameter to indicate
where you start counting.
That will prove quite
useful in this method.
You can also have counting for loops
that count by something other than one.
This loop counts by seven so, it would
print the values of four, 11, 18, and 25.
Of course, you can count by a variable or
a parameter instead of
the constant seven you see here.
That may be very useful
as you write sliceString.
Once you've written slice string, you will
want to write the method try key length.
This method finds the visionary key for
an encrypted message, assuming the key
length is klength the parameter.
It also takes a parameter if the most
common character in the language
this parameter is for later.
For right now, you'll just pass it e.
When you write this method,
you'll want to make use of sliceString
that we just discussed, and you'll
want to use the CaesarCracker class.
We've provided you with
a version of CaesarCracker
that's similar to the one you wrote
before, but with a few changes.
First, we separated out
the code that finds the key
from the code that decrypts the message
and second, we've made a constructor
which takes the most common letter in
the language that you're working with.
In this part of your program, you'll
just pass the most common parameter.
This method should return an int array.
Of length keylength, which holds each
of the shifts that the CeasarCracker
found for each slice of the message.
After you've written trykeylength,
you have one more method to write for
this part of your program, breakVigenere.
This is the method you'll
want to call from BlueJ.
It will set everything up and
will call the method tryKeyLength.
You'll want to use a FileResource object
to read in the file that
you want to decrypt.
FileResource has a useful method,
asString,
which reads the entire file
into a string for you.
Once you've read the entire file,
you'll want to call tryKeyLength.
Passing the message you just read.
The keyLength which is given
to you at this stage and
the letter e which is
the most common letter.
Trykeylength will return
the key as an array of ints.
You'll simply pass this to
the constructor VigenereCipher and
you'll make use of it's .decrypt method
to decrypt the encrypted message.
Finally you'll print out the result,
voila, you are done.