Okay, great, now you have cracked
Vigenere for English messages of
unknown key length, but what if
the messages were in other languages?
What if you did not know the language?
Well, you can use the same technique and
just try each language.
For each potential language, you would
need a list of words in that language and
to know the most common character,
which is not E for all languages.
Then you can try breaking the cipher for
each language.
You would use the same code you
already wrote to find the key length
that gives you the most real
words in each language.
This gives you the best choice for
that particular language.
Then you just see which language
results in the most real words.
That is, which language's best
decryption is best overall?
To do this, you're going to read
the words in for each language.
You can make use of the readDictionary
method that you already wrote.
As you read each dictionary,
you will want to put it into a hash map,
whose keys are strings and
whose values are hash sets of strings.
In particular,
the key is the name of the language and
the value is the dictionary that
you read in with read dictionary.
Such a hash map would
conceptually look like this here.
Here you have a table where the keys
are the names of languages.
The values are then the sets
of words in each language.
You might think that this
type looks a little complex.
You have multiple sets of angle
brackets nested together.
However, it is a great example of
an important programming principle.
Do you remember the idea of composition?
If you took our course
Programming in the Web for
Beginners, you learned about
it in the context of HTML.
The idea that programming languages
allow you to put small pieces together
to make larger pieces, and that they obey
the same rules when you put them together.
This principle lets you make and
understand large and complex things.
In this case you can understand
this complicated looking type
by understanding the pieces.
So what exactly do you need to make
your Vigenere breaker work for
unknown languages?
You need to write two new methods, one
that counts the most common character and
hash set of strings, and
one that tries the different languages.
You also need to modify two old methods,
the break Vigenere method,
which is what you run from BlueJ,
and the breakForLanguage method.
You need to write the mostCommonCharIn
method to account for
the fact that E is not the most
common letter in all languages.
So you will count the frequency of
each letter in the HashSet of strings
which is the list of words for
that language.
You have seen and done many problems with
counting how often you find something, and
figuring out which of
something occurs most often.
So hopefully, you are getting
proficient in these skills by now.
The other new method we'll try
each language in that keySet
of the HashMap language.
You will want to use breakForLanguage
to do the work of trying to break
that one particular language.
You will want to use .get,
to get the word list out of the HashMap
to pass into breakForLanguage.
You will then want to see how
many words you ended up with
in the string that
breakForLanguage returns.
Fortunately, we already wrote
a method that does that.
You will then want to pick the best
language, the one with the most words, and
its decryption.
Print them out so
that you know what your program found.
You will want to make a few
changes to breakVigenere(),
the method that you call from BlueJ.
Instead of just reading
one language's word list,
you'll want to read many of them.
The other change is that you will want
this method to call breakForAllLangs
instead of breakForLanguage, so
that it tries all of
the languages that you read in.
You will also want to make one
small change to breakForLanguage.
Up to now, you have just passed
an E as the most common letter.
However, now you will want to
use the mostCommonCharIn method
that you just wrote to find the most
common letter in the word list, and
pass that into try key links.
So, now that you know the plan,
it's time for
you to devise your algorithms and
write your code.