Hello.
We'll introduce the class character,
which you can use to determine
properties of character values in Java.
The type char is a primitive type,
like int, boolean, and double.
Some people pronounce it char,
some people pronounce it car,
and some people say care.
But everyone says the word
character the same way, so
I typically use the careful pronunciation.
Char values are specified
with single quotes.
For example, you can see quote A quote and
quote 1 quote.
End quote, space quote here.
These are character values.
The value "a" is a string value.
It's usually much easier to write the code
than to say all these quote values.
The character class has several
methods you can use in writing code.
You may remember the methods
Integer.Parseint and Double.ParseDouble.
These are methods of the classes
Integer and Double, respectively.
The method Character.toLowercase returns
a lowercase equivalent to its argument.
For example,
this call will return a lowercase g,
since an uppercase G is the argument
to Character.toLowerCase.
If you pass a character that
is already in lowercase,
the same value will be returned.
The table shows Boolean value
functions like, isLowerCase and
isDigit, as well as conversion functions
like toLowerCase and toUpperCase.
Using the Java documentation, we'll show
you more Boolean and conversion methods.
Have fun building character,
and writing code.
We have the CharacterDemo class here
in BlueJ, and we've got two methods
that I'm going to run through and
illustrate, and I'll add one very quickly.
This first method, digitTest, creates a
test string that has uppercase characters,
lowercase characters,
digits, and punctuation.
Move through every
character of the string and
calls the character.isDigit method,
a Boolean method.
And the Character.isAlphabetic method,
another Boolean method.
So, let's run through digitTest,
and see what it does.
I'm going to create a new object on
my work bench, by right-clicking.
And then I'm going to run the digitTest
method by right-clicking on that.
And we can see here pretty clearly that A,
B, C, uppercase characters,
little a, little b, little c,
those are all alphabetic characters.
And then the digits are labeled
as digit characters.
Notice that no punctuation was printed,
so that when I go back to my editor,
we can see that the uppercase
characters were all alphabetic.
The characters that look like
digits were all labeled as digits.
And the punctuation wasn't any character
in that it didn't have the label,
alphabetic and
it didn't have the label, digit.
Just want to illustrate
one quick thing here.
I can also say if ch is
equal to the character #,
then I can print a message that,
It's a hashtag.
Highly enlightening.
And now if I compile this program,
it compiled without any errors.
And I'll make another object.
I'll invoke the digitTest method.
And we can see that lo and
behold, # is a hashtag.
That's just a reminder that for
characters we use single quotes
to differentiate the values.
Whereas strings use double quotes.
We can see that here,
where I've created another string
test in the method conversionTest.
I've created a similar string
with uppercase characters,
lowercase characters,
digits and some punctuation.
I'm going to loop through by
using the string charAt method.
To store a character variable ch.
I'm creating an uch variable and
an lch variable, both of type char.
I'm creating them calling
Character.toUpperCase which will return
an uppercase character, and
Character.toLowerCase that will
return a lowercase equivalent.
Remember that converting
a digit to upper or
lowercase doesn't change the digit at all.
And if a character is already lowercase,
converting it to lowercase
leaves it alone.
So, running that method, I will right
click on my class and call conversionTest.
We can see that I get the characters
in my string on the left column.
The function that you got
by calling toUppercase and
the results that you get
by calling toLowercase.
So I get character, uppercase, lowercase.
You can see that in each column, I have
all uppercase characters or digits and
punctuation.
All lowercase characters
weren't considered punctuation.
And as one quick review of that code,
to remind you of where that came from,
you can see that I called toUppercase,
toLowercase, and then printed them
as the character, the uppercase
version and the lowercase version.
Using the Java documentation for
characters will help a lot
in making your program run smoothly,
when you're using character values.
Have fun building more character
than you did last time.