Welcome back.
Now you have all the concepts required
to implement a Caesar Cipher.
So let's get started
developing the algorithm.
As always,
you should start with step one, working
an instance of the problem yourself.
Even though we have seen some
instances worked, it is good to work
a small instance, so you can write
everything down and think it through.
Let's encrypt the message I AM, which is
really I, space, A-M with a key of 17,
meaning you will shift each letter
17 positions through the alphabet.
You might want to start by
writing down the alphabet, and
then writing down the alphabet shifted
by 17 characters underneath it.
For example, A has R beneath it,
where R is 17 characters to the right
of A in the original alphabet.
Next you would go through and
replace each character in the message
with the appropriate letter
from the shifted alphabet.
When you are done you have
the encrypted message Z RD.
Great, you have finished Step 1..
Now it is time to do Step 2, and
write down exactly what you just did.
The first thing you did was
write down the alphabet.
Then you computed the shifted alphabet.
The third thing you did was to look
at the 0th letter of the message.
Don't forget, when you index into
sequences such as strings and
string builders,
the first element is at index zero.
That letter was I, so
you looked in the alphabet to find I,
then you found the letter in the shifted
alphabet at the same position which was Z.
So, you replace the zero
character of the message with Z.
Next, you look at the first letter of the
message which is a space If you look for
space in the alphabet,
you would not find it, so
you would not change the character
at index one of the message.
Next, the second character is an A, for
which you perform a very similar process
as you did for the 0th character,
and end up changing it to R.
Finally, you do the same thing for
the third character which is
an M that you turned into a D.
Now that you have thought through
all of that, you have a list of
the 17 things you did for this particular
message, and this particular key.
However, there's one more thing that is
good to note here before you proceed.
Notice that your algorithm calls for
replacing characters in the message.
If your message is a string,
you cannot do that.
As you recently learned, strings are
immutable, meaning you cannot change them.
If you recognize this issue now you can
adjust your algorithm to reflect the fact
that you want to work
with a string builder.
Here we've added a step at the start
to create a string builder
from the string message.
And then we updated the algorithm
to work on the string builder.
If you do not realize
you need to do this now,
you would figure it out at a later step.
But the earlier you can figure it out,
everything you need to do, the better.
Looking at this algorithm you can see that
the first few steps are an initial setup,
before you begin performing repetitive
steps for each letter in the message.
If you focus on the steps after
the initial set-up, you can see that you
are doing almost, but not quite the same
thing for each character n the message.
One significant difference is what
you decide to do based on whether or
not you find the letter in the alphabet.
Replacing the current
character if you find it.
Or doing nothing if you do not.
If you look at the steps for one
particular character where the letter is
in the alphabet, you will notice
that the character you looked for
in the alphabet is the current
character in the string.
And that the letter you used to
replace the current character
is what you found in the same
position in the shifted alphabet.
Now that you have thought
this all through,
you can write down,
a much more general algorithm.
Notice that the step number two
here requires a little thought, and
a couple of statements.
But you've already seen how to do it.
When you are looking for patterns,
you should examine any constants,
such as zero here, and
ask if you always use that constant.
Or if you need to look for
a more general pattern.
Here you always want to start from zero.
What about three?
Do you always want to
stop counting at three?
No.
How high you count depends on
the length of the message.
Here we've written that you want to
count to the length of encrypted.
But noted that you want to count to less
than it, not less than or equal to it.
In our example, encrypted was four,
and you only want to count to three.
Now it's time to test out the steps.
Pause the video now and try to encrypt
the message, a space bat with a key of 19.
Did you catch the subtle
problem with this algorithm?
Even though it computed
everything you wanted,
we never said what the final answer is.
You want to be sure to
explicitly say this so
that you know what to return from your
method when you translate the code.
Your answer is the string inside of
the string builder you called encrypted.
Now that you have fixed this detail
of your algorithm you are ready to
turn it into Java code.
Thank you.