Okay, now that you've developed
the algorithm for Caesar Cipher,
it's time to turn it into code.
We've started here with the CaesarCipher
class, which has an encrypt method which
takes the input to encrypt, and an integer
for the key to use to encrypt it.
I've written here the comments,
with the pseudo code that we
just developed in our algorithm.
And I've gone ahead and
written the first two lines of code.
The first step is to make a new
StringBuilder with the input.
And call it encrypted.
And the second is to write down
the alphabet, which is a string.
The next thing is to compute
the shifted alphabet.
So we're going to make a string,
shiftedAlphabet.
And remember, we saw in previous videos,
that we can use substring to do that.
lphabet.substring(key) +,
that's what plus means for strings,
alphabet.substring(0,key).
That will slice the alphabet
up into two pieces and
can concatenate them back together to
give us the shifted alphabet we want.
Now we can count from zero to being
less than the length of encrypted.
And we want to call each
number that we count i.
So this is going to be a counting for
loop, for
( int i = 0 i < encrypted.length(),
the length of encrypted, i++).
And what do we want to do?
Well, we want to look at the ith
character, and call it currChar.
char currChar = encrypted.charAt(i).
Then we want to find the index
of currChar in the alphabet.
int idx, we said over here call it idx,
= alphabet.indexOf( currChar), and
then we want to see if
that's in the alphabet.
As you've seen before, indexOf will return
a negative one if something is not there
and some other number if it is.
So if would not be there if idx is index,
or is negative one.
We want != -1 to mean it is there.
Now we want the idxth
char of shifted alphabet,
and we want to call that newChar
= shiftedAlphabet.charAt(idx).
And now I want to replace
the ith character of
encrypted with newChar so
encrypted.setCharAt and
then I want the ith
character to be newChar.
That's everything I want to do inside
of that if, otherwise, do nothing.
I don't need to write an alt if I
don't want to do anything otherwise.
This curly braces closes my counting for
loop, and at the end here,
I said I want my answer, so
I want to return something,
to be this string inside of encrypted,
so encrypted.toString.
I'm gonna compile that,
it says no syntax errors.
And I've written here already
this method testCaesar,
which is going to make a new file
resource, so it'll prompt us for a file.
Read it all in is a string encrypt it.
It will print out the encrypted message,
and then it will also decrypt it and print
out the decrypted message, because if we
just saw a jumble of random characters,
we wouldn't really be able
to tell if we did it right.
But being able to tell that
we got the original back
makes us more confident that
what we did was correct.
I'm gonna go over here to BlueJ.
I'm gonna say new CaesarCipher.
I'm gonna say Test Caesar, and
it's gonna prompt me for a file.
And I have here this message in
a file called message1.txt that says,
free cake in the conference room.
Maybe I want to send this to
Robert without Owen seeing it and
being able to get all the cake, and
so I'm gonna choose message1.txt.
And we can see the encrypted message here,
WIVV, etc., etc.
It's been made more difficult to read.
And then we can see down here,
where it decrypted it correctly.
So I'd be a little more confident in this.
I'd want to go through and
check by hand that this actually came
out with the correct key before I'd
be completely certain that this
test case worked correctly.