Now, we've written and
tested our CaesarCipher class.
We tested it out on one message and
it looked like it worked.
Does this mean we can be
sure our code is correct?
Of course not.
Remember, when you're testing software
each test case makes you more confident
in your code, but no number of tests can
guarantee that your code is correct.
You want more and
more tests to be more and
more confident and
one test case generally isn't enough.
So, here I have a different method.
Dear Owen,
no matter what you may have heard,
thee's no cake in the conference room.
The cake is a lie.
Please keep working on Coursera videos.
So I wanna encrypt this, and
send an encrypted message to Owen.
To fend him off from the cake in case
he intercepted my message to Robert.
I'm going to use my test Caesar.
And now I'm going to do message2.txt.
And when I look to at this, I'm going to
see that the D in dear turned into a U.
That's good.
But then e, a, and r were left the same.
Then the O in Owen turned into an F.
But then w, e, n were all left the same.
And in fact, most of this is unchanged.
So my code isn't quite right.
If I look back at it, I'm gonna see
that it's only going to work with
capital letters and
not with lower case letters.
This was the problem in
our first test case.
It only had capital letters.
It didn't have lower case letters, so we
didn't really test all the cases enough.
We're gonna leave this to you to fix.
There are a couple of different
ways you can do it, and
we hope you can figure one of them out.
So good luck, and
happy fixing of your code.