Let us wrap up this lesson
where you learned a lot.
First, you learned a bit about
the historical, as well as,
modern importance of cryptography.
Then you learned some more concepts
about strings, as well as,
how to use a StringBuilder to
efficiently construct a string.
Then you learned about counting for
loops, adding another important tool
to your programming repertoire.
Finally, you implemented
the Caesar Cipher, a classical cipher,
dating back thousands of years.
As you will learn in the next lesson, this
cipher is not secure by modern standards,
but it is a good starting point to
understand the ideas of cryptography.