[MUSIC]
All right, in this last lesson, we're
going to look at the very last part of
the project, where you're going to add the
ability to suggest words to the user for
misspelled words that they typed.
And this part of the project is really
motivated by our societal dependence
on spellcheckers these days.
You've already got the ability to add
into your project, the ability to check
whether a particular string is a word,
and that's essential these days.
When I'm typing up a document,
I rely on that underlined red to say, oh,
I mistyped that word,
that's not actually how you spell it.
But we're gonna take that a step further.
So not only are you going to be able to
identify misspelled words, but you'll
be able to give the user some suggestions
on how to correct their spelling.
So by the end of this video,
you'll be able to describe the basics of
an algorithm to do those
spelling suggestions.
And it turns out this algorithm
isn't really that complicated.
And in the next video, we'll look at
the details of how to implement it.
So let's start by thinking
about what we need to do.
So let's say I have this
piece text of here,
spell correction,
only I've misspelled the first word.
I've spelled it speel instead of spell.
And the question is, how can I generate
possible suggestions of valid words
that are good suggestions for
replacements for that speel word?
Well we want to generate a set
of words that is somehow close
to the word that I typed.
Because I probably typed
the word mostly correctly, but
I just made a small error here.
So I don't wanna give the user suggestions
of all the words in the English language,
that would be way too many.
I want to start by suggesting words
that are pretty close to the thing I
actually typed.
So now the question is, how can we
precisely define what it means for
one string to be close to another string?
What we're going to do is take
the definition where we say
that a string is close to another string
if it's altered as little as possible.
And what do we mean by altered?
Well we're gonna think about
ways we can alter a word to be one
step away from another string.
We're altering a string to be
a step away from another string
by performing one of three
transformations on that string.
The first transformation we can perform on
that string is we can do a substitution.
And all of these are of
a single character.
So we can choose any character
in that original string speel,
and we can choose to change
it to any other character.
So, for example, I could produce
the strings apeel, sbeel, spell,
speak just by changing one character from
my original speel to a new character.
Now there are going to be many
more strings that I can produce
via the substitution method.
I'm just showing you
a few here as examples.
The next transformation I
can apply is an insertion.
So I can take at any
position in this word,
in this original string,
either before the first character, or
between any of the characters,
or after the last character.
I can insert any of the characters in
the alphabet to produce new strings.
So that could produce new
strings like bspeel or
sipeel, and the strings you can see there.
Now notice that none of these are words,
but these are just possible strings I
can produce that are one step
away form my original string.
The last way I'm going to think about
transforming my original string
is via deletions.
So I can take any of the letters in my
original string, and I can remove it.
And that will give me a list of
possible strings that are one away,
still, from my original string.
Notice that there are in this case only
in this case five of those, because there
are only five characters I can delete,
and two of them end up being the same.
So if I delete either of the e's,
it will give me the same S-P-E-L
possible string that's one step away.
So this now lends itself to a simple
spell suggestion algorithm.
What I'm gonna do is I'll take
my original misspelled word, and
then I'll generate all the possible
strings that are one transformation away
from that original misspelled word.
Then from that list, I will get rid
of everything that's not a word.
And I'll be left with a set of words
that are one transformation away
from the original string
that the user typed.
And these are words that are close
to what the user originally typed.
So here I've just drawn that same
algorithm with a different visualization
of what I'm doing here.
So up at the top you see the original
word that was typed, and
then down on the next layer you see all
the strings that can be produced, or
at least a subset of the strings.
There's a dot dot dot indicating that this
layer is going to go on, and on, and on,
much larger than what you see here,
that are one transformation away from
that original string that was typed.
So then the question becomes,
well, what if that's enough?
What if that doesn't produce any words, or
doesn't produce enough options for
the user?
What should I do?
We can just extend this
to go two steps away.
So now instead of generating
the next layer down,
I can take each word
in that next layer and
apply the same set of transformations
to go one step away from those words.
So here I'm showing you the expansion
of just one of the strings
in that first layer expanded out to some
of the strings in the next layer down.
Then from all of those strings,
in the first layer and
the second layer, I can now get rid
of everything that's not a word,
preserve the things that are words,
and those are my spelling suggestions.
Okay, but what if that's still not enough?
How deep should I go?
I could keep going, and going, and
going, and build a big, huge tree.
But at some level, I need to decide what
is enough words to offer to the user.
So this is kind of a basic overview.
And in the next video, we'll get into
details like how do we actually manage
when to stop looking for
words to suggest to the user.