[MUSIC]
All right, in that last video you saw the
idea behind how we're going to generate
spelling suggestions for misspelled words.
In this video we'll get into a little bit
more details of the algorithm, and this
will help you with your implementation for
part of the project in this module.
So by the end of this video you'll be able
to describe the details of the algorithm
that your gonna to implement in order
to generate these spelling suggestions.
So here is the algorithm, in a little
bit more detail than you saw last time.
It's actually going to generate
the list of suggested words for
a misspelled word that the user types.
And I'm gonna walk you through
this algorithm step by step.
What you can see, at the top,
is the algorithm and
then at the bottom I'm going to
maintain two data structures.
A queue, which Leo has talked to you
about before, in which you've used
in the auto completion component of
the assignment in the last module.
And then the list of suggestions
that you ultimately the functions
gonna return back as suggestions for
this misspelled word.
And you'll see how those get filled
in as the algorithm progresses.
So, first step in the algorithm.
I'm going to take that misspelled word,
that string and
I'm going to add it to my queue.
Then, I'm going to enter a loop.
So, this loop says, while I don't have
enough suggestions, right now I have none,
so I definitely don't have enough.
And my queue still has more
elements in it, it's not empty,
I'll proceed to the body of the loop.
So in the body of the loop,
the first thing we do, is we take
that first string off of the queue.
So in this case,
it's my original misspelled word, speel.
So I'll take that off of the queue, and
I'll set it aside because
I'm gonna work with it.
So you can see it off to the side there.
Then I'm going to generate all of
the strings that are one step away
from that thing I removed from my
queue as we saw in the last video.
So, all of the strings that have
produced with substitutions, insertions,
or deletions.
And I'll put those into the queue.
Then what I'll do,
is I'll take, of those, the things
that actually represent real words.
And I'll add them to my
list of suggestions.
Then I'm going to go back
to the top of the loop and
check, am I done, do I have enough
suggestions, and is my queue empty?
Well my queue is not empty,
and let's say I don't have enough
suggestions yet, I want to keep going.
So, what do I do?
I repeat the process.
I go into the loop.
I remove the first string from the queue.
I set it aside.
It's going to be a special word that
I'm going to use in the next few steps.
And then I'll generate all
the strings that are one step away
from that new word that I've removed, and
I'll add those to the queue at the end.
From there, I just repeat the process
of what I did originally.
From that new list of words I generated,
or strings I generated, I take the ones
that are actually words, and I move them
down into the suggestions list, and so on.
And this process is just going to repeat,
taking new words off the queue,
generating potential words to explore.
And adding the real words we found
to the list of spelling suggestions.
When I've got enough suggestions,
I'll return that list of suggestions.
That's really it.
That's the algorithm that you're
going to be implementing.
See, I told you,
it's not really that complicated.
There is one optimization that you can do.
You may have noticed that in this process
of doing this generation of possible
words, we're gonna see some repeats.
So for example, from apeel,
we can get right back to speel,
which was the original
misspelled word we started with.
So, an optimization you can do,
is you can keep track of the words or
strings you've already generated and
not revisit those strings,
so don't add them back into the queue.
You have to be a little bit careful about
how you implement this optimization,
because if you don't implement it well,
you could end up doing more work to
optimize than you would do if you just let
those strings exist in the queue again.
And the last thing that we need to think
about is, now that we have this list of
suggestions, in what order should
we present these to the user?
Now this is kind of a subtle question and
one that we're not going to
ask you to explore for
the required part of the project but
that you can explore in
extension if you're interested.
So, if you were to turn these words in
the order that they were to appear in
the suggestions list, what order they're
going to be in, is just ordered from
close to the original word typed, to
farther away to the original word typed.
In terms of those number
of transformations applied.
Now that may be the right thing to do, but
you also might want to
get a little bit smarter.
Because some of those words are going to
be more likely to appear in the English
language than others.
So you might want to do something like,
take the more commonly occurring words and
move them to the front
of the suggestions list.
That's something you could explore doing.
Another thing you might
want to think about is,
some transformations
are more likely than others.
For example,
it's pretty likely that you accidentally
type two letters in the reverse order.
Well, in order to
generate that suggestion,
you would need to go two steps
away from your original word because
you need to transform both
of the transpose letters.
But you may decide that that
transposition is actually
more likely to occur than one
of your one step away words.
So you might decide to move that sort of
transformation up in the list as well.
So those are just two ideas for
optimizations on the list of spelling
suggestions that you could explore.
And those kinds of optimizations
are some of the things that are built in
to real world spell checkers and
spell suggesters.
So with this in mind, you can
implement this piece of the project.
And next, we'll talk about the very
last piece of the project, which is
to implement, to extend on these ideas,
to find paths between two different words.