[MUSIC]
All right, in this video we're gonna talk
about something called edit distance, and
also talk about the very last piece
of your programming assignment,
which is to find the path between
two words in the English language.
So by the end of this video,
you'll be able to define
the notion of edit distance.
You'll be able to describe a naive
algorithm, very naive, for
solving the edit distance problem, and
you'll also be able to talk about how
pruning can help restrict
the size of a search space, and
make problems, big problems,
more manageable.
So let's start off with a little game and
this is game you'll be implementing
the solution for
in your programming assignment.
And the game is to take any two
words in the English language and
find a path between those words
such that each step in the path
only does one transformation,
either a substitution.
A, an insertion or deletion like we
talked about in the previous videos, and
it produces a word that's also
valid in the English language.
So for example, to get from spell to mine,
I could take the e in spell and
replace it with an i, to get me spill,
I could then drop the first
s to give me pill take that last l and
turn it into an e to get pile.
Take that l and
turn it into an n to get pine.
And then, take the p and
turn it into an m and I've got mine.
So in this case, I've got five steps that
it took me to get from spell to mine.
Now this game is actually an illustration
of a more general problem
called the edit distance problem.
Our spelling error word path game is
a restricted version of this problem
because the general edit distance
between two sequences is just the number
of transformations you have to make
to turn one sequence of characters or
things into another sequence
of characters or things.
And you don't actually necessarily care
about whether those intermediate strings
are valid words.
So this tree illustrates the notion
of edit distance very nicely.
So at the first layer in this tree,
you can see all the words that are just
one transformation away
from my original word.
They're at a distance one.
The next layer in the tree shows me all
the strings that are edit distance two
away from the original word,
and so on and so forth.
So you can see that you can actually
solve the general edit distance problem
by just building out this tree,
layer by layer.
Looking for the word that you're
trying to transform into.
So I start with my
original word at the top.
I generate layer by layer
by layer in this tree,
until I find the word that
I'm actually looking for.
And then I have a nice path as well
as a distance from my original word
down to the word that I'm looking for.
This is a very naive implementation, and
we'll talk about limitations of
that solution in a little bit.
But before we go on, I wanna say that
edit distance problem is actually
a general problem used in a number of
fields, not just in spelling suggestions.
So it's used in computational biology.
For example, when you're comparing two
DNA sequences to try to figure out
how far apart are those
two DNA sequences really?
It's also used in natural
language processing.
For example,
to align two different sentences
to see how close they really are.
So it has a number of applications
beyond what we're using it for here.
Your assignment will just introduce you
to the idea then to an algorithm for
solving it.
This tree based structure illustrates
a general problem solving strategy
that involves exhaustively searching
a space looking for a solution.
So this is a strategy that's used in a lot
of artificial intelligence problems,
where again the goal is to just
really search an entire problem space
until you find a particular solution.
So each layer in the tree basically
transforms the state of the problem into
a slightly different state, until you've
found the state that is the solution.
So in this case, our original
state was our original word, and
our solution is going to be the word
that we're looking to transform into.
Then we can get a path to the solution by
following the path to the tree from start
to solution.
However, one problem that comes up
with building these trees to do these
exhaustive searches,
is that they tend to get really large.
And we're going to do a little bit of
analysis to kind of get a ballpark
estimate of how big does this tree get.
So let's think about that
first layer down in the tree.
How many strings do we produce that
are just one away from my original word.
If that original word
has k characters in it.
In this case k equals five.
Well in order to reason about that,
we need to think about the number of
strings that are produced via
substitutions, via insertions, and
via deletions, and
just add those all together.
So thinking about substitutions,
we have k different characters in
my string that we can substitute.
And there are 25 other characters that we
could put in in place of the character
that's already there.
So we have 25 times k strings that
are produced via substitution.
Moving on to insertion.
We actually have k plus 1 locations in the
string where we can insert a character.
We can insert before
the beginning of the string,
between any of the characters of the
string, and then after the last character.
So that's k plus 1.
And we can insert any of the 26
characters that we have available to us.
So that's going to be 26 times k+1,
stings that are produced via insertion.
Finally, we get to deletions.
Deletions are much smaller class, because
we can only delete each character once.
So in this case,
we could delete five characters.
But in general, we can delete k
characters, leading us to k new strings.
Produced via deletions.
So we add those all together, and we get
that in the first layer of this tree,
we're going to have 52 k,
plus 26 new strings produced.
Plus the one that we had.
Originally up at the top of the tree.
So that may not seem too bad, but
that's just the first layer of this tree.
Now let's consider searching
deeper in the tree.
What happens if we go down to level two,
to add a distance two?
Well, now we're going to have each of
these 52k plus 26 strings in the first
layer, expand out in the exact same way
as that very first word expanded out.
So for each of the 52k plus 26 strings,
we're going to have another
52k plus 26 strings produced.
And in fact that's a slight
underestimate because our k,
our length of our string,
is actually getting bigger.
Many of those strings in the first
layer are actually 1 longer
than the original string
with started with.
So our k is not just gonna be k anymore.
It's actually going to have
grown to somewhere between k and
k + 1 on the next layer down.
So I'm representing the total
number as 52k plus 26 squared,
but that's actually an underestimate for
the number of strings in the tree.
That's okay, because this number's
gonna get big enough even with
the underestimate, and this makes it a
little bit more simple to do the analysis.
So moving up, what if I want to look
at an arbitrary level in the tree and
layers deep?
Well, when I go n away,
that just changes the power that
I raise that 52k plus 26 to.
Every time I add a layer, I have to
multiply again by the 52k plus 26.
So by the time I get n layers deep in the
tree, and now this is going to be a vast
underestimate for the size of the tree,
I've got 52 k plus 26 to the n.
And anytime you see something that's
to the n you should be very worried.
That's a number that's
going to grow very quickly.
We're not going to be able to
go much deeper than say, four or
five layers deep in that tree
without getting a huge explosion and
way too many possibilities to consider.
So, how are we going
to solve this problem?
There are two possible solutions to making
the solutions to the edit distance problem
faster.
If we want to consider the general
edit distance problem.
Then it turns out this tree based approach
is not the way we would to go
about solving the problem at all.
There's a much faster algorithm, using
something called dynamic programming.
That can solve the general edit distance
problem in order k squared time.
So it's really cool,
it's a great algorithm, and
unfortunately we're not going
to be covering it in this class.
But you will see this algorithm
covered if you take, say,
a computational biology class and you'll
see the general concept of a programming
technique called dynamic programming,
which is really cool.
When you go on to take
a course on algorithms.
But again, it's a bit beyond
the scope of this particular course.
The way we're going to structure the
problem is we're actually going to look
at a slightly different problem that I
mentioned at the very beginning of this
video, which is that we're going
to restrict our edit distance path
to going through real words
in the English language.
So we won't have to
explore this entire tree.
We're going to employ heavy
pruning of this tree.
So what that means is that at each layer,
each level of the tree,
instead of letting it span
out to its full breadth,
we'll remove all the strings that are not
actually words in the english language.
So then this tree-based structure is going
to allow us to solve the problem that we
want to solve, and
it's going to avoid that huge explosion
of possibilities at each level.
So this is the algorithm you'll be
implementing for your project and
you'll be able to solve
this word path problem.