[MUSIC]
This videos going to walk you through
your first programming assignment.
You've already seen what the output of
the entire program is going to look like,
but here we're going to focus
on what you're going to do for
the first module for this first week.
So here we are in
the programming assignment and
what you're going to do is you
going to read all these instructions.
There's a lot here which is why we
going to walk you through what you need to
do very carefully.
So, if you start reading instructions,
the first thing you need to do
is to get everything set up.
So if you haven't already
followed the set up guide
you will want to follow that setup guide.
You can access that setup guide right
here, just clock on this link, or you have
already seen it as a reading if you have
been going through the course in order.
I will want you to follow that
setup guide to get Eclipse and
your starter code all set up even if you
have already worked with Eclipse and
even if you have already worked with Java.
Because there's going to be some
differences between the set up for
this course and the set up that
you might have used in the past.
So it's important that you go to that
set up guide even if you're with us in
the first course and
even if you use the clips and Java before.
Just to make sure you got
everything set up correctly.
Then once you think you've got everything
set up correctly you could verify
that it's all set up by going
over here into a clips.
And then,
running the front end application.
So you can open up the project, which
will be your MOOC text editor project.
Open up the source folder and
then go into the application package.
And you'll find the file
that you're going to
run in order to run that
text editor right here.
It's the main app.
So, Iet's open up main app, and
I'm going to close all the other windows
here so you can just see the main app.
And this is already written for you,
so all you have to do is press run and
you will see the application
run right like that.
And you'll see that if
I type some text Hello.
This is text.
You can see that it doesn't
actually do anything.
So, I type the flesch index and it gives
me a flesch index score of zero which
obviously isn't correct but that's because
we haven't implemented anything yet.
So the load text button is going to work.
But all these other buttons
are not going to do anything.
If I ask for example spelling suggestions,
it's just going to tell me that everything
is misspelled because I don't have
any of my dictionaries implemented.
So I can detect text, I can load text,
I can clear the text, but
that's about all I can do.
So what are you going to be
adding in this assignment?
Well, in this assignment, you are going to
be adding the functionality of that
Flash index score and let's take
a look at how you're going to do that.
You're going to do that by
adding the substarter code, so
we recommend here in step three
that you take a moment or
yourself to the starter code for
this assignment.
And the starter code for this assignment
is document.java and basicdocument.java.
So, let's open those app.
So their found over here
in the document package.
So here's the document package,
I can open up basic documents and
I can open up documents.
And what you'll see when you open up this
two files is that you'll see that their
market are little to do items.
So there are some things that
you need to do in these files.
And I'll talk about what they are as
I walk through the assignment.
So, the first thing, part one,
is you're going to implement the missing
methods in BasicDocument.java.
So what you'll find in BasicDocument.java,
and
we'll look at it in a second,
is that there are a few methods missing.
So the method getNumSentences,
getNumWords, and getNumSyllables,
none of those are implemented at all and
it's your job to implement them.
And the most important piece of this
implementation is that these 3 methods
will be implemented fairly naively in
that it's okay to process the whole
text to count the number sentences
the number of words the number of
syllables every single time
you call these methods.
In fact, it's not only okay,
it's what we want you to do.
But we don't want you to
do this from scratch.
So, let me talk about the code, and
we are actually going to write.
So, let's go to BasicDocument.java,
and if we click on this first todo,
you'll see that the first todo is to
implement the getNumWords method.
This method should return
the number of words in the text
which represents this document.
But you don't want to do this
completely from scratch.
We've actually provided you with this
helper method that you're going to
find extremely useful in
implementing this method.
So if you go over here to Document.java.
You'll see that there's a method
up here called getTokens.
GetTokens is a method that we
mentioned in our videos and
in particular in that support video.
But what getTokens is going to do is it's
going to take a pattern which is a regular
expression and it's going to return
all of the tokens in the document,
in the text for the document that matched.
That pattern.
So, it's a good way to extract all
the words in the document, for example.
You just need to write a pattern
that will match a word.
So, look at the support
video if you get stuck.
There's a support video that really
walks you through how to implement
the three methods that you need
to implement in basic document
using that getTokens method.
So you should be calling that getTokens
method with some regular expression
in getNumWords, getNumSentences,
and getNumSyllables.
Now in getNumWords and getNumSentences,
there won't be much else to do.
If you've got the right regular
expression, the method is almost done.
But in getting syllables
you'll need to do a bit more.
Not only will you need to get the words,
you'll need to count the number
of syllables in each word.
And for that process we're actually
recommending that you implement a helper
method in the document class.
The stub right here that will take
a string representing a word and
return the number of syllables in it.
You'll need to loop through
the characters the word one at a time
to count the syllables.
So that's all for part one, for
the first part of this assignment.
And make sure you read this text
carefully and be very clear
about what constitutes a word, a sentence,
and a syllable using our definition,
because we're going to be grading you
using our definition of words, sentences,
and syllables,
not using whatever you want to use.
It has to be our definition, because
that's what our auto-grader is going
to use when we grade your assignment.
So, once you've got everything working,
go ahead and test your code.
And we've provided a method called Test
Case in the document class, and we've got
some examples of how to cull that method
in the main method inside basic documents.
So take a look at the tests we provide,
add your own,
and get those methods working.
Notice we've got a few hints for
this first part of the assignment here,
so read through those hints they
kind of have talked about what I've
already said in this video.
Then we've got an optional
part which is that you can
make your basic document code work
with the text center application.
By default implementing the methods and
basic document and
then later the flash core which we will
do in part b it's not going to show up.
It's not going to work in that
Text Editor application I just showed you
because currently we use a different
implementation of the documents class for
the Text Editor.
So, if you want to have this first
assignment change how the Text Editor
functions, then what you're going
to need to do is, I'll show you.
You go over here and
you go into the application folder and
into this file called LaunchClass.java.
And in LaunchClass.java you'll see
this method called get document and
we've annotated it with a comment.
You're going to change this line
right here that says return
new document.EfficientDocument.
You're just going to go ahead and
change that to say, basic document.
That's all you need to do.
I'll put it back to efficient.
And then you would put
it back to efficient,
as well, when you go on to next
last week's programming assignment.
So don't forget to do that.
So that's it for part 1.
In part 2 you'll implement
the Flesch score method,
the getFleschScore method
in the document class.
So, all you have to do is go over here
to Document.java and you'll see that one
of these to do is I think this one down
here, says, implement this method.
Right now, the method returns at 0.0
which is obviously is incorrect.
What you wanted to do is you
wanted to return the results of
this calculation here and so, you'll use
your getNumWords, getNumSentences, and
getNumSyllables method in order to
calculate the results of this formula and
then, you just return it.
That's it Once you finished part 1 and
part 2 you're ready to submit.
We do have an optional part 3 for
you which is which is just to have fun
calculating the Flesch readability
score for any text that you want.
So find some text online,
use some of your own text and
set up your text editor application.
Like we talked to you about
before in this video, so
that you can load the code in there and
just see its Flesch readability score.
So there's nothing to submit for part 3.
Just have fun with it.
What you are going to submit is you're
going to submit files for part 1 and
part 2.
You're actually going to
submit the same file.
For part 1 and part 2, so
all you need to do is create a zip file
containing your Document.java and
BasicDocument.java files, so put those two
files into a zip file you call whatever
you like, you need to find those files in
your work space into the direct that you
set up in your computer file system,
and then upload this file twice,
once for part 1 and once for part 2.
We're going to grade different
aspects of these files
in each of these different parts.
Then submit.
And submission will take a little bit but
eventually you'll see some grading
feedback, so if you have any trouble at
all, you can figure out what went wrong.
By running our grader.
We provide you with this grader.
It's in a file called basic
document grader dot Java, and
it's in the document package.
So, just go ahead and
run the grader locally,
figure out what went wrong, fix your code,
and resubmit, until you get it right.
Have fun with this assignment.